<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The royall advocate. Or, An introduction to the magnificent and honourable laws of Jehovah the Lord Christ, now contaminated and despised by the present army-men of this nation. Asserting and controverting the holinesse, righteousness, perfectnesse, and universallity thereof, of divine right: in opposition to the heathenish, and antichristian laws, traditions, and vaine imaginations of the past and present, pretended Christian magistrates of this nation which they yet so much dote upon and endeavour to support, against the alone law giver, lord of heaven and earth, god of gods, king of kings, and lord of lords. / Published by John Spittle-house, now a prisoner for his testimony against the idolatry and tryanny of the present army men, priests, lawyers &amp;c ...</title>
            <author>Spittlehouse, John.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1655</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 232 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 41 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B05943</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S5014</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R184541</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">52614959</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 52614959</idno>
            <idno type="VID">176196</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B05943)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 176196)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2764:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The royall advocate. Or, An introduction to the magnificent and honourable laws of Jehovah the Lord Christ, now contaminated and despised by the present army-men of this nation. Asserting and controverting the holinesse, righteousness, perfectnesse, and universallity thereof, of divine right: in opposition to the heathenish, and antichristian laws, traditions, and vaine imaginations of the past and present, pretended Christian magistrates of this nation which they yet so much dote upon and endeavour to support, against the alone law giver, lord of heaven and earth, god of gods, king of kings, and lord of lords. / Published by John Spittle-house, now a prisoner for his testimony against the idolatry and tryanny of the present army men, priests, lawyers &amp;c ...</title>
                  <author>Spittlehouse, John.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 70, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for the authour, and are to be sold at the Crown in Popes-Head-Alley,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1655.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imperfect: print show-through.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: National Library of Scotland.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Divine right of kings --  Great Britain --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Church and state --  Great Britain --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:176196:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>The Royall ADVOCATE:</hi> OR, An Introduction to the Magnificent and Honourable Laws of Jehovah the Lord Chriſt, now conta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minated and deſpiſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d by the preſent Army<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n of this NATION.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Aſſerting and Controverting the Holineſſe, Righteouſnes, Perfectneſſe, and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſallity thereof, of</hi> Divi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Right: <hi>In oppoſition to the Heathe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iſh, and Antic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>riſtian Laws, Traditions, and vaine imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the paſt and preſent, pretended Chriſtian Magiſtrates of this Na<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>n which they yet ſo much dote upon and endeavour <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>upport againſt the alone Law giver, L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rd o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> heaven and earth, God of Gods, King of Kings, and Lord of Lords.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Publiſhed by <hi>John Spittle-houſe,</hi> now a priſoner for his Teſtimony ag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſt the Idolatry and Tyranny of the preſent Army men, Prieſts, L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>wyers, &amp;c. For the Information of the followers o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Lambe,</hi> now <hi>appearing</hi> as the <hi>Lyon of the tribe of Judah.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Mat. 15. 7, 8. </bibl>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ye</hi> Hypocr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>es, <hi>well did El<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>h propheſie of you, ſaying, This peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple draweth nigh unto m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>h their mouth, and honoureth me with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>heir li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s, but their heart is far from me. But in vain do they worſhip me, teaching for Doctrines the</hi> commandements <hi>of men. (whether in things Civill or Spirituall.)</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>Mat. 23. 13, 14.</bibl>
               <p>
                  <hi>Wo unto you</hi> Scribes, Phariſees, Hypocrites, <hi>for ye ſhut up <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>he</hi> Kingdome of Heaven, againſt men; <hi>for ye neither go in</hi> your ſelves, <hi>nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> ſuffer ye <hi>them that are</hi> entering <hi>to go in:</hi> Therefore ye ſhall receive the greater damnation.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for the Authour, and are to be ſold at the <hi>Crown</hi> in <hi>Popes-Head-Alley,</hi> 1655.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:176196:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:176196:2"/>
            <head>To the now contaminated Saints and Servants of God and (yet faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full followers of the Lamb in this crooked and perverſe generation) under the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the <hi>fifth Monarchy-men,</hi> and enemies of all Magiſtracy and Miniſtry, <hi>with all others whom it may concern.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Dear Brethren and Friends,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THe Providence of God is not unaptly compared to the wheels of a Clock, which albei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> they run variouſly, yet they agree harmoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly to the producing of that end, to which they are appointed; and therefore notwi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hſtanding the affairs of this Nation, have for ſome time had a contrary motion to the general expectation of the people of God, which probably hath been the cauſe of all the flaggings, and ſecret murmu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ings and repinings among them<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> as though the Lord had forgot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten to be gracious, or to perform his peromiſes; yet if we ſearch narrowly into the mind and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ill of Jehovah, we ſhall prove no better by our <hi>incre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulity,</hi> than the Diſciples of our bleſſed Saviour, <hi>Luk. 24. 25. i. e. fools</hi> and and ſlow of heart, to believe all that the Prophets, and the Lord Jeſus and his Apoſtles have ſpoken ſhall come to paſſe in the laſt dayes; as for <hi>inſtance,</hi> the preſent Apoſtacies of the Army, and ſeveral of the <hi>fooliſh</hi> (though) virgin Churches in this Nation, (in point of external ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces) <hi>i. e.</hi> thoſe that have lately ſubſcribed their approbation of this <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Government</hi> we now live under, to be <hi>of God,</hi> and ſuch as ought to be complied with, as the Saints have formerly done to the Governments of <hi>Heathen Potentates,</hi> (without the leaſt conſideration of the <hi>prohibition</hi> which the Lord Jeſus hath made and appointed againſt the worſhip of the <hi>Beaſt</hi> and his <hi>Image,</hi> o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> that receiveth his <hi>mark</hi> in his <hi>forehead,</hi> or in his <hi>hand</hi> or his <hi>Name,</hi> or number of his name, and that under the pain and penalty of drinking of the wine of the wrath of God powred out without mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xture into the cup of his indignation, and that they ſhall be tormented wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h Fire and Brimſtone in the preſence of the holy Angels, and in the preſence of the Lamb, and that the ſmoak of their torment ſhall aſcend up for ever and ever, and that they ſhall have no reſt day nor night, who worſhip the Beaſt and his Image, <hi>&amp;c. Rev.</hi> 14, 9, 10, 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>.) hath doubtleſſe been a great ſtumbling block in the way of Gods people, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o what they are now in expectation of: and therefore to the end that all men may ſee and know, that the preſent Government runs paralel with the Beaſt, and that
<pb facs="tcp:176196:3"/> the ſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>pro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>, (<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>one preſumptuouſly) are guilty of the aforemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> puniſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>s <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>or ſo doing wil appear,</p>
            <p n="1">1. From the ingagement of the Army againſt the late King, and <hi>his Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy,</hi> as one of the ten horns of the Beaſt, guilty of the blood of the Saints.</p>
            <p n="2">2. By the <hi>joynt con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> of thoſe very perſons whom it is to be feared have now preſumptuouſly worſhipped the Image of the Beaſt, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> witneſſe their preaching, praying, faſting and fighting againſt that Government, the image of which they now ſo much hug and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace, and are now grown ſo <hi>ſhamefully impudent,</hi> as to declare the ſame to be <hi>of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. By the <hi>Deſcent</hi> of the <hi>preſent Government</hi> from the fall of <hi>Adam,</hi> i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving run through the veins of all the <hi>Idolaters</hi> and <hi>Tyrants</hi> that have been unto this day, as in the enſuing Treati<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e will appear, and that by the <hi>Teſtimony</hi> of the <hi>Grand</hi> new <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>at<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Doc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>our</hi> of the times Mr. <hi>John Owen,</hi> who hath been very much aſſiſting unto me in the proof thereof, as you will alſo find.</p>
            <p n="4">4. By the clear Teſtimony of Mr. <hi>Tillinghaſt</hi> in his Epiſtle to his late Book titled the <hi>Knowle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> of the times:</hi> ſo that the apoſtacies of the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>named <hi>perſon</hi> and <hi>perſons</hi> (if rightly uſed) may rather conduce to the great advantage of Gods people, and to the ſtrengthening and confirm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the faith and confidence of thoſe that hold faſt their integrity, <hi>i. e.</hi> that the <hi>Great day</hi> of the Lord is at hand, and that judgement is now be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun at the houſe of God, that the Lords fire is now kindled in <hi>Sion,</hi> and his furnace h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ating in <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> that the <hi>Refiners fire is</hi> now melting a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the tinne and droſſe from <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>s jewels, that the Fullers ſope is now ſcowring up the garments of the Saints, making them white and clean <hi>(i. e.</hi> by a pure and unſpotted life and converſation, that they may now be as a City ſet upon the top of an hill, or as a Candle put into a Candleſtick, to give a light to the inhabitants, that they may approve themſelves chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of the light, and of the day, that their light may ſo ſhine before men, that they may ſee their good actions, and ſo be a means to ſtir them up to glorifie their Father which is in heaven) for our bleſſed Saviour hath foretold that it ſhall be in the laſt dayes, or time of his coming to judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as it was in the dayes of <hi>Noah,</hi> Mat. 24. 37. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> at which time it is clear from <hi>Gen.</hi> 6. that there hapned <hi>a very great apoſtacy</hi> in thoſe perſons, who went under the Notion of the ſons of God, <hi>v.</hi> 2. by means of which the ſins of that world became ripe for judgement, every imagination of
<pb facs="tcp:176196:3"/> the thoughts of their hearts being then evil, and that continually, <hi>v.</hi> 5. and therefore ſeeing the ſaid Proph<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſie is now ſo evidently fulfilled before our eyes, both in reference to the Army (onely a <hi>few cordiall and thrice noble Commanders,</hi> who rather than they would become a reproach and ſcandal to what they had ſo publickly declared for, or an occaſion to the enemies of God and his Chriſt to <hi>blaſpheme,</hi> have diſſerted their imployment and commands in the Army, as Major General <hi>Harriſon,</hi> Colonel <hi>Rich,</hi> Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonel <hi>Okey, &amp;c.</hi> and ſome like noble <hi>Heroes now priſoners</hi> for their diſrelliſh of the preſent apoſtaci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s of the army, as Major General <hi>Overton,</hi> Colo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonel <hi>Allured</hi> with ſeveral others upon the like account) as alſo of the now worſe than <hi>Meroſh Churches</hi> afore mentioned, who have been far from helping the Lord againſt the mighty, as that quite contrary-wiſe, they have helped the mighty againſt the Lord, by their new ſtrengthening the hands of the adverſari<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s of the truth, to perſecute the faithfull followers of the Lamb; and therefore to the end, that all that hear or ſhall hear of theſe their <hi>Diabolical actions,</hi> may henceforth learn to take warning by them. I have writ theſe lines, as alſo th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t they may learn with the indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrious B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e to gather hony from that <hi>gall of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>itterneſſe,</hi> and <hi>bond of iniquity,</hi> thoſe poore ſouls have involved themſelves in, by ſuch their con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ederacy againſt Chriſt and his Government, (as by this Treatiſe will appear) as alſo that the faithful witneſſes of the truth may be hereby incouraged to act for <hi>Chriſt,</hi> as the other have done for <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> for <hi>God;</hi> as the other have done for the <hi>Devil,</hi> being <hi>ſuch</hi> as are probably of that number, that will erelong cry, <hi>Lord, Lord, have we not fought in thy name? and conquered in thy name, and preached in thy name, and baptiſed in thy name?</hi> and yet ſhall receive for anſwer, <hi>Depart from me, I know you not, &amp;c.</hi> Such, <hi>whoſe dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation ſlumbereth not,</hi> witneſſe the preſent <hi>Hurlyburlies</hi> among them, all their affairs lying as it were in a Chaos of confuſion, and doubtleſſe will do e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very day more &amp; more, untill his Government be ſet up whoſe right it is <hi>to govern the whole world</hi> by his Holy, Juſt and Perfect Laws and Ordinances contained in the Scriptures of truth, which if once imbraced by the people of this nation, will, I dare be bold to aſſert, free the Inhabitants therof from theſe following burdens and oppreſſions they now (Aſſe-like) ly under, <hi>Gen. 49. 14. 15. i. e.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. Of the charge of a <hi>ſtanding Army,</hi> (and ſo it may be at liberty to fight the Lords battels againſt his adverſaries in forreign parts, upon the Lords <hi>account,</hi> and ſpoil of their enemies, and not like <hi>Drones</hi> to live upon the labours of the induſtrious <hi>Be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> (or High-way-men to rob one another)
<pb facs="tcp:176196:4"/> which at the rate of 120000 pounds <hi>per menſem,</hi> according to the Souldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers Moneth of 28 dayes, will ſave 156000 pounds <hi>per annum,</hi> or nere upon.</p>
            <p n="2">2. From Exciſe, and the vaſt charge thereof.</p>
            <p n="3">3. From Cuſtomes, eſpecially of our own nation, and the great charge thereof.</p>
            <p n="4">4. From the vaſt charge of Lawſuits.</p>
            <p n="5">5. From Tithes, and ſeveral other things of like nature, and therefore worthy to be ſeriouſly conſidered, not onely b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> thoſe, who do <hi>really</hi> and <hi>cordially</hi> deſire the promotion of the <hi>Law of God,</hi> as they do the good of their own ſouls, as do the fifth Monarchy-men (and not of any carnal de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigne, as is falſely ſuggeſted of them by the enemies of the truth) but alſo of the <hi>ſelf-intereſted men [Not that I urge this Royal Law or Government in the leaſt upuon a carnal account, but that carnal men may ſee what benefit there is to be had under the ſhadow of it]</hi> of this nation, who are <hi>in love with their money</hi> in that what one way, what other, it would in a ſhort time <hi>double</hi> their preſent eſtates by ſaving th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſe annual expences, which are ſcrued from them, lit wil alſo concern younger brethen to ruminate hereof; for whereas it is the Cuſtome of this Nation, to make the elder ſon a Gentleman, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and the reſt half beggers, this <hi>Juſt and Righteous Law</hi> doth alot the eldeſt ſon a <hi>double portion,</hi> and the reſt to have all <hi>equal portions,</hi> Deut. 21. 17.</p>
            <p n="6">6. By advancing this law, we do thereby own <hi>Jehovah</hi> to be our God and <hi>Legiſlator,</hi> which now we <hi>cannot,</hi> but are ſuch in a <hi>Civil ſence,</hi> as (the Apoſtle ſaith,) are <hi>without God in the world.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="7">7. By promoting the law, all the <hi>v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſt civil breaches</hi> of this Nation would be made up, for by covenanting to be conformable to this <hi>Government,</hi> we ſhall the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eby be all made <hi>Brethren,</hi> and ſo ſhould forget all former injuries<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and alſo it would be a fair way to make us one in a ſpiritual Relation) which otherwiſe will never be done.</p>
            <p n="8">8. By exalting this law, we ſhall be freed from the <hi>Curſe</hi> which we now lye under, <hi>For curſed is every one that continueth not in the words of the Law to do them,</hi> Deut. 37. 26. and John 7. 49. <hi>This people that know not the Law are ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curſed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="9">9. By magnifying of this Law, we ſhall have Juſtice done ſpeedily, and upon all occaſions, as well upon ſmall as great matters, Judges being ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed in all the gates of the Cities in the Nation. <hi>Deut.</hi> 16. 18. to do Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice and Judgement without wreſting, <hi>Exod. 23. 6. Deut. 24.. 17. without unrighteouſneſſe</hi> Levit. 19. 15. <hi>Without reſpect of perſons,</hi> Deut. 1. 17.</p>
            <p n="10">
               <pb facs="tcp:176196:4"/>10. By ſubmitting to this Law men ſhall not be condemned to <hi>Priſon,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>before they be heard,</hi> Deut. 9. 15. John 7. 51. as is the practice of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Governours of this Nation, and which I can ſpeak by experience, having been formerly kept by their means ſeventeen weeks a priſoner, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving not a word to ſay unto me, either before, or during my impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, being never called before any man, or examined or charged by a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny during that time, or at all, but on<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ly told me I might be gone: and now again, they have alſo kept me fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>teen weeks, knowing not in the leaſt wherefore, not yet having been called or queſtioned before any, ſo that they have been <hi>more cruel</hi> than the <hi>Pagan Romans;</hi> for <hi>Feſtus</hi> thought it a thing unreaſonable, (and conſequently <hi>Brutiſh)</hi> to ſend a priſoner, and not withall to ſignifie the crime laid againſt him, <hi>Acts</hi> 25. 27.</p>
            <p n="11">11. By <hi>exalting</hi> this <hi>Royall Law,</hi> every knowing man may plead his own cauſe, it will be laid down ſo plain, and ſtated ſo clear, in the words of the Text, and therfore needs not to be ſeven years apprentice to <hi>Moſes,</hi> as that blaſphemous <hi>Rabſhakeh, Needham</hi> hath ſcoffingly ſpoken of <hi>Moſes</hi> and the <hi>Law.</hi> Who then that is rational, would not rather forſake thoſe mud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy ſtreams of <hi>Juſtinian, Gratian,</hi> and other blind and ignorant men, (and ſuch as the Prophet ſaith, turneth the needy from Judg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ment, and taketh away the right from the poore, that maketh widows their prey, and rob the Fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>herleſſe, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 10. 2.) for thoſe <hi>pure ſtreams of Juſtice and Judgement</hi> that cometh out <hi>from God,</hi> and riſeth <hi>in him;</hi> who would not, that looks upon himſelf as a <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> rather ſubmit to that judgement that is <hi>Jus Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinum,</hi> than that which is a Traditional <hi>Jus Humanum,</hi> from all the <hi>Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latrous</hi> and <hi>Tyrannical Governours</hi> that have been in the world.</p>
            <p n="12">12. What <hi>Liberty</hi> would this Law bring to this Nation, what <hi>freedome</hi> from <hi>expence,</hi> from unjuſt impriſonment of mens perſons, from being de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived in their cauſes, and from being overborn in their Judg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ments by delay of Juſtice, whereby potent adverſaries have great advantage given them to corrupt Judges, hinder Juſtice, and get falſe witneſſe, many guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty perſons by this means ſcaping unpuniſhed, and many innocent perſons undone (by impriſonments) in their eſtates, families, and repute among men, which would not be done, had we but <hi>Judges,</hi> as at the firſt, and <hi>Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers</hi> as at the beginning of the Common-wealth of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> i. e. <hi>Men fearing God, and hating covetouſneſſe,</hi> and valiant for the truth, to put this <hi>Holy, Juſt,</hi> and <hi>Perfect Law</hi> in execution, not fearing the face of any, knowing
<pb facs="tcp:176196:5"/> that <hi>the Judgement is the Lords,</hi> the accompliſhment whereof, that the Lord would in much mercy haſten, is the earneſt deſire of him, who is now a priſoner at <hi>Lambeth</hi> for the Teſtimony of the truth as it is in Jeſus, which he is ready to vindicate with all that is near or dear unto him.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>John Spittlehouſe.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>Errata.</head>
            <p>REader, the Authour not having had a ſight of this printed Copy be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it was wrought off, throu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h the Correctours negligence, theſe following Errors have hapned, which are not onely very many, but ſome alſo very groſſe, the matter being left out in ſome places, ſo that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out correcting thereof with thy pen, before thou readeſt, it will be trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleſome to underſtand what is printed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Page 3 line 15. read See, and in the Margent r. be, p. 8. l. 29. r. covet, p. 10, l. 2. r. heard, l. 4. r. commending, and in marg. r. were, l. 26. r. hence, p. 11. l. 11. r. hence, p. 11. l 12. r. Reſtauration, and for commanded r. commended, l. 16. r. hence, and in margent againſt l. 25. place figure (4.) p. 12. l. 3. r.</hi> Jam. <hi>p. 14. l. 24. r. whether, l. 31. r. denounced, p. 15. l. 2. r. that they, l. 5. betwixt ſaying and in r. he hath, and betwixt term and that r. affirmed, l 8. r. Civil, l. 3. betwixt many and after r. wiſe, p. 17. l. 5. r. enemy, l. 27. r. over all, 31. r. careth, l, 32. r. then, p. 18. againſt l. 31. place figure (4) in marg, p. 22. l. 1. r. declined, p. 23. l. 20, r. thoſe, l. 28. r. their, p. 24. l. 14. r. quiet, p. 29. l. 36. dele<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> by, p. 32. l. 14. r. it. l. 27. betwixt at and bringing r. the p 39. l. 8. r. thence, p. 40. l 35. r. contrivers. p. 43. l 2. r. a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>pectable. l. 28. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>novel- p 49. l. 29. r. intended, p. 56. l. 1. r. ſuch, l. 15. betwixt of and Nation r. this, l. 36. r judgeth, and betwixt of and Antichriſt, r. the, l. 37. r. his, p. 58. l. 13. r. deſired, p. 62. and l. 31., r. and not that it is.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:176196:5"/>
            <head>THE Royall Advocate, &amp;c. <hi>Aſſerting,</hi>
            </head>
            <div n="1" type="assertion">
               <head> 
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Assert. </seg>1</label> I. <hi>That the Contents of the Royall Law of Jehovah, the Lord Chriſt, was planted in Mankinde by</hi> Nature. </head>
               <p> 
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Proof. </seg>
                  </label> ALbeit our <hi>firſt Parents</hi> were created in the <hi>Image of God,</hi> which conſiſteth in <hi>Righteouſnes</hi> 
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Gen. 1. 26, 27. Epheſ. 4. 24</note> and <hi>true holineſſe;</hi> yet were not they there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by made <hi>Lawleſſe Perſons,</hi> as appeareth from the Teſtimony of the <hi>Apoſtle Paul, Rom.</hi> 2. 14, 15. where he ſaith, <hi>The Gentiles, which have not the Law, do by</hi> Nature <hi>the things contained in the Law, theſe having</hi> 
                  <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>viz.</hi> the written law</note> not the Law, <hi>are a Law unto themſelves, which ſhew the work <note n="*" place="margin">Or, opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or, ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects of the law.</note> of the Law, written in their</hi> Hearts, <hi>their</hi> Conſcience <hi>alſo bearing them witneſſe, and their thoughts, in the mean while accuſing or excuſing one another.</hi> And hence the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle ſaith, I have lived in all good Conſcience before God, Act. 23. 1. vid. 24. 16. 2 Cor. 1. 12. 1 Tim. 1. 5. 19. 2. Tim. 1. 3. Heb. 13. 18. 1 Pet. 3. 16. 21. From which I <hi>Argue,</hi> that ſeeing Mankinde in <note place="margin">The conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence is as a thouſand witneſſes.</note> their <hi>adulterate</hi> and <hi>depraved eſtate,</hi> had the operations of the <hi>Royall Law</hi> of Jehovah <hi>written</hi> in their <hi>hearts by Nature,</hi> as alſo a <hi>Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence</hi> accuſing or excuſing them in point of <hi>obedience</hi> or <hi>diſobedience</hi> thereunto. It muſt needs be, that they had the ſame <hi>much more</hi> in their <hi>Virgin</hi> and <hi>pure eſtate,</hi> when they were in their <hi>Innocency</hi> and <hi>Integrity before their fall.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And this doth <hi>clearly appear</hi> from Gen. 3. 6, 7, 8. Where no ſoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner had our <hi>firſt Parents</hi> violated the <hi>divine precept,</hi> by means of the ſuggeſtions and deluſions of Satan, but immediately their <hi>eyes</hi> are ſaid to be <hi>opened,</hi> and that they <hi>ſaw their nakedneſſe,</hi> and went and ſowed fig-leaves together to make themſelves <hi>Aprons:</hi> As alſo in that aſſoon as they heard the voice of the Lord in the Garden, they went to <hi>hide themſelves</hi> among the Trees of the Garden.</p>
               <p>All which doth clearly <hi>denote</hi> unto us, that their Conſciences had <hi>teſtified</hi> unto them their <hi>diſobedience,</hi> as alſo <hi>condemned</hi> them for what they had done, and therefore they are ſaid to be <hi>afraid,</hi> as in
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:176196:6"/> 
                  <hi>v.</hi> 10. If our Conſcience condemn us, God is greater than our Conſcience, and he ſhall much more condemn us. <hi>Vid. Heb.</hi> 9. 14.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="assertion">
               <head> 
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Assert. </seg>2</label> II. That this <hi>Royall Law,</hi> ſo planted in mankind by <hi>Nature,</hi> is comprehended in <hi>two grand Principles,</hi> i. e.</head>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>To love God above all.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>To love our neighbour as our ſelf.</hi>
               </p>
               <p> 
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Proof. </seg>
                  </label> 
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 6. 4, 5. Hear O Iſrael, the Lord our God is one Lord, and thou ſhalt <hi>love</hi> the Lord thy God, with all thy heart, and with all thy ſoul and with all thy might.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 10. 12. And now O <hi>Iſrael,</hi> what doth the Lord thy God require of thee, but to fear the Lord thy God, to walk in all his wayes, and to <hi>love him,</hi> and to ſerve the Lord thy God, with all thy heart, and with all thy ſoul, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Lev.</hi> 19. 17, 18. Thou ſhalt not hate thy brother in thy heart, thou ſhalt in any wiſe rebuke thy neighbour, and not ſuffer fin upon him. Thou ſhalt not <hi>avenge</hi> or bear <hi>grudge</hi> againſt the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of thy people, but, <hi>Thou ſhalt love thy neighbour as thy ſelf.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I am the Lord.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="assertion">
               <head> 
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Aſſert. </seg>3</label> III. <hi>That this Doctrine was ratified by Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> 
               </head>
               <p> 
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Proof. </seg>
                  </label> 
                  <hi>Mark</hi> 12. 28. Then one of the <hi>Scribes,</hi> (that was a <hi>Lawyer Mat. 22. 35.) coming unto him, and asking him, which was the</hi> firſt Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement <hi>(or</hi> great Commandement in the Law, <hi>Mat. 22. 36.) of all. Jeſus anſwered him: The</hi> firſt <hi>of all the Commandements, (or the</hi> Great Commandement in the Law, <hi>Mat. 22. 38) is,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Hear O Iſrael, the Lord our God is one Lord, and thou ſhalt love the Lord thy God with all thy heart, and with all thy ſoul, and with all thy mind, and with all thy ſtrength.</p>
               <p>This is the <hi>firſt</hi> and <hi>Great Comm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ndement.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And the <hi>ſecond</hi> is like unto it, namely this.</p>
               <p>Thou ſhalt <hi>love thy neighbour as thy ſelf.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There are no other Commandments that are greater than theſe.</p>
               <p>Mat. 22. 40.</p>
               <p>On theſe <hi>Commandements,</hi> hang <hi>all the Law,</hi> and <hi>the Prophets.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="assertion">
               <head> 
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Aſſert. </seg>4</label> IV. <hi>That this Doctrine was taught by the Apoſtles of the Lord Jeſus, under the diſpenſation of the Goſpel-ſtate.</hi>
               </head>
               <p> 
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Proof. </seg>
                  </label> 
                  <note place="margin">The Chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cters of a right <hi>5<hi rend="sup">th</hi>
                     </hi> mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy man.</note> 
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 5. 22. The fruits of the <hi>Spirit</hi> is <hi>Love,</hi> Joy, <hi>Peace,</hi> long-ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering, <hi>Gentleneſſe,</hi> Goodneſſe, <hi>faith,</hi> Meekneſſe, <hi>Temperance,</hi> Againſt which there is no <hi>Law.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:176196:6"/>
               <p>And they that are Chriſts have crucified the fleſh with the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections and luſts thereof, if we live in the Spirit, let us walk in the ſpirit, Let us not be deſirous of vain-glory, provoking one another, envying one another.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Jam.</hi> 2. 8. If ye fulfill the Royall Law according to the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, <hi>Thou ſhalt love thy neighbour as thy ſelf,</hi> thou ſhalt do well; But if ye have reſpect to perſons, ye commit ſin and are convin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced of the Law as tranſgreſſors; for whoſoever ſhall keep the whole Law, and offend in one point, <hi>He is guilty of all.</hi>
               </p>
               <p> 
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>
                  </label> For he which ſaid, <hi>Do not commit Adultery,</hi> ſaid alſo <hi>Do not kill.</hi> Now if thou commit no <hi>Adultery,</hi> yet if thou <hi>kill</hi> &amp;c. thou art be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a tranſgreſſour of the Law.</p>
               <p>1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. 22, 23. Seeing ye have purified your ſelves in obeying the <hi>tr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>th</hi> through the Spirit, unto unfained love of the brethren; ſo that ye love one another with a pure heart, fervently.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Cap.</hi> 3. 8. &amp;c. Be ye all of one mind, having compaſſion one of another: Love as brethren, be pitifull, be courteous: not ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring railing for railing, but contrary-wiſe bleſſing, knowing that ye are thereunto called, that ye ſhould inherit a bleſſing. For he that will love life, and ſee good dayes, let him refrain his tongue from evil, and his lips that he ſpeak no guile. Let him eſchew evil and do good, let him ſeek peace and enſue it. <hi>Read the following words.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>1 <hi>John</hi> 3. 14. We know we have paſſed from death to life, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we <hi>love the Brethren,</hi> v. 27. whoſo hath this worlds goods, and ſeeth his brother hath need and ſhutteth his bowels of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion <note place="margin">Bar Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers in this particular.</note> towards him, how dwelleth the love of God in him. My little children, let us not love in word, neither in tongue but in deed and in truth, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> v. 33. And this is his Commandement, that we ſhould believe on the name of his ſon Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>and love one another,</hi> as he gave us commandement, and he that keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth his commandements dwelleth in him, and he in him, and here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by we know that he abideth in us, by the Spirit which he hath given us.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Cap.</hi> 4. 17. Beloved, let us love one another, for love is of God, and every one that loveth is born of God, and knoweth God; he that loveth not, knoweth not God, <hi>For God is love,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Eccleſiaſtes 12. 13. Let us hear the con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>luſion of the</hi> whole matter, Fear God and keep his commandements, <hi>For this is the whole duty of man,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="assertion">
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:176196:7"/>
               <head> 
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Assert. </seg>5</label> V. <hi>That in proceſſe of time theſe two</hi> generall Principles <hi>were branched by the</hi> alone Law-giver, <hi>into</hi> ten Precepts <hi>or</hi> words, <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly termed the</hi> Decalogue <hi>or Ten Commandements.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Exod. 20. 1. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>God ſpake all theſe words, ſaying,</hi>
               </p>
               <p> 
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Proof. </seg>
                  </label> 
                  <hi>I am the Lord thy God, which brought thee out of the Land of Egypt, and out of the Houſe of Bondage.</hi>
               </p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. <hi>Thou ſhalt have no other gods before me.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. <hi>Thou ſhalt not make to thee any graven Image, or any likeneſſe of any thing that is in heaven above, or that is in the earth beneath, or that is in the water under the earth. Thou ſhalt not bow thy ſelf to them, nor ſerve them.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>For I the Lord thy God am a jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous</hi> 
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>
                     </label> 
                     <hi>God, viſiting the iniquity of the Fathers upon the children, unto the third and fourth generation of them that hate me, and ſhewing mercy unto thouſands of them that love me and keep my Commandements.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3. <hi>Thou ſhalt not take the name of the Lord thy God in vain;</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>For the Lord will not hold him guiltleſſe, that taketh his name in</hi> 
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>
                     </label> 
                     <hi>vain.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>4. <hi>Remember</hi> that thou keep holy the Sabbath day: <hi>Six dayes ſhalt thou labour, and do all thy work, thou nor thy ſon, northy daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, thy Man-ſervant, nor thy maid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervant, nor thy cattel, nor thy ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, that are within thy ga<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>es;</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>For in ſix days the Lord made hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven</hi> 
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>
                     </label> 
                     <hi>earth, the ſea &amp; all that in them is,</hi> and reſted the ſeventh day, wherefore <hi>the Lord bleſſed the Sabbath day</hi> and hallowed it.</item>
                  <item>5. Honour thy Father and Mother,</item>
                  <item>Reaſon, <hi>That thy dayes may be long in the Land, which the Lord thy God giveth thee.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>6. <hi>Thou ſhali not kil.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>7. <hi>Thou ſhalt not commit Adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>8. <hi>Thou ſhalt not ſteal.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>9. <hi>Thou ſhalt not bear falſe wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe againſt thy neighbour.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>10. <hi>Thou ſhalt not covet thy neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours houſe, thou ſhalt not covet thy neighbours wife, nor his Man-ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant, nor his maid-ſervant, nor his ox, nor his Aſſe, nor any thing that is thy neighbours.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="assertion">
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:176196:7"/>
               <head> 
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Aſſert.  </seg>6</label> VI. That the Lord Jeſus came not to deſtroy this Law.</head>
               <p> 
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Proof. </seg>
                  </label> 
                  <hi>Mat. 5. 17. Think not that I am come to deſtroy</hi> the Law, or <hi>the Prophets</hi>—I am <hi>not</hi> come to <hi>deſtroy,</hi> but to <hi>fulfill, (for verily)</hi> I ſay unto you, till heaven and earth paſſe, one jot or one tittle in no wiſe ſhall paſſe from the Law, till all be fulfilled, wherefore, who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever ſhall break one of theſe leaſt Commandements, and teach men ſo, ſhall be called leaſt in the Kingdome of heaven. But whoſoever ſhall do and teach them, ſhall be alſo called great in the Kingdome of heaven.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="assertion">
               <head> 
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Assert. </seg>7</label> VII. <hi>That the Apoſtles of our bleſſed Saviour did eſtabliſh this Law under the Goſpel.</hi>
               </head>
               <p> 
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Proof.  </seg>
                  </label> 
                  <hi>Rom. 2. 11, 12, &amp;c.</hi> For there is no reſpect of perſons with <note place="margin">All the world lia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to be judged by Gods Law The Law not made void through faith.</note> God, for as many as have <hi>ſinned without Law,</hi> ſhall <hi>periſh with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Law,</hi> and as many as have <hi>ſinned in the Law,</hi> ſhall be <hi>judged by the Law.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rom,</hi> 3. 19. &amp;c. Is he the God of the Jews onely, is he not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo of the Gentiles, yea, of the Gentiles alſo, ſeeing it is one God which ſhall juſtifie the Circumciſion <hi>by faith,</hi> and the uncir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion <hi>through faith,</hi> Do we then make void the Law <hi>through faith,</hi> God forbid, <hi>Yea, we eſtabliſh the Law:</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="assertion">
               <head> 
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Assert. </seg>8</label> VIII. <hi>That the Law, which God gave unto</hi> Moſes <hi>in Mount</hi> Sina, <hi>were of three ſorts,</hi> i. e. <hi>the</hi> Moral, <hi>the</hi> Judiciall <hi>and the</hi> ceremoniall <hi>Law.</hi>
               </head>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The Contents of the Morall Law.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The</hi> Morall Law preſcribeth a perfect Rule of righteouſneſſe, <hi>diſcerning things that are</hi> Right and Juſt, <hi>from the</hi> contrary, <hi>both</hi> towards God <hi>and</hi> man, <hi>both in reference to</hi> externall <hi>and</hi> internall duties, <hi>requiring obedience under pain</hi> of everlaſting death.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The Contents of the Judiciall Law.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The</hi> Judiciall Law <hi>belonged to the</hi> Civil State, <hi>and were ſuch</hi> Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances, <note place="margin">
                        <hi>The Judici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all conſiſts of Rules of Equity and</hi> Juſtice.</note> 
                     <hi>as contained</hi> rules of equity <hi>for the</hi> judging <hi>and</hi> deciding of civil controverſies, <hi>and</hi> queſtions, decreeing puniſhments <hi>for the</hi> tranſgreſſions <hi>of the</hi> Morall <hi>and</hi> Ceremonial Lawes, <hi>and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently</hi> the very Bond of them Laws, <hi>keeping the people</hi> in order and Obedience.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:176196:8"/>
                  <head>The Contents of the Ceremoniall Law.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The</hi> Ceremoniall Law <hi>concerned ſuch</hi> Rites <hi>and</hi> ſacrifices, <hi>as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longed to the</hi> externall worſhip of God, <hi>preſcribed to the people of the</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ews, <hi>in reference to the</hi> promiſed ſeed of the woman, <hi>which was to bruiſe the Serpents head, Gen. 3. 14, 15. and to typifie his</hi> coming to this end, <hi>as alſo to</hi> diſtinguiſh <hi>them from other</hi> Nations <hi>in the world, and to be ſignes</hi> and <hi>Symbols</hi> unto them <hi>of the</hi> Spiri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uall graces <hi>of the</hi> New Teſtament, <hi>to be fulfilled by the</hi> Meſſiah.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The Ceremoniall Law utterly aboliſhed.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>As touching the</hi> Ceremoniall Law, <hi>it is</hi> utterly aboliſhed, <hi>ſo that there is</hi> no place <hi>for them</hi> under the Goſpel. Neither can they be <hi>revived</hi> without <hi>derogation</hi> to the Goſpel of Chriſt, as the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle ſaith, if ye be circumciſed, Chriſt ſhall profit you nothing, <hi>Gal. 5. 2. for when the</hi> body <hi>is come the</hi> ſhadow <hi>muſt be done</hi> away, <hi>but the</hi> Cremonies <hi>were</hi> ſhadows, <hi>the</hi> body <hi>is</hi> Chriſt, <hi>Col.</hi> 2. 17.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>Their</hi> Temple <hi>ſignified the</hi> body of Chriſt, <hi>in his Church their</hi> Holy place HEAVEN, <hi>or the</hi> bodies of the Saints, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6. 19. Know ye not that your bodies are the Temples of the Holy Ghoſt, which is in you, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> their ſacrifices <hi>the</hi> paſſion of Chriſt. <hi>Heb. 9. 26. 28. their</hi> expiation <hi>the</hi> Remiſſion of ſinnes, <hi>Heb. 22. &amp;c. theſe things then being</hi> fully verified <hi>and</hi> fulfilled <hi>in</hi> Chriſt, <hi>have</hi> no more place in the Church.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. <hi>Theſe</hi> Ceremonies <hi>ſerved onely for that</hi> carnall people, <hi>which were as</hi> children <hi>kept in</hi> Bondage <hi>under the</hi> Elements and Rudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments <hi>of the</hi> world, <hi>Gal.</hi> 4. 3. But now we are no longer under Tutours and Governours, the time appointed of the father being expired, but are ſet free and redeemed by Chriſt.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. <hi>A third Reaſon for the</hi> aboliſhing of them, <hi>is in reſpect of that people to whom they were preſcribed as</hi> a mark <hi>and</hi> Cognizance <hi>to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcern them</hi> from all other nations. <hi>But now this</hi> diſtinction <hi>alſo being taken away, and the</hi> wall of partition <hi>being</hi> broken down, Jew and Gentile, <hi>being now made</hi> all one <hi>in Chriſt</hi> by faith, <hi>that alſo is</hi> abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed, <hi>which</hi> diſcerned <hi>them from</hi> other people.</p>
                  <p> 
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>4</label> 
                     <hi>For the</hi> Cauſes being changed, <hi>for the which the</hi> Law was made, <hi>there muſt</hi> needs be <hi>alſo an</hi> Alteration <hi>of the</hi> Law it ſelf. </p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The Moral Law remaineth in full force, in point of obedience.</head>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:176196:8"/>
                  <p>The <hi>Moral Law</hi> remaineth yet in <hi>full force,</hi> and is not <hi>abrogated in reſpect of obedience,</hi> which thereunto is <hi>ſtill required</hi> under the <hi>Goſpel.</hi> But in reſpect of the <hi>Curſe</hi> 
                     <note n="*" place="margin">Chriſt hath onely taken away the Curſe and malediction of the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Law.</note> and <hi>malediction,</hi> which Chriſt hath taken away (ſo that it is moſt true which our bleſſed Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our Saith, <hi>He came not to deſtroy the Law but to fulfill it,</hi> Mat. 5. 17, 18 19.) he hath <hi>fulfilled it;</hi> firſt, in his own perſon, in keeping it; 2. in paying the puniſhment for us, which was due by the Law to the tranſgreſſors thereof; 3. inabling us by his grace, to walke in obedience to his Law.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Why it pleaſed God, to give his written Law into the World.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. God did not give the <hi>moral law</hi> in <hi>writing,</hi> in that he was ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>mutable</hi> in changing his <hi>firſt determination,</hi> or that in <hi>proceſſe of time,</hi> he had found out <hi>a more profitable</hi> way then he knew before, as ſome have wickedly objected of old; and now revived by the <note place="margin">The Ranters and Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers Tenent.</note> 
                     <hi>Ranters</hi> and <hi>Quakers</hi> of this Apoſtate Generation, ſaying, that by the <hi>light of Nature</hi> before the Flood, Men diſcerned <hi>good</hi> from <hi>evill, juſt</hi> from <hi>unjuſt,</hi> ſo that the <hi>old world</hi> ſinning againſt the <hi>law of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture</hi> was <hi>juſtly puniſhed,</hi> it being imprinted in their <hi>hearts,</hi> they ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>effects</hi> of that Law written in their hearts, their <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences</hi> alſo bearing them witneſſe?</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſwer.</hi> 1. But becauſe the <hi>law of Nature</hi> was now <hi>much obſcured,</hi> and almoſt <hi>quite obliterated</hi> by reaſon of the <hi>Idolatry</hi> and <hi>Tyranny</hi> that was then ſpread over the earth, which flowed from the <hi>cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption of nature.</hi> Therefore the Lord thought it <hi>needfull</hi> to give it forth by a <hi>Viſible writing</hi> thereof in two Tables of Stone: To his then onely peculiar people, who from that <hi>very cauſe,</hi> was <hi>ſelected</hi> out of the world, <hi>Gen. 17. 1, 2, 4. Exod.</hi> 15. 26. and 20. 2, 3. <hi>Deut.</hi> 5. 1, 2, 3. and 6. 12, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. Leaſt men ſhould complain, that ſomewhat was <hi>wanting in the heart;</hi> therefore to take away <hi>all pretext of ignorance,</hi> the Lord gave his <hi>written Law;</hi> ſo that all men in generall are <hi>left</hi> without <hi>excuſe.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3. Becauſe it was to <hi>prepare</hi> and make way for the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> to ſhew that we have <hi>not ſtrength</hi> in our ſelves to <hi>fulfill the law,</hi> in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference to the <hi>ſpirituall part thereof:</hi> and ſo it was our <hi>Schoolmaſter to bring us unto Chriſt,</hi> Gal. 3. 24.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. It was given as <hi>a ſupply</hi> of the <hi>weakneſs</hi> and <hi>ignorance</hi> of <hi>man,</hi> that whereas there was <hi>no certain rule</hi> before to know what was <hi>good</hi> and what was <hi>evill;</hi> but men according to their <hi>blinde phan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taſie</hi> and <hi>carnal imagination,</hi> placed happineſſe ſome in one thing,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:176196:9"/> and ſome in another, the <hi>written law</hi> was to <hi>correct their erronious opinions,</hi> &amp; to teach <hi>one conſtant</hi> &amp; certain rule of truth and virtue.</p>
                  <p> 
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>
                     </label> For although in <hi>Civill</hi> and <hi>Politick matters,</hi> the <hi>eſteemed wiſe</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Heathen, by their <hi>depraved light of nature</hi> and experience had attained to ſome degree of knowledge therein; yet they were utterly ignorant of the <hi>true knowledge</hi> thereof, and worſhip which God required therein: all which is <hi>explained</hi> in the <hi>law,</hi> with the <hi>ſtatutes</hi> and <hi>judgments</hi> annexed thereunto.</p>
                  <p>So that in doing of this, the Lord is ſaid to commit the <hi>greateſt treaſure</hi> in the world to mankinde, as <hi>Moſes affirmeth, Deut.</hi> 4. 8. What Nation is there ſo great that hath <hi>Statutes</hi> and <hi>judgments</hi> ſo righteous as all the Law that I ſet before you this day.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>
                     <hi>The fourfold uſe of the</hi> moral law <hi>in the fourfold State of man.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>Firſt, As man was <hi>in his creation</hi> and ſtate of <hi>Innocency,</hi> he recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved <hi>two benefits</hi> by the <hi>knowledge of the law,</hi> which was grafted in him <hi>by creation.</hi> For 1. thereby he was made <hi>conformable to the image of God.</hi> And ſo directed, as that he ſhould not have ſwerved from the <hi>will of his creator:</hi> 2. He had <hi>aſſurance</hi> ſo long as he wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked in obedience thereunto of <hi>certain eternity,</hi> never to have taſted of <hi>Death, Corruption,</hi> or <hi>Mutability.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>For he that keepeth the Law ſhall live thereby.</head>
                  <p>Secondly, in Mans <hi>corrupt</hi> and <hi>decayed eſtate, the law</hi> ſerved to <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain the evill,</hi> (i. e. the written Law) and therefore the Apoſtle ſaith, that the <hi>Law</hi> is not given to a <hi>righteous man,</hi> but to a lawleſs and <hi>diſobedient,</hi> 1 Tim. 1. 9. as alſo to <hi>diſcover</hi> unto them their ſins; and hence the ſame Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>without the law ſin is dead,</hi> Rom. 7. 8. <hi>i. e. ſin</hi> was not known to be <hi>ſin,</hi> for ſaith he, <hi>I had not known Luſt, except the Law (i. e.</hi> the written Law) <hi>had ſaid,</hi> Thou ſhalt not commit, <hi>verſ.</hi> 7.</p>
                  <p>Here then that <hi>Soul-deſtroying</hi> notion of <hi>Quakiſme</hi> is confuted, <note place="margin">The Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers opinion confuted.</note> which alloreth men that are in this corrupt and <hi>decayed condition</hi> of nature <hi>(viz. evill</hi> and <hi>unregenerate men,</hi> to look to the light of nature within them, for their guidance and direction, and not to the <hi>revealed will of God,</hi> in his word, or at leaſt rather; notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the Apoſtle doth <hi>poſitively declare all ſuch light</hi> to be abſolute darkneſſe, even darkneſs in the <hi>Abſtract:</hi> As in <hi>Eph.</hi> 5. 8. where he telleth the Church at <hi>Epheſus,</hi> that they had been ſometimes <hi>dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,</hi> and that at ſuch time they walked according as other Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles walked, in the vanity of <hi>their minds,</hi> according to the <hi>courſe of this world,</hi> according to the <hi>Prince of the power of the Aire,</hi> the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:176196:9"/> Spirit that worketh in the children of <hi>diſobedience,</hi> &amp;c. as alſo that they were by <hi>Nature,</hi> i. e. ſince the fall; for it cannot be meant of Nature in <hi>Adam</hi> before his fall, for it was then <hi>good,</hi> and <hi>ſo good,</hi> as that it is termed the <hi>image of God,</hi> (as afore mentioned) <hi>the children of wrath, even as others.</hi> Now I would gladly know, what <hi>light of Nature</hi> theſe Epheſians had, when they <hi>were even</hi> Darkneſſe <hi>it ſelf,</hi> &amp;c. and when they were <hi>without Chriſt,</hi> and <q>ſtrangers from the Covenant of promiſe without hope, and without God in the world.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>If the <hi>Quakers</hi> reply that <hi>Chriſt</hi> is that <hi>Light,</hi> which lighteneth every man that cometh into the world.</p>
                  <p>I anſwer and demand of them, how he had <hi>inlightened theſe Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles,</hi> which the Apoſtle compared the Epheſians unto (as afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid) Again, if <hi>Chriſt</hi> hath inlightned <hi>every man</hi> that cometh in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the world, <hi>in their ſenſe,</hi> then the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> was a <hi>vain-glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious perſon,</hi> who termeth himſelf <hi>a ſpirituall father to the</hi> Corin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thians, 1 Cor. 4. 15. and that he had <hi>begotten them through the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel;</hi> for if the <hi>Light of the Goſpel</hi> had been <hi>naturally in them,</hi> how could <hi>Paul</hi> be ſaid to be <hi>Gods inſtrument</hi> of conveying that <hi>Goſpel-Light unto them.</hi> Again, if ſo, wherefore do theſe perſons make uſe of <hi>Prayer</hi> and <hi>preaching,</hi> if it be not <hi>advantageous to illuminate their Auditors,</hi> and if they be illuminated thereby, then thoſe ſo illuminated, cannot attribute the <hi>Light,</hi> they ſo receive from o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, <hi>to themſelves;</hi> and ſay that they had not received the ſame <hi>inſtrumentally</hi> from their brother <hi>Quakers:</hi> It will therefore <hi>una<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voidably follow,</hi> that the Quakers <hi>practice</hi> doth <hi>deſtroy</hi> and <hi>confound</hi> their <hi>accurſed</hi> Principle, of holding forth that <hi>dark Lanthorn</hi> of the <hi>depraved light of Nature</hi> to light men that are <hi>meerly Naturall</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the <hi>wayes</hi> of <hi>truth</hi> and <hi>righteouſneſſe.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>When one came to enquire of our bleſſed Saviour what he <note place="margin">Jeſus Chriſt was no Quaker.</note> ſhould do to <hi>obtain eternall life,</hi> he did not (as theſe Quakers) ſend him to the Light within him, but asketh him ſaying, <hi>what is written in the Law, how readeſt thou?</hi> Luke, 10. 26, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Again, ſpeaking to the Sadduces, who ſay there is <hi>no Reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction</hi> (and ſo full Couſin germans to theſe <hi>Quakers)</hi> ſaith, that <hi>they erred in not knowing the Scriptures,</hi> Mat. 2. 29. Mark 12. 24. clearly implying that the Contempt of the Sacred Scriptures is the <hi>Originall of Error,</hi> as hath been too evidently made manifeſt by the <hi>Ranters,</hi> who ſince they have deſpiſed the Scriptures, have run themſelves into the very height of wickedneſſe. The Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:176196:10"/> 
                     <hi>Paul</hi> in ſuch caſes doth therefore exhort <hi>Timothy</hi> to <hi>beware of evil men and Seducers,</hi> and to <hi>continue</hi> in the things that he <hi>had read,</hi> and had been aſſured of; knowing of <hi>whom he had learned them,</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">The Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture more holy in <hi>Pauls</hi> eſteem.</note> commanding him in that of a Child, he had known the Holy Scripture, which was <hi>able to make him wiſe unto ſalvation,</hi> through the faith which is in <hi>Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> affirming that <hi>all Scripture</hi> is given by <hi>Inſpiration of God</hi> 
                     <note place="margin"> The excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent uſe of holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</note> , and is profitable for <hi>Doctrine,</hi> for <hi>Reproof,</hi> for <hi>Correction,</hi> for <hi>Inſtruction in Righteouſneſſe,</hi> that the man of God may be <hi>perfect, throughly furniſhed unto all good works,</hi> 2 Tim. 3. 13, 14, 15, 16, 17.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, in mans regenerate condition, the Law or Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, (the goſpel being onely the Spirit of the Law) is a perfect <hi>Rule of righteouſneſſe,</hi> witneſſe the Prophet <hi>David,</hi> who ſpeaking of the <hi>Law of God,</hi> ſaith it was <hi>A Lanthorn to his feet, and a light unto his paths,</hi> Pſal. 119. 105. and Pſal. 19. 7. he ſaith, <q>the Law of God is perfect, converting the ſoul, the teſtimony of the Lord is pure, and enlightneth the eyes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> more to be deſired than gold, yea, than much fine gold, ſweeter alſo than honey, or the honey comb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>; moreover ſaith he, 'by them is thy ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant taught, and in keeping of them there is great reward.'</q> Again, Pſal. 119. 24. <hi>Thy Teſtimonies alſo are my delight and my Counſellours,</hi> by all which it is clear that godly <hi>David</hi> did not run to <hi>a Notion</hi> within him to be his <hi>counſellour,</hi> but to the <hi>Law</hi> and to the <hi>Teſtimony,</hi> knowing that whoſo walketh not according to <hi>that Rule,</hi> it is becauſe they have <hi>no light in them.</hi> Iſa. 8. 20.</p>
                  <p>Again, how it is the Lord threatneth his people, for that they <note place="margin">
                        <hi>A leſſon for the</hi> Ranters <hi>and</hi> Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers.</note> had forſaken his Law, which he had ſet before them, and did not obey this voice, neither walked therein, but walked after the imagination of their own hearts <hi>Jer.</hi> 9. 13, 14, 15.</p>
                  <p>Our bleſſed Saviour alſo telleth his Apoſtles, ſaying, <hi>By this ye ſhall know ye are my Diſciples, if ye obſerve whatſoever I Command you:</hi> he doth not ſend them to the Dictates of their own phan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taſies, but what he had <hi>commanded them.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> alſo affirmeth, that <hi>whatſoever things were written aforetime, were written for our Inſtruction, that we through pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience and comfort of the Scripture might have Hope,</hi> Rom. 15. 4.</p>
                  <p>The Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> alſo exhorteth the people of God <q>to be <note place="margin">Theſe Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments were not Notions.</note> mindfull of the words which were <hi>ſpoken</hi> before, by the <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Prophets,</hi> and of the <hi>Commandements of them the Apoſtles</hi> of the Lord Jeſus, <bibl>2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3. 2.</bibl>
                     </q> as alſo that no <q>
                        <hi>Propheſie of Scripture is</hi>
                        <pb n="11" facs="tcp:176196:10"/> 
                        <hi>of any private interpretation,</hi> and that <hi>Propheſie came not in old time by the will of man, but that Holy men of God ſpake as they were moved by the Holy Ghoſt.</hi> 
                        <bibl>2 Pet. 1. 20, 21.</bibl>
                     </q> We are not then to imitate theſe <hi>Quakers,</hi> to leave a certainty for an incertainty, the written word for a whimſie in the brain, making their phanſies their Scripture and rule to walk by, no ſaith the Apoſtle ſpeaking of the Holy Scripture, <q>as many as walk by this rule, peace ſhall be upon them, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> what will befall ſuch then as <hi>walk not</hi> accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to this Rule, but tribulation and wrath, <hi>&amp;c</hi>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>Secondly, in mans regenerate condition, the written Law teacheth the true knowledge of God, and how it was that the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> commanded the <hi>Bereans,</hi> becauſe they tryed his Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the Touchſtone of the Scriptures, Acts 17. 11. <hi>Thoſe of</hi> Berea <hi>were more noble than thoſe of</hi> Theſſalonica, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Thirdly, it aſſureth a man that walketh therein of his <hi>Election,</hi> and how our bleſſed Saviour ſaith, <hi>If ye know theſe things, happy are ye if ye do them,</hi> John 13. 17. as alſo the Apoſtle <hi>Peter,</hi> 
                     <q>If ye do theſe things, ye ſhall never fall, <bibl>2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. 10.</bibl>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>Fourthly, it ſheweth what benefit we have received by Chriſt, <hi>i. e.</hi> the renewing of that image wherein man was firſt created, (the Scriptures being a <hi>Lanthorn</hi> and <hi>a Light</hi> to that purpoſe, as <hi>David</hi> h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>th acknowledged) Col. 3. 10. <q>Having put on the new man which is created in knowledge, after the image of him that created h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>m.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>In the ſtate of Reformation of all things, the Law ſhall have that uſe which it had before mans fall, to ſhew the conformity of mankind in their holy obedience, with the bleſſed will of their <hi>Glorious Creatour,</hi> Lord and Maſter Jeſus Chriſt, bleſſed for ever, <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Of the Judiciall Law.</head>
                  <p>The <hi>Judicialll Law</hi> floweth from the <hi>Morall Law,</hi> which is the <hi>Fountain</hi> and <hi>Foundation</hi> thereof; and as the <hi>Morall Law</hi> is <hi>fixed</hi> in the <hi>Heart</hi> and <hi>Conſcience</hi> of every man <hi>by nature,</hi> Rom. 2. 14, 15. ſo the <hi>Judicialls</hi> appertaining thereunto, flow from the <hi>ſame Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain,</hi> and therefore ſeeing no <hi>Common-wealth</hi> can ſtand without a <hi>Civil</hi> and <hi>Judiciall Conſtitution;</hi> the Lord therefore having provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the <hi>Law</hi> that <hi>binds in Conſcience,</hi> ſo here he ſets forth the <hi>pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ll lawes,</hi> whereby the <hi>obſtinacy of men</hi> may be <hi>reſtrained;</hi> for if men were left to themſelves, there would be few that would not rather live as they liſt, as the <hi>Ranters,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:176196:11"/>
                  <p>1. Therefore becauſe it might ſo fall out, that <hi>all</hi> would not be <note place="margin">Why the Judicial Law was given.</note> obedient to the <hi>Moral Precept,</hi> it was neceſſary that the alone <hi>Law-giver,</hi> (Rom. 4. 12.) <q>who is onely able to ſave and to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy, to preſcribe what Puniſhment every tranſgreſſour of the Law ſhould be liable unto.</q>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Of the word Judgement.</head>
                  <p>As touching the word <hi>Judgement</hi> in the Singular, it doth not ſignifie as <hi>Judgements</hi> in the Plurall; for <hi>Judgement</hi> in the Singu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar doth for the moſt part ſignifie condemnation, but in the plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall it ſignifies as well the revenge and puniſhment of the guilty, as the defence of the innocent.</p>
                  <p>2. The word <hi>Judgement</hi> is taken three wayes, as firſt it ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s the Act of Judgement and underſtanding, which determineth what is meet and convenient to be done, and ſo it is the fountain and beginning, whence good Lawes do proceed.</p>
                  <p> 
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>
                     </label> 
                     <hi>For the Law is made good out of Judgement.</hi> 
                  </p>
                  <p>So that the <hi>Judiciall Law</hi> is in effect as if the Lord had ſaid un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Moſes,</hi> whereas I have already given the people <hi>Generall Rules</hi> of ſerving me, as alſo how to dem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>an themſelves one towards a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, now upon <hi>a full</hi> and <hi>deliberate conſultation</hi> and <hi>Iudgement given</hi> I ſhall deliver their <hi>particular demeanour</hi> touching the ſame; as alſo the <hi>puniſhment</hi> that ſhall be inflicted upon the <hi>violatours thereof,</hi> whether <hi>towards me,</hi> or towards <hi>one another.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>2. The word Judg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ment is taken for the <hi>Adminiſtration of Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice,</hi> which is the executive part of the Law.</p>
                  <p>3. It is taken for the <hi>Law it ſelf,</hi> according to which <hi>Iudgement i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> given.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>
                     <hi>The</hi> Iudiciall Law of three ſorts.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. They either were ſuch as were annexed to the <hi>Moral Law,</hi> as the ſtatutes and Judgements touching the <hi>Contemners</hi> of the <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Law</hi> in <hi>Generall</hi> or in <hi>particular,</hi> as in <hi>Blaſphemy, Idolatry, Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, Adultery,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Or ſuch as were <hi>appendent</hi> to the <hi>Ceremoniall Law,</hi> as the <hi>Statutes</hi> and <hi>Iudgements</hi> touching <hi>any dead thing,</hi> or that were <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibited</hi> and the like.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Or ſuch as appertained to the <hi>particular Policie and State of</hi> the <hi>Jews Common-wealth,</hi> as concerning the <hi>year of Jubile, raiſing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> ſeed to the brother departed without iſſue, by marrying his wife,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>The two laſt of theſe are aboliſhed, one with the Ceremonies on which they attended, the other as being onely peculiar to
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:176196:11"/> that Government, is now decayed and <hi>determined</hi> with it.</p>
                  <p>The Great Controverſie <hi>now to debate,</hi> is whether the firſt of of theſe, <hi>i. e.</hi> the <hi>Statutes</hi> and <hi>Judgements</hi> annexed to the <hi>Moral Law</hi> be as <hi>Binding</hi> to <hi>all Nations,</hi> as the <hi>Moral Law it ſelf.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>In r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ference to which, I take the <hi>Affirmative part,</hi> and ſay, That the <hi>Judicial Laws,</hi> annexed to the <hi>Moral Law, is as Bind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> as the <hi>Law,</hi> and ought to be put in practiſe by the <hi>Magiſtrates</hi> of ALL the NATIONS <hi>in the whole world.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>This great Argument controverted.</head>
                  <p>It is acknowledged that the Moral Law, is obligatory, uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal, <note place="margin">The Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion.</note> and eternal; for that it is agreeable to the Law of nature commanded by God to <hi>Moſes,</hi> revived and ratified by Jeſus Chriſt in the Goſpel: and therefore may really and truly be termed the Law of Chriſt, and the Royall Law of <hi>Jehovah,</hi> binding ALL NATIONS.</p>
                  <p>But as for the judiciall Law, it ended with the Jews Common <note place="margin">Their Obje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</note> wealth, for which it was intended; and therefore untill it can be ſhewn, when and where it was renued and impoſed upon all Nations Mounſeir <hi>Needham</hi> the Court Parraſite and Penſioner, that ſcoffing <hi>Iſhmaelite</hi> and blaſphemous <hi>Rabſhakah</hi> of the times ſaith he will not believe it.</p>
                  <p> 
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Reſp. </seg>
                     </label> I am glad this Court Sycophant and Temporiſing Paraſite hath ſo much grace as to acknowledge what he hath in reference to the <hi>Royal Law of Jehovah,</hi> i. e. the <hi>Moral Law,</hi> and as touching the other, I anſwer and ſay.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>That the</hi> Judiciall Law <hi>annexed to the Moral Law, is no more ended or determined than the</hi> Moral Law <hi>it ſelf. Neither can be, And that for theſe following Reaſons,</hi> i. e.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. For they are as I have ſaid, <hi>concluſions</hi> and <hi>rules of juſtice,</hi> 
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>13</label> grounded upon the <hi>Morall Law,</hi> or <hi>Royal Law;</hi> and were not ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed to prefigure any thing, but meerly grounded upon the <hi>law of Equity</hi> and <hi>Juſtice;</hi> and therefore can nor ought to be laid aſide any more than thoſe <hi>precepts</hi> of <hi>equity</hi> and <hi>juſtice,</hi> to which they are ſo <hi>inſeparably annexed,</hi> as that the one <hi>cannot ſuffer detriment without the other,</hi> and conſequently neither the law, ſtatute, or judgment, but by an open and apparent contempt of <hi>Jehovah</hi> the Lord Chriſt, the God of <hi>equity</hi> and <hi>juſtice,</hi> who hath <hi>eſtabliſhed</hi> and <hi>ratified</hi> them to be his <hi>laws</hi> to ſuch purpoſe, and ſo not judaicall, or peculiar onely to the Jews, but to all that are under the verge of the <hi>Moral Law.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <pb n="14" facs="tcp:176196:12"/>2. For that the <hi>breach</hi> of the <hi>Moral Precept,</hi> (or Law is the <hi>ſame</hi> before the <hi>alone Law-giver)</hi> in <hi>one part of the world,</hi> as in <hi>ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> as to <hi>kill a man wilfully,</hi> or by <hi>Accident,</hi> is now the <hi>ſame ſin</hi> before the eyes of God in <hi>England,</hi> as it was then in <hi>Canaan,</hi> and conſequently of any other tranſgreſſion of the <hi>Moral Precept;</hi> and therefore in ſuch caſes, the great and <hi>ſingular Law-giver</hi> hath de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared that <hi>one Law</hi> ſhould be for the ſtranger, <hi>(i. e.</hi> the Gentile) as for the home born, (or Jews themſelves) Exod. 12. 49. Lev. 24. 22.</p>
                  <p>And therefore unleſſe this <hi>Changeling,</hi> will undertake to prove <hi>Iehovah the Lord Chriſt,</hi> ſuch an one as <hi>himſelf,</hi> as to prefix <hi>one puniſhment</hi> in <hi>Canaan</hi> for the violation of <hi>a Moral Precept,</hi> (whether <hi>General</hi> or <hi>particular)</hi> and <hi>another ſort of puniſhment</hi> for the <hi>ſame Tranſgreſſion</hi> in <hi>another Country,</hi> as in <hi>England,</hi> &amp;c. (which blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Aſſertion he is as like to maintain as any I know, <hi>for a Sti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pends ſake)</hi> he cannot avoid, but muſt <hi>per Force</hi> ſubſcribe, that the ſaid ſtatutes and Judgements, are of as large an extent, as the <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ral Law it ſelf</hi> acknowledged by him, <hi>i. e.</hi> Obligatory, Univerſal and Eternal, and Binding all Nations.</p>
                  <p> 
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>2</label> All Nations have a latitude left them of making ſuch Civil Laws as they ſhall think convenient, for the <hi>better Government</hi> of themſelves, according to Prudence and Diſcretion, provided they be not contrary to that Royal Law.</p>
                  <p> 
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Reſpon. </seg>
                     </label> 
                     <hi>Prag.</hi> I here <hi>challenge thee,</hi> and <hi>all thy Maſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>s,</hi> which in <hi>Court, City,</hi> or <hi>Country, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſities</hi> or <hi>Innes of Court,</hi> by what <hi>names</hi> or <hi>titles</hi> ſo ever, <hi>dignified</hi> or <hi>diſtinguiſhed,</hi> to ſhew me <hi>one Text of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture</hi> that granteth <hi>any ſuch latitude</hi> to Magiſtrates, by the alone <hi>Law-giver,</hi> as they are (or ought to be) his <hi>Miniſters</hi> or <hi>ſervants,</hi> to put <hi>his Laws in execution,</hi> but contrary-wiſe ſuch Actions are ſo <hi>abominable</hi> in the eyes of Jehovah the Lord Chriſt, as that he hath denoted a <hi>curſe</hi> againſt thoſe that <hi>do take upon them,</hi> either to <hi>adde</hi> or <hi>detract,</hi> that either <hi>ſwerve</hi> to the <hi>right hand</hi> or <hi>the left,</hi> from thoſe <hi>Laws, Statutes</hi> and <hi>Iudgements</hi> preſcribed by him: for proof hereof ſee <hi>Deut. 27. 26. Gal.</hi> 3. 10. No <hi>Monſieur, Prag.</hi> thoſe that are <hi>Diſpenſers of Iehovahs lawes,</hi> muſt not make <hi>Laws for him,</hi> whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in reference to <hi>Statute</hi> or <hi>Iudgement,</hi> he is as able to <hi>preſcribe</hi> his <hi>puniſhment,</hi> as his <hi>Law,</hi> without their <hi>help</hi> or <hi>aſſiſtance.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And therefore it was that our bleſſed Saviour ſo much inveigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed againſt the Scribes, Phariſes, hypocrites, of his time of abode here on earth, (like unto <hi>Needhams</hi> forementioned Maſters)
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:176196:12"/> for that they had not onely tranſgreſſed the <hi>Commandements of God,</hi> by their <hi>vain Traditions,</hi> (or Expoſitions) but he had <hi>even</hi> made them thereby <hi>of none effect,</hi> Mat. 13. 3, 4, 5 <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>So that I <hi>affirm</hi> that <hi>Clauſe</hi> in <hi>Needhams</hi> Objection, <hi>(i. e.) For the better Government,</hi> &amp;c. to be <hi>abſolute blaſphemy,</hi> for that by ſo ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in <hi>plain terms,</hi> that his (aforeſaid Maſters, are Wiſer than the <hi>Great God of Heaven and Earth, in reference to the compoſing of all Government for the ſonnes of men;</hi> and therefore according to the <hi>Statute</hi> and <hi>Iudgement</hi> appropriated by <hi>Iehovah</hi> in <hi>ſuch Caſes</hi> he ought to be put to death, <hi>vid.</hi> Lev. 24. 11. 15. 23. as alſo for his <hi>ſcurrilous expreſſions</hi> againſt <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>the Laws,</hi> given by God un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him to communicate to the people; for he that deſpiſed <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe's</hi> Law, was to <hi>dye without mercy,</hi> under the teſtimony of two or three witneſſes, which Judgement will doubtleſſe fall upon the heads of <hi>Needham, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>In ſo ſaying, he clearly giveth the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> the lye, who aſſerteth, <hi>That the fooliſhneſſe of God is wiſer than the wiſdome of men, 1. Cor.</hi> 1. 25. The meaneſt of the <hi>Divine Orders,</hi> being far beyond the <hi>wiſeſt</hi> of <hi>his</hi> or his <hi>Maſters vain imaginations:</hi> ſo that by ſuch their <hi>deceived fooliſh hearts,</hi> they onely contract to themſelves that <hi>Heatheniſh Character,</hi> i. e. <hi>by profeſſing themſelves <note n="*" place="margin">Rom. 1. 2, 2.</note> wiſe, to be Down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right Fooliſh;</hi> for in ſuch Caſes the Apoſtle doth <hi>poſitively affirm,</hi> that <hi>the wiſdome of the world, (viz.</hi> Athenian like Wiſdome) <hi>is fooliſhneſſe to God; for it is written, I will deſtroy the wiſdome of the wiſe</hi> (whether in Civil or ſpirituall matters) <hi>I will bring to nought the Councels of the prudent. Where is the wiſe? where is the Scribe? where is the diſputer</hi> (or <hi>Needhams) of this world? hath not God made</hi> Fooliſh <hi>the</hi> Wiſdome (or <hi>politick carnal wiſdome)</hi> of this World? and therefore he concludeth, that <hi>not many after the fleſh, not many mighty, not many noble, are called by God</hi> to be <hi>made Inſtruments in his work or ſervice</hi> (whether in Civils or Spiritualls) but contrary<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe hath made choice of that which is Fooliſh in the eſteem of <hi>Needham</hi> and his Maſters (whether in reference to perſons or things) <hi>to confound that which they eſteem wiſdome, that no fleſh might glory in his preſence,</hi> vide Rev. 27, 28, 29.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. I doe therefore hereby <hi>affirm,</hi> that God that <hi>gave life</hi> and <hi>limbs</hi> unto men, &amp;c. hath <hi>onely power to diſpoſe of them,</hi> and <hi>none elſe;</hi> and that he that <hi>taketh away</hi> either the <hi>life</hi> or <hi>limb</hi> of any man, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther wiſe than God himſelf hath appointed, or given direction (in the <hi>holy Scriptures</hi> of the Old and New Teſtament) either by
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:176196:13"/> 
                     <hi>general rule,</hi> or particular <hi>precept,</hi> is a <hi>Murtherer</hi> and a <hi>Tyrant.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. I do alſo hereby affirm, that whoſoever <hi>doth not</hi> take away <hi>life</hi> or <hi>limb,</hi> in ſuch caſes as the <hi>alone law-giver</hi> hath appointed is <hi>an unjuſt Judge.</hi> And that he will be puniſhed by Jehovah the Lord Chriſt for ſo doing:</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Reaſon,</hi> For he hath ſaid <hi>Yee ſhall do no unrighteouſnes in judgment, thou ſhalt not reſpect the perſon of the poore, nor honour the perſon of the mighty, Levit.</hi> 19. 15.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>But in Righteouſneſſe ſhalt thou judge thy Neighbour.</head>
                  <p>(A text that ere long may be urged againſt thoſe that have ur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged it againſt others, <hi>vid. Abridg. Remonſt. Albans pag.</hi> 10. with ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall other ſcriptures to ſuch purpoſe.) And hence it was, that <hi>Moſes</hi> charged the Judges of Iſrael, ſaying, <hi>Heare the cauſe between your brethren and judge</hi> Righteouſly, <hi>between every man and his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and the ſtranger that is with him; and yee ſhall not reſpect perſons in Judgment, but yee ſhall heare the ſmall as well as the great, you ſhall not be afraid of the face of man,</hi> Deut. 1. 15, 16, 17.</p>
                  <p>Reaſon, <hi>For the judgment is Gods.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>3. That in all <hi>other caſes,</hi> the Magiſtrate being the Miniſter or ſervant of God (or at leaſt ought ſo to be) Rom. 13. 4. ought to <hi>execute juſtice,</hi> as the alone Law-giver their Lord and Maſter hath <hi>preſcribed,</hi> which they cannot do otherwiſe than by <hi>putting his laws in execution,</hi> according to thoſe <hi>ſtatutes</hi> and <hi>judgments</hi> eſtabliſhed by God himſelf (and not according to thei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>own luſts</hi> and <hi>humours,</hi> as our preſent Magiſtrates do at this day, puniſhing ſeverall things <hi>by death,</hi> which the alon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Law-giver hath appointed other <hi>puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments;</hi> and ſeverall things with other puniſhments, for which the alone Law-giver hath <hi>appointed death.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Reaſon.</hi> For it is required in a <hi>diſpoſer,</hi> that he ſhould be <hi>found faithfull, 1 Cor.</hi> 4. 2.</p>
                  <p>But Gods will otherwiſe appeareth not, then <hi>in his word or law.</hi> Therefore who ſo doth not <hi>accordingly,</hi> doth not perform the will of the alone Law giver, in his word or Law, and conſequently of the number of thoſe Magiſtrates mentioned by <hi>Solomon</hi> in his book titled <hi>Wiſdome, cap.</hi> 6. 1. to whom he ſaith, by way of <hi>rebuke</hi> and <hi>admonition,</hi> Heare therefore O yee Kings and underſtand, learn ye that be <hi>Judges</hi> of the ends of <hi>the earth;</hi> give ear you that <hi>rule the people,</hi> and <hi>glory</hi> in the <hi>multitude of Nations,</hi> for <hi>power is given you of the Lord, and ſoveraignty from the higheſt,</hi> (i. e. the Conſtitution of Authority or Magiſtracy, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. 3, 4. and that according to
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:176196:13"/> the Armies own conſtruction of that place, in their <hi>Abridgment</hi> of the <hi>Remonſtrant Albans,</hi> wherein pag. 6. they ſay, that <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks in that place of Authority, <hi>&amp;c. Magiſtracy in its conſtitution,</hi> not of <hi>a Perſon abuſively exerciſing it to</hi> be Gods inſtrument of Good to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very one, and an <hi>incourager of good in every man,</hi> and an envying to evill) who will try your work (or pollicy) and ſearch out your Counſel: then Counſellours look to your ſelves, you had need then to treble your guards about you.</p>
                  <p> 
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>
                     </label> Becauſe being Miniſters of his Kingdom: (the Kingdome will be then found to be the Lords, and not theirs, who are now Uſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers both over it, and the Lords Goverment, which he hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed for it) ye have not judged right, (wherein have they not <hi>judged right,)</hi> nor kept the Law? What will become of thoſe Magiſtrates then that have neither kept the Law, <hi>i. e.</hi> that have not <hi>judged according to the Law</hi> of the <hi>alone Law giver;</hi> neither have judged according to their own <hi>Laws,</hi> ſurely the following judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment will fall with a Witneſſe upon ſuch Magiſtrates.) Nor walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed after the Counſel of God (no nor of <hi>good men</hi> neither, but of a company of <hi>fawning Parraſites,</hi> the <hi>Frogs, Locuſts, Caterpillars,</hi> and <hi>Cankerworms of Nations)</hi> horribly and ſpeedily will he come upon you: For a ſharp judgment ſhall be to them that are in high pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, for mercy will pardon the meaneſt (ſuch as may not proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be termed the <hi>makers and judges of Heatheniſh Laws,</hi> i. e. <hi>the petty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foggers of the Laws and governments of man,</hi> i. e. ſuch as are not <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſionated</hi> to ſuch purpoſe) but mighty men ſhall be mightily tormented.</p>
                  <p> 
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>
                     </label> For he that is <hi>Lord Oneral</hi> ſhall fear <hi>no mans perſon</hi> (How?) not the perſon of <hi>O. P. &amp;c.</hi> Neither ſhall he ſtand in aw of any mans greatneſſe (but ſure he dare not meddle with <hi>his Highneſſe,</hi> that is, a degree above <hi>greatneſſe)</hi> for he hath made the <hi>ſmall</hi> and <hi>great,</hi> and <hi>earth for all a like,</hi> (how, for <hi>all alike?</hi> thats a <hi>ſtrange ſaying indeed,</hi> ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, the Lord will be <hi>a leveller with a witneſſe)</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>But a ſore tryall ſhall come upon the mighty:</hi> Let her alone un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till that day, The <hi>Fox</hi> fares b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſt when he is threatned moſt. Theſe are but <hi>Bug-bear-expreſſions</hi> to <hi>frighten children,</hi> valiant <hi>Heroes</hi> fears them not, <hi>me vive fiat,</hi> ſaith <hi>Nero</hi> and his Comrades, <hi>let this day of judgment come in their time,</hi> ſo much do they fear it; <hi>tuſh,</hi> they are onely mock-beggers, and ſcar-crows, they ſee by reaſon and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:176196:14"/> that all things <hi>continue</hi> as they were <hi>from the beginning of the Creation,</hi> let a company of <hi>dreaming Prophets</hi> ſay what they will, doth God take notice of idolatry or <hi>Tyranny,</hi> as the ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple vulgar term it? <hi>Tuſh,</hi> he ſeeth no ſuch thing, there is <hi>no ſuch knowledge in the moſt high,</hi> and if he do know, yet doubtles he <hi>hideth away his face, and will not ſee it;</hi> For ſurely otherwiſe he would not have ſuffered it ſo long to have been practiced as he hath done; a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way therefore with all ſuch Fancies, and let us look after our <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent work</hi> to ſuppreſſe ſuch <hi>ſawcy inſolent fellows,</hi> that dares to <hi>cite ſuch Treaſonable Texts,</hi> to the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nd they may <hi>affright us.</hi> What! doth not our <hi>Prognoſticatours tell us,</hi> that <hi>our</hi> Government is permanent, and will not admit of <hi>alteration</hi> for many <hi>hundreds of years?</hi> what then ought we to give heed to <hi>ſuch bablers.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Unto you <hi>O Kings</hi> (ſaith <hi>Solomon)</hi> do I ſpeak, that <hi>Ye may learn wiſdome,</hi> and <hi>not fall away.</hi> (How now <hi>Solomon,</hi> do <hi>you</hi> give us this <hi>Counſel,</hi> ſurely this book was made when you were in your <hi>do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling condition,</hi> when you began to have <hi>one leg in the grave,</hi> it was not ſo with you when your <hi>Government laſhed your brethren,</hi> as with <hi>whips,</hi> when your proviſion for one day, was thirty mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of fine floure, and threeſcore meaſures of meal, ten fat ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en, and twenty oxen out of the paſture, beſides Harts, and Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bucks, and Fallow-deere, and fatted fowl, when you had for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty thouſand ſtalls of horſes for your Chariots, and twelve thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand horſemen; when you had ſeven hundred wives, and three hundred concubines: No, this was when you began to <hi>ſurfet</hi> of your <hi>pleaſures,</hi> and therefore to cry <hi>all is vanity</hi> and <hi>vexation of ſpirit,</hi> well, when we have <hi>taken our fill of pleaſure as you did,</hi> we ſhall peradventure take your adviſe, in the mean time give us leave to <hi>ſatisfie the luſts of our own hearts,</hi> and if not, know, we will take leave, and ſo farewell <hi>Solomon.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Seeing that which is not of <hi>of faith or firm perſwaſion</hi> is ſin, <hi>Rom.</hi> 14. 23. and <hi>faith</hi> muſt be <hi>grounded</hi> upon the <hi>Word,</hi> as being wrought by the Word, <hi>Rom.</hi> 10. 16, 17, 18. The Magiſtrate can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not juſtifie his <hi>Acts of Juſtice in the ſight of God,</hi> unleſſe he can <hi>warrant the ſame from the word of God:</hi> and what word is there for taking away the life of a man for <hi>ſimple theft,</hi> &amp;c. with ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral other things now acted by the <hi>preſent Magiſtrates</hi> of this Nation, as I ſhall undertake to prove, if ever providence call me thereunto.</p>
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:176196:14"/>
                  <p>5. In as much as God hath <hi>created man</hi> in his <hi>own Image,</hi> Gen. 1. 26. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which <hi>Image</hi> is in <hi>Mans Soul, animating his body:</hi> This <hi>Image</hi> I ſay, ought not to be <hi>defaced</hi> and <hi>diſſolved,</hi> but by <hi>warrant</hi> and <hi>direction</hi> from the <hi>word of God,</hi> and conſequently in <hi>all other Caſes,</hi> where the <hi>Great Law-giver</hi> hath as well <hi>preſcribed the Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> as the <hi>Offence,</hi> i. e. the <hi>judgement</hi> or <hi>puniſhment,</hi> as the <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept</hi> or <hi>Statute,</hi> and that who ſo doth not ſo, is a <hi>Rebell</hi> and <hi>Traitor</hi> to the <hi>alone Law-giver,</hi> whoſe ſervant he <hi>ought to be in all faitfulneſſe,</hi> and not an <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurper</hi> of his <hi>Maſters Authority</hi> or <hi>Legiſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torſhip,</hi> as our <hi>preſent Magiſtrates are at this day.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p> 
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
                     </label> 
                     <hi>Mordecay</hi> and <hi>Daniel,</hi> having place of Government under the <hi>Babyloniſh</hi> and <hi>Perſian</hi> Kings, did no doubt adminiſter Juſtice ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Laws and Cuſtomes of that Country.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Therefore the Laws of the Heathens were aſſented unto by godly perſons.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p> 
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Reſp. </seg>
                     </label> The Caſe is now <hi>far different,</hi> for thoſe <hi>Emperours</hi> or <hi>Kings</hi> were <hi>Heathen,</hi> but the <hi>preſent Magiſtrates</hi> of <hi>this Nation,</hi> are at leaſt in pretence <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> and therfore for them (above all other) to act <hi>by</hi> and <hi>according</hi> to thoſe <hi>Heatheniſh Laws and Cuſtomes</hi> doth render them <hi>to be Worſe than the very Heathen.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p> 
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>
                     </label> For the <hi>Heathens</hi> did <hi>make</hi> and <hi>act</hi> by ſuch <hi>Laws,</hi> meere<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y out of <hi>blind ignorance, Acts</hi> 17. 30. and therefore God is ſaid to <hi>wink thereat,</hi> but ſince hath commanded <hi>All Men every</hi> 
                     <note n="*" place="margin">None then can plead excuſe.</note> 
                     <hi>where</hi> to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent of ſuch their <hi>wickedneſſe,</hi> becauſe he hath Appointed a day in which he will <hi>Iudge the World</hi> in <hi>Righteouſneſſe,</hi> which can be done by <hi>no other,</hi> than his <hi>own Holy, Iuſt, perfect and Righteous Laws,</hi> by the <hi>Man</hi> whom he hath <hi>ordained, &amp;c.)</hi> but the preſent Magiſtrates of this Nation, or <hi>Supreme power,</hi> which I take (with Mr. <hi>Feak)</hi> to reſide in the <hi>Army</hi> or Chief Officers thereof, they do it Preſumptuouſly, witneſſe their <hi>Declarations, Remonſtrances,</hi> &amp;c. in which they have <hi>Notoriouſly proclaimed</hi> to <hi>All the World,</hi> that they have fought to ſet up <hi>the Lord Ieſus Chriſt</hi> to be <hi>King</hi> or <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſlator</hi> in this <hi>Common-wealth,</hi> as alſo <hi>vowed obedience</hi> unto him up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his Own Terms, and that they would <hi>admit</hi> Him Onely to the exerciſe of his <hi>Royall Authority,</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>and in order thereunto have <hi>affirmed,</hi> that the Law that was put into the hands of <note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>which was no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than the ſtatutes and judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pending <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>pon the Moral Law</hi> Deut. 17, 18, 19.</note> 
                     <hi>Ioaſh</hi> at his <hi>Coronation,</hi> to be a <hi>Law from heaven,</hi> as alſo a <hi>Rule for all Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers,</hi> and that whoſoever is not under thoſe Laws, owns not
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:176196:15"/> his <hi>Subjection</hi> to God. So that what the Apoſtle ſaith of the <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then,</hi> Rom. 1. 21. <hi>i. e.</hi> (That when they knew God, they did not worſhip him as God, but became vain in their imaginations, their fooliſh hearts being darkened, and ſo profeſſing themſelves wiſe became fools, and thereby left themſelves without ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe) I may fitly apply to the late actions of theſe <hi>Army men,</hi> yea, and that in a <hi>Greater meaſure,</hi> in reference to the Law of God; <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon. </seg>
                     </label> For in this particular <hi>Iehovah</hi> hath not afforded <hi>many of the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then that priviledge,</hi> as to have either the <hi>Letter</hi> or <hi>true ſence</hi> of the <hi>Law,</hi> Rom. 2 14. But <hi>theſe perſons</hi> have both the <hi>Letter</hi> and <hi>true ſence of the Law,</hi> and yet <hi>wilfully refuſe to put them in practice,</hi> and conſequently <hi>receive this great grace and favour of God in vain,</hi> chu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing <hi>rather</hi> with <hi>Turks</hi> and <hi>Infidels,</hi> to be a <hi>Law unto themſelves.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And what is this <hi>leſſe</hi> in a <hi>Civil Sence,</hi> than the <hi>Quakers</hi> and <hi>Ranters Tenent</hi> in a <hi>Spirituall Sence,</hi> the <hi>one</hi> thinking they have <hi>No need</hi> of the <hi>Touchſtone rule,</hi> or <hi>Standard</hi> of the <hi>Scriptures</hi> of the <hi>New Teſtament,</hi> to guide them in their <hi>Spiritual condition,</hi> or <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Man,</hi> living meerely upon the <hi>dictates, figments</hi> or <hi>Notions</hi> of the <hi>wild Fancies</hi> of <hi>their frisking brain.</hi> The other that they have likewiſe, <hi>Reaſon and light of nature enough within them</hi> to govern <hi>themſelves</hi> and their <hi>Vaſſals</hi> in reference to the <hi>outward man,</hi> and therefore like the other, will not make uſe of the <hi>Old Teſtament,</hi> for that purpoſe, but eſteem them as things <hi>baſe</hi> and <hi>deſpicable</hi> for ſuch wiſe and Profound Perſons, as Mr. <hi>Needham</hi> and his <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters,</hi> the now great Courtiers are.</p>
                  <p>And thus betwixt them do they <hi>compleat</hi> that Body of Iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and <note n="*" place="margin">And have filled up the meaſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e of the wrath of their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſſours in iniquity<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently ripe for judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ch ſleepeth not.</note> Tranſgreſſions, and therefore with the <hi>Heathen</hi> may properly be ſaid to be without Law, and without God in the World, and conſequently at the very <hi>threſhold</hi> of entring into that unpardonable ſin againſt the Holy Ghoſt, which is defined to be a reſiſting of the <hi>known truth,</hi> which can be no other than the Holy Scriptures of the <hi>Old and New Teſtament,</hi> not of <hi>infirmity,</hi> or for <hi>fear</hi> or <hi>favour,</hi> but of <hi>more Malice</hi> and <hi>Hatred</hi> againſt the <hi>writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten Word,</hi> i. e. the LAW and the Goſpel (the one <hi>trampled under foot</hi> by the <hi>Ranters</hi> and <hi>Quakers,</hi> and the other deſpiſed and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temned by <hi>Need<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>am</hi> and his <hi>Maſters,</hi> witneſſe his <hi>ſcurrilous pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phlet, tituled the Obſervator)</hi> notwithſtanding they are the <hi>very di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctates of the Spirit of God to</hi> Moſes, <hi>the Prophets and Apoſtles,</hi> as I have proved.</p>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:176196:15"/>
                  <p>And therefore ought to be of as <hi>much value and eſteem among</hi> the <hi>people of God,</hi> as if the <hi>ſame words were now inſpired into them by the ſame Spirit:</hi> ſo that by having the benefit of the <hi>Holy Scriptures,</hi> it is as much as if we had <hi>Moſes and all the Prophets,</hi> with <hi>Ieſus Chriſt</hi> and his <hi>Apoſtles</hi> now Extant with us, <hi>with all the Miracles which were wrought by them</hi> for the <hi>Confirmation thereof,</hi> John 20. 31. and conſequently do thereby injoy <hi>God, Chriſt</hi> and <hi>the bleſſed ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits breathings,</hi> as if the <hi>ſame were now breathed upon us,</hi> in reference to our <hi>guidance</hi> and <hi>direction in the duties required of us by God,</hi> either as to <hi>himſelf</hi> or <hi>our Neighbour,</hi> ſo that where it is <hi>propheſied,</hi> that in <hi>the latter dayes, we ſhall be all taught of God,</hi> I affi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>m, it is meant of <hi>no other teaching,</hi> than that of the <hi>Old</hi> and <hi>New Teſtament</hi> which ſhall then be the <hi>Onely Rule and Square of our Actions,</hi> whether in reference to <hi>things ſpirituall</hi> or <hi>Civil;</hi> for it cannot be other than <hi>Blaſphemy to aſſert,</hi> that the <hi>bleſſed ſpirit</hi> ſhould <hi>teach Contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictions,</hi> to teach <hi>one Rule in Scripture,</hi> and <hi>another Rule in Notion,</hi> and if ſo, then <hi>all Notions whatſoever</hi> theſe Ranters, Quakers, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> pretend unto, which are <hi>not as agreeable</hi> with the <hi>Letter of the Scriptures,</hi> as a pair of <hi>Indentures</hi> agreeth with one <hi>another,</hi> and even as <hi>face</hi> anſwereth <hi>face in a glaſſe,</hi> I ſay, and <hi>do teſtifie</hi> that they are of their <hi>Father the Devil.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And therefore the words of the Apoſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e, may fitly be applyed to theſe men, <hi>Heb.</hi> 4. where ſpeaking of ſuch as <hi>were once inlight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and have taſted of the good word of God, and the power of the world to come,</hi> ſaith, that <hi>it is</hi> impoſſible <hi>for ſuch if they ſhall fall away, to be renewed again by Repentance, ſeeing they have crucified to themſelves the Son of God, and have put him to an open ſhame,</hi> as alſo thoſe words in <hi>Cap. 10. 26, 27, &amp;c.</hi> where he ſaith, <hi>If we ſin wilfully after we have received the knowledge of the truth, there remaineth no more ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice for ſin, but a fearfull loo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ing for of Iudgement and fiery Indignation which ſhall devour the Adverſaries.</hi> Again, <hi>if he that deſpiſed</hi> Moſes <hi>Law died without mercy under two or three witneſſes, of how much great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er puniſhment ſhall he be thought worthy, who hath troden under foot the Son of God, and hath done deſpite to the ſpirit of grace, ſuch <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> now term the ſame ſpirit, the ſpirit of the Devil,</hi> which they have <hi>all along hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto</hi> (during the time of their Straits and Low Condition) <hi>owned</hi> for the Spirit of God; and <hi>the ſole guider and director of their Actions,</hi> 
                     <note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Simile.</hi> Vid. Epiſt. Jud. v. 10, 11, 12, 13, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </note> much like the <hi>Apoſtate Sons of God</hi> in the <hi>old world,</hi>
                     <pb n="22" facs="tcp:176196:16"/> who having <hi>once declared their holy profeſſion,</hi> through the <hi>luſts of the fleſh,</hi> the <hi>luſt of the eyes,</hi> and the <hi>pride of life,</hi> became the <hi>moſt deſperate wretches that were in that world,</hi> running themſelves <hi>head-long</hi> (like a <hi>horſe into the battel)</hi> into <hi>all manner</hi> of <hi>Exceſſe</hi> and <hi>Riot,</hi> neither <hi>fearing God nor man,</hi> which abominable wickedneſſe was the occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the <hi>deſtruction</hi> of <hi>that world.</hi> And our Lord Jeſus hath <hi>foretold,</hi> that as it was in the dayes of <hi>Noah, ſo ſhall it be at the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Son of man.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Implying that a <hi>great Apoſtacy</hi> ſhall happen at that time among the <hi>Profeſſours of the truth,</hi> which this day is too evidently fulfil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led both in the <hi>Eyes</hi> and <hi>Ears</hi> of all that truly fear God, and <hi>keep his Commandements, to do them, but to the thing in queſtion.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>2. If <hi>Mordecay</hi> and <hi>Daniel</hi> might have had their <hi>will,</hi> they would doubtleſſe have <hi>promoted the Royall Laws of their Jehovah,</hi> with the <hi>Statutes</hi> and <hi>Judgements</hi> annexed thereunto, as clearly appeareth by the practice of good <hi>Nehemiah,</hi> Cap. 8. 1, 2. who no ſooner had the <note n="*" place="margin">Gal. 6. 10 <hi>As we have opportunity let us do good.</hi>
                     </note> Opportunity put into his hand of <hi>magnifying the Law of God, and making it Honorable,</hi> but <hi>forthwith put it in practice,</hi> which ſad experience teacheth, our Army-Men <hi>have not,</hi> albe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>it, all their <hi>opportunities, vows</hi> and <hi>proteſtations</hi> to that purpoſe, as before expreſſed, whereas it is the mind of God, that if a man <hi>vow</hi> or <hi>ſwear an oath to bind his ſoul with a bond that he break not his word, but do according to all that proceedeth out of his mouth,</hi> Numb. 30. 2. Again Deut. 23. 21. <hi>When thou ſhalt vow unto the Lord thy God, thou ſhalt not ſlack to pay it; for the Lord thy God ſhall ſurely require it of thee, and it will be ſin to thee:</hi> again Eccleſiaſt. 5. 4, 5, 6. <q>When thou voweſt a vow unto God, defer not to pay it, for he hath no pleaſure in Fools. Pay that which thou haſt vowed, better it is thou ſhouldeſt not vow, than that thou ſhouldeſt vow and not pay. Suffer not thy mouth to cauſe thy fleſh to ſin, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſay thou before the angel that it was an error; wherefore ſhould God be angry at thy voyce, and deſtroy the work of thy hand, <hi>All that your Swords have gotten you.</hi>
                     </q> Godly <hi>David</hi> telleth God, that <q>he will pay the vows which he made to him when he was in trouble,</q> but it ſeems our <hi>Army-men,</hi> are content with <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> to proclaim the God of <hi>Daniel</hi> to be worſhipped in their Dominions, provided he will be content to have it done after the <hi>Bayloniſh faſhion.</hi> Otherwiſe they have <hi>no more to ſay un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:176196:16"/>
                  <p>Again, it is worthy our <hi>obſervation,</hi> what notabe Jugglers <note place="margin">Inſtance.</note> the <hi>Kings</hi> or <hi>Tyrants</hi> of the earth have <hi>ever been with God,</hi> as for in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance in <hi>Dan.</hi> 2. 47. we find <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> (having lately recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved a favour from <hi>Daniels</hi> God, in reference to the knowledge of his dream, openly declaring, <hi>that of a truth</hi> Daniels <hi>God was a God of Gods and a Lord of Kings, and a revealer of Secrets,</hi> and yet notwithſtanding all this, in the third verſe following, we find the ſame <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> er<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>cting an image of Gold, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelling the worſhip<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ers of <hi>Daniels</hi> God, <hi>to fall down and worſhip it.</hi> An Act not much unſuitable to the preſent actions of our Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my-men, who having formerly <hi>proclaimed Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> as aforeſaid, <note place="margin">Compariſon.</note> (by way of thankfulneſſe for their <hi>wonderful preſervations from ſo many eminent dangers, and to exalt and magnifie him onely,</hi> and that by his own Way, or Rule of Worſhip, in and by his own Laws, and Ordinances, contained in the holy Scriptures, that they would ſuppreſſe whatſoever was contrary thereunto, both in Church and State) but the Nine Dayes Wonder being over, forthwith caſt all their Ingagements behind their backs, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of performing thereof, turn direct <hi>Antipodians,</hi> or <hi>Retro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gradians,</hi> by ſetting up an image of ſome things that had been deſtroying, and not onely ſo, but alſo <hi>commanding obedience thereunto,</hi> witneſſe the <hi>late Gooernment they have erected.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>3. Albeit <hi>Mordecay</hi> and <hi>Daniel</hi> did act according to the <hi>Laws and Cuſtomes</hi> of that Country, <hi>during their captivity</hi> in that place, that doth not in the <hi>leaſt argue</hi> or <hi>conclude</hi> that the <hi>Laws</hi> of the <hi>Babylonians</hi> and <hi>Perſians</hi> ſhould now be <hi>promoted among us.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p> 
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>
                     </label> For what ſhould we do with their <hi>Laws,</hi> without their <hi>Idols,</hi> for their <hi>Laws</hi> were their <hi>Religion,</hi> by which they worſhip Fleſh, God or King, or Tyrant, at whoſe <hi>Luſt</hi> and <hi>Pleaſure,</hi> the <hi>lives</hi> of men were <hi>ſacrificed</hi> to appeaſe his <hi>wrath,</hi> or their <hi>graven</hi> and <hi>mol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten gods,</hi> with the <hi>Rites and Ceremonies appertaining thereunto.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Therefore in as much as we do at leaſt pretend, that we do not worſhip their gods, what uſe have we of their Laws or Religion? whether in reference to their idolatries, or Tyrannicall worſhip required by them?</p>
                  <p>So that the neceſſary Conſequent of what hath been ſaid <hi>will be,</hi> that ſo many of this Nation, as <hi>own that God,</hi> which made <hi>his own Law</hi> in Mount <hi>Sina,</hi> by which he will be worſhipped, as
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:176196:17"/> alſo how his Subjects ſhall demean themſelves one towards ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and which was eſtabliſhed and ratified by his ſonne, and our Saviour (in <hi>Mount Olivet)</hi> and alſo by his Apoſtles, (as hath been <hi>proved)</hi> That they henceforth indevour the <hi>promotion</hi> of thoſe <hi>Holy, Juſt,</hi> and <hi>perfect Laws,</hi> with all their <hi>might</hi> and <hi>power,</hi> and contrary-wiſe to <hi>ſuppreſſe</hi> all ſuch <hi>perſons</hi> and <hi>things</hi> that are <hi>oppoſite thereunto,</hi> whether in Church or State.</p>
                  <p> 
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
                     </label> Our Saviour commandeth us to give tribute to <hi>Ceſar,</hi> and the Apoſtle injoyned obedience to the higher powers, which doth bear the Sword, and that for conſcience ſake, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. all which giveth <hi>Approbation to the Laws of Nations.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p> 
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Reſp. </seg>
                     </label> The people of God, were then (as I have ſaid) under the power of <hi>Heathen Magiſtrates;</hi> and therefore to the end they might procure unto themſelves <hi>a great</hi> and <hi>peaceable life in all godlineſſe, and honeſty,</hi> 1 Tim. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>2. 2. Our Lord Jeſus and his Apoſtles, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſhed them in ſuch caſes, not to <hi>oppoſe</hi> or <hi>reſiſt them,</hi> and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed who would not <hi>feed a hungry and greedy Lion,</hi> rather than to be torn in pieces, and devoured by him. But all this doth not <hi>in the leaſt prove,</hi> that the <hi>Laws of Ceſar,</hi> or the Image thereof, are better than the Laws of God, or that the people of God, having now under God freed themſelves from the Dominion of <hi>Ceſar,</hi> ſhould now <hi>by force be brought back again to worſhip and adore the image and Superſcription of</hi> Ceſar, <hi>under a</hi> Ceſarian <hi>Habit,</hi> that they ſhould ſubmit to the <hi>Laws, Cuſtomes and Traditions of thoſe falſe gods</hi> they have <hi>Conquered,</hi> and Neglect the <hi>Laws, Statutes and Judgements of that God by whoſe might and power they have conquered theſe falſe gods, and their worſhippers;</hi> for if ſo, what is it other than to imitate thoſe <hi>diſobedient Iſraelites</hi> (who joyned in league with the <hi>Canaa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nites, whom the Lord ſigned for deſtruction)</hi> and with them to <hi>worſhip</hi> Baalim, and the <hi>Groves,</hi> Judges 3. 6, 7.</p>
                  <p>Therefore ſuch whom the Lord hath made inſtrumentall, either by <hi>word</hi> or <hi>ſword, to extirpate the name and perſon of</hi> Ceſar <hi>out of this nation,</hi> ought doubtles to <hi>perſevere therein until they have as well ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinguiſhed and blotted out his Image and Superſcription, in whomſoever, and whatſoever they ſee or find it to be fixed in,</hi> and that to <hi>All Ends and purpoſes;</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>For <hi>without all Controverſie,</hi> the one is <hi>altogether</hi> as <hi>lawfull,</hi> if not More than was the other, yea doubtleſſe, it is a far leſſe <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:176196:17"/> of Magiſtracy</hi> to deſtroy the Image and Superſcription <hi>of Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſar,</hi> than it was to deſtroy His Name and Perſon, but the Army af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed, it was no reſiſting of Magiſtracy to deſtroy the perſon and name of <hi>Ceſar,</hi> therefore it will be no <hi>reſiſting of Magiſtracy</hi> in the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, to deſtroy the Image and Superſcription, <hi>in whomſoever, and whatſoever they find it.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>For in ſuch Caſes the Army hath concluded it as a <hi>Maxime,</hi> that it is no reſiſting <note n="*" place="margin">Note.</note> to <hi>ſide with juſt Principles, i. e.</hi> in ſuch Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, whereupon the life and death of True Religion, whether in reference to God or our neighbour doth depend) and that in ſuch Caſes, men are bound in duty and conſcience both to God and their Neighbour, (where no effectuall help doth from elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where appear) not to be wanting <hi>in any thing,</hi> they can either do or ſay, to hold off <hi>impending Ruine</hi> from an <hi>Honeſt People</hi> and <hi>a good Cauſe,</hi> but that as in <hi>publick fires</hi> all ought to <hi>lift up their Voice</hi> and <hi>Hand,</hi> bringing what <hi>Ladders, Buckets,</hi> or what <hi>other aſſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance they can (vid.</hi> Abridgement, Remon. <hi>Albans p.</hi> 1.) as did (ſay they) part of the <hi>people in Arms,</hi> or an ARMY <hi>interpoſing againſt the Standing Authority,</hi> for the life of good <hi>Jonathan,</hi> 
                     <q>
                        <bibl>1 Sam. 14. 45.</bibl> And the People ſaid unto <hi>Saul,</hi> ſhall <hi>Ionathan</hi> dye, who hath wrought this great ſalvation in <hi>Iſrael?</hi> God forbid, as the the Lord liveth, there ſhall not one hair of his head fall to the ground, for he hath wrought with God this day.</q> 
                     <hi>So the People reſcued</hi> Jonathan <hi>that he dyed not.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>From which (with ſeverall other Preſidents in the ſaid a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridgement) it is <hi>clearly apparent,</hi> that an <hi>Honeſt and juſt cauſe,</hi> doth <hi>juſtifie</hi> the <hi>Means</hi> that may <hi>accompliſh it,</hi> as alſo the <hi>inſtruments</hi> that <hi>acteth therein,</hi> what then is there wanting, <hi>but the ſword of the Lord, and of</hi> Gedeon, <hi>to deſtroy all ungodlineſſe, and unrighteouſneſſe of man from off the face of the earth, and to erect thoſe holy, juſt and perfect Laws, Statutes and Ordinances of Iehovah the Lord Chriſt, inſtead thereof.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p> 
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
                     </label> The Moral Law was ratified by Jeſus Chriſt and his Apoſtles, but not the judiciall Law you plead for, yea, Jeſus Chriſt doth in ſeverall places, null ſome of the Statutes and Judgemen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s, which were conſtituted, and appointed by <hi>Moſes,</hi> as in <hi>Mat.</hi> 5. 38. where he ſaith, ye have heard that it hath been ſaid, <hi>An eye for an eye, and a tooth for a tooth,</hi> (as in <hi>Exod, 21. 22, 23, 24, 25. Lev. 24 19, 20. Deut. 19. 20,) but I ſay unto you, that ye reſiſt not evil, but whoſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſhall ſmite thee on the right cheek, turn to him th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> other alſo.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:176196:18"/>
                  <p> 
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Reſp. </seg>
                     </label> Our bleſſed Saviour doth here neither <hi>abrogate</hi> the <hi>Statute</hi> nor the <hi>Iudgement,</hi> depending on that precept, <hi>Thou ſhalt not kill,</hi> but onely <hi>freeth the ſame</hi> from the <hi>Traditions,</hi> and <hi>interpretations of the Scribes and Phariſes, Hypocrites of thoſe times,</hi> who <hi>took</hi> and <hi>gave li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty</hi> to foſter and follow <hi>private revenge,</hi> and therefore in as much as <hi>vengeance is Gods,</hi> and in that he ſaith he will repay it by his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments, <hi>i. e.</hi> by ſuch Magiſtrates as ſhall put his Laws in exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution). The Lord Jeſus doth hereby rebuke them for taking on them to revenge their <hi>particular</hi> and <hi>private injuries,</hi> and ſo to ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogate to themſelves <hi>that power</hi> that belonged to him, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently to his Lawfull <hi>Deputies,</hi> the <hi>Civil Magiſtrate,</hi> and not that he doth here <hi>in the leaſt</hi> take off the <hi>puniſhment</hi> that <hi>God by</hi> Moſes had appointed <hi>in ſuch caſes,</hi> i. e, <hi>An eye for an eye, and a tooth for a tooth,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  <p> 
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>
                     </label> For if ſo, then it would <hi>unavoidably follow,</hi> that every man that <hi>liſteth</hi> may ſtrike out the <hi>eyes</hi> and <hi>teeth</hi> of his Neighbour at <hi>pleaſure,</hi> as alſo that the perſon <hi>ſo offended</hi> ſhould be ſo far from <hi>ſeeking revenge</hi> on the <hi>offender,</hi> as that he is <hi>ingaged</hi> by our Saviour to <hi>provoke the offender</hi> to do him more miſchief, by turning unto him the other cheek to be ſmitten: and if this be not the mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, then I would gladly know what courſe men ſhould take in point of ſuch injuries offered unto them. <hi>That may be collected from this expreſſion of our Saviour afore mentioned.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>If it be <hi>replyed</hi> that <hi>complaint</hi> is to be made to the <hi>Civil Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate,</hi> to the end he may do <hi>Juſtice</hi> therein on the perſon of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fending.</p>
                  <p> 
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Reſp. </seg>
                     </label> I demand <hi>by what Rule,</hi> for it is clearly evident to all that are rationall, that thoſe words of our bleſſed Saviour, will bear no ſuch <hi>conſtruction,</hi> but quite contrary-wiſe, that the perſon ſo injured, ſhould endeavour to provoke the offender to do him <hi>more miſchief.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Again, put caſe that an <hi>Appeal</hi> is to be made to the <hi>Civil Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate,</hi> if that Civil Magiſtrate, to whom the Appeal is made, be an Adminiſtrator or Executioner of the <hi>Laws</hi> of the <hi>alone Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maker,</hi> and giver, what other puniſhment ought he inflict, than that which he findeth preſcribed in his <hi>Maſters Laws,</hi> ſo that in <hi>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ch caſe Magiſtrates</hi> muſt either of neceſſity wholly omit any pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment for ſuch like offences, or they muſt judge by the <hi>ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:176196:18"/> Rule</hi> preſcribed in the <hi>Law of God,</hi> contained in the five books of <hi>Moſes.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>So th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n without all Controverſie, where <hi>Jehovah</hi> hath as well preſcribed the puniſhment as the offence, it ought not to be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered by any Magiſtrate whatſoever; and therefore for any Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate to aſſume the impudence to diſſolve thoſe things, <hi>that God hath ſo joyned together,</hi> by the <hi>dictates</hi> of their own <hi>phantaſie</hi> or <hi>light of Nature within them,</hi> is no other than by profeſſing them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves <hi>wiſe</hi> to become <hi>fools.</hi> Again, the Apoſtle <hi>James</hi> affirmeth, That there is but one Law-giver, who is able to ſave and to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy: It is therefore an abſolute uſurpation of Gods Legiſlative power, to ſave or deſtroy by any other means or rule, than that <hi>great</hi> and <hi>onely Law-giver</hi> hath preſcribed. Again, in point of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ſence, to whom can it rather refer to give rules of direction, for what offence <hi>mans life</hi> ſhall be ſaved, or other puniſhments to be inflicted; and for what his life ſhall be taken away, then to that holy, juſt, and righteous Law-giver, who is the <hi>Author</hi> and <hi>giver of life,</hi> and at whoſe will and pleaſure mans <hi>life</hi> and <hi>limbs</hi> ought to be taken away, and not otherwiſe.</p>
                  <p>And therefore I do hereby aver, that whoſoever ſhall hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth <hi>contaminate</hi> or <hi>deſpiſe</hi> the aforeſaid <hi>ſtatutes</hi> and <hi>judgments</hi> doth <hi>directly derogate</hi> from <hi>Gods Authority</hi> and ſubjection, who is the <hi>onely</hi> and <hi>ſufficient Law-giver,</hi> as alſo from the <hi>ſufficiency of his Laws,</hi> which is <hi>ten thouſand times</hi> more perfect than any other conſtitution whatſoever, and will thereby bring upon them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves an unavoidable deſtruction.</p>
                  <p>And it is well worthy our <hi>obſervation,</hi> that whileſt the preſent Army owned thoſe <hi>judicials,</hi> I plead for, to be <hi>from heaven,</hi> and a <hi>rule</hi> for <hi>all Rulers;</hi> and that who ſo was not <hi>ever</hi> under them <hi>owned not his ſubjection to God.</hi> They urged no other <hi>rule of juſtice</hi> to try the late King by, as is cl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>erly manifeſt in that paper titled the <hi>Abridgment of the R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>monſt. Albans,</hi> where they cite multitudes of preſidents out of <hi>holy writ,</hi> to prove him <hi>guilty of death:</hi> but not <hi>one ſtatute law of the Nation:</hi> No, they were then out of date with them: but now <hi>temporamutantur, &amp;c.</hi> And the world is run round again ſince that time.</p>
                  <p>Object. Jeſus Chriſt and his Apoſtles never commanded the practice of the Judicial Laws you ſpeak of, therefore not to be urged under the Goſpel.</p>
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:176196:19"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Reſpon.</hi> I have proved from Jeſus Chriſt himſelf, that he came not to deſtroy the <hi>morall percepts,</hi> and conſequently, not thoſe <hi>ſtatutes</hi> and <hi>judgments</hi> which are in ſeparably annexed thereunto, and have no dependance at all either upon the <hi>Ceremonial Law,</hi> or their <hi>pollitick conſtitutions,</hi> but are as I have ſaid, <hi>concluſions</hi> and <hi>rules of juſtice,</hi> grounded meerly upon the <hi>Loyall Law;</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>could not deſtroy the one without the other.</hi> But <hi>Need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> himſelf hath confeſſed that Jeſus Chriſt did <hi>ratiſie</hi> the <hi>Royal law: Ergo,</hi> thoſe <hi>judiciall precepts</hi> afore mentioned.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Reſp.</hi> 2. That the Apoſtles of the Lord Jeſus taught the uſe thereof, appeareth from <hi>Pauls 1 Epiſt.</hi> to <hi>Tim. 1. v.</hi> 9, 10. where he ſaith, the Law is made for <hi>unholy</hi> and <hi>prophane perſons:</hi> For <hi>mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therers of fathers</hi> and <hi>murtherers of mothers,</hi> for <hi>manſlayers,</hi> for <hi>Whoremongers,</hi> for them that <hi>defile themſelves with mankinde;</hi> for <hi>men ſtealers,</hi> for <hi>lyers,</hi> for <hi>perjured perſons:</hi> and if there be <hi>any other thing</hi> that is <hi>contrary to ſound doctrine,</hi> according to the glorious Goſpel of the bleſſed God, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> From which words it is clear, that the Judiciall Law, (I ſtand for) was to be <hi>in force under the Goſpel.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Reaſon,</hi> For ſeverall things here <hi>numerated</hi> by the Apoſtle, are not found in the Decalogue or Ten Commandements, or Royal Law, but are deductions there from, <hi>i. e.</hi> part of thoſe <hi>ſtatutes,</hi> which depend thereon as the Five Books of <hi>Moſes</hi> will ſufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly teſtifi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>: For the Royal Law, onely ſaith <hi>Thou ſhalt not kill.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>It doth not particulariſe <hi>killing of fathers</hi> or <hi>mothers,</hi> or <hi>manſlay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, &amp;c.</hi> Again, it alſo ſaith in a g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>neral expreſſion, <hi>Thou ſhalt not Commit Adultery.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>It doth not particulariſe <hi>Whoremongers,</hi> or ſuch as <hi>defile them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves with mankinde.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Again, in point of <hi>Theft,</hi> it only ſaith in a general term, <hi>Thou ſhalt not Steal.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>It doth not particulariſe <hi>Man-ſtealers, &amp;c.</hi> and ſo in the reſt: There can then be nothing more clear than that the Apoſtle doth here ſpeak of the <hi>Judicial Law,</hi> annexed to the <hi>Moral precept,</hi> which he affirmeth to be good and lawfull to be practiced amongſt Chriſtians.</p>
                  <p>Therefore it may be <hi>ſafely concluded,</hi> that the Judicial Law an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexed to the Moral precepts, is as well to be practiced by Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:176196:19"/> 
                     <hi>under the Goſpel,</hi> as before among the Jews, and that to <hi>all ends and purpoſes,</hi> which I collect from theſe words; if there be <hi>any other thing</hi> that is contrary to ſound doctrine, i. e. <hi>Loving God above all, and our neighbour as our ſelf;</hi> that alſo ſaith the Apoſtle, ought to be determined by thoſe <hi>Statutes</hi> and <hi>Judgments.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1. Becauſe God hath given no other rule to govern the world by; who are <hi>all under the Royal Law,</hi> as hath been proved, from <hi>Rom.</hi> 3. 9. 29. and conſequently under the other, <hi>i. e.</hi> the <hi>Statutes</hi> and <hi>judgments.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. In that Jeſus Chriſt did not deſtroy the one more than the other.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. In that the Apoſtle <hi>ratifieth the one</hi> as well <hi>as the other:</hi> As then it was <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aron</hi> before <hi>Chriſt,</hi> ſo now <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Chriſt</hi> in the <hi>Goſpel State</hi> (as Mr. <hi>Brain</hi> well obſerved.) God is ſaid to judge the ſecrets of mens hearts <hi>(i. e.</hi> the inward man) by or according to the Goſpel, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2. 16. And the things done in the fleſh <hi>(i. e.</hi> the actions of the outward man) by the Statutes and Judgments aforementioned, as hath been ſhewed, as alſo from 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5. 17. where the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>The ſins of ſome are open before hand, and go before to judgement,</hi> i. e. before the Civill Magiſtrate: Others follow after, and ſo under the <hi>Judgment of Chriſt</hi> in the Church. And this is further illuſtrated, from <hi>Rom.</hi> 2. 2. we are ſure that the judgment of God, is according to truth, againſt them that commit ſuch things, which things if you would know read cap. 1. and you will find them to be <hi>idolatry</hi> and <hi>falſe worſhip,</hi> as in making <hi>images of men,</hi> and <hi>birds</hi> and <hi>four footed beaſts</hi> or <hi>cree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping things,</hi> as alſo in <hi>vile affections</hi> as of <hi>men</hi> and <hi>women, changing their kinde, fornication, &amp;c.</hi> all which appertaining to the <hi>judiciall precepts.</hi> Again, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. the Apoſtle doth make <hi>a clear diſtinction</hi> betwixt them that are <hi>properly</hi> under the <hi>civil</hi> and <hi>ſpiritual govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, i. e.</hi> the external and internal, of <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Chriſt,</hi> as in <hi>verſ.</hi> 12, 13. where he ſaith, <hi>What have I to do to judge them that are with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out, do not ye judge them that are within? But them that are without God judgeth:</hi> as if he had ſaid, Men are now to be judged <hi>in things civil,</hi> by the <hi>civil law of God,</hi> committed to the Magiſtrate, and that not only by the men of the world, but members of Churches alſo; for the Apoſtle doth not blame the <hi>Corinthians cap.</hi> 6. of that Epiſtle, for that they brought their <hi>civill controverſies</hi> to be decided by the <hi>civill Magiſtrate.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:176196:20"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Reaſon</hi> 1. But becauſe thoſe civil Magiſtrates <hi>did not judge by the law of God,</hi> and therefore could not give <hi>a juſt judgment.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Reaſon</hi> 2. As alſo in that they were <hi>ſuch Judges,</hi> as were not <hi>rightly fixed</hi> or <hi>qualified,</hi> for ſuch a purpoſe: the latter is evident by the <hi>title,</hi> which the Holy Ghoſt putteth upon them, <hi>verſ. 1. viz. unjuſt Judges:</hi> the former is alſo evident, by the place of their a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bode <hi>viz Corinth,</hi> the Magiſtrates thereof being <hi>unbelievers,</hi> v. 6. <hi>i. e. Heathen Judges,</hi> judging by <hi>Heatheniſh Laws,</hi> as are all that <hi>now Govern</hi> as they did. And in things ſpiritual by the <hi>cenſures</hi> of the <hi>churches,</hi> as the afore mentioned expreſſions do clearly evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence. Again, our bleſſed Saviour himſelf, doth clearly mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt that <hi>judgement of external acts</hi> againſt the Law of <hi>Moſes, was left to</hi> Moſes, <hi>Luke</hi> 12, 13, 14. where the man coming to have the <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance divided,</hi> Chriſt gave him this Anſwer: <hi>Man, who made mee a judge and divider over you?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Again, in the caſe of the woman taken in the Act of Adultery, <hi>John</hi> 8. 3, 4, 5, 6. Jeſus Chriſt would neither <hi>accuſe</hi> or <hi>condemn her,</hi> ſo that the woman was <hi>diſmiſſed,</hi> not <hi>abſolved;</hi> Shiloh being now come, <hi>the Scepter was now departed from Judah, and a Law-giver from between his feet,</hi> Gen. 49. 10. The <hi>Jews</hi> at this time being then un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the <hi>dominion of the Romans,</hi> had not power to put any to death, by their Law, as clearly appeareth by comparing the 7 <hi>v.</hi> of <hi>John</hi> 19. with <hi>v.</hi> 31. of <hi>cap.</hi> 18. where the Jews tell <hi>Pilate,</hi> they have <hi>a law</hi> to <hi>puniſh blaſphemers by death:</hi> And yet the caſe was then ſuch with them, that they could not put any to <hi>death thereby.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And hence I conceive it was that the Scribes and Phariſees, Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrites brought the woman taken in the act of <hi>Adultery</hi> to our bleſſed Saviour, to entrap him, <hi>i. e.</hi> to ſee if he would take upon him to <hi>put their law in execution,</hi> and that if he had, then to have accuſed him for <hi>intermedling upon the priviledge of Caeſar,</hi> as is clear from <hi>John</hi> 19. 12. Where they tell <hi>Pilat,</hi> that if he let <hi>Jeſus</hi> go he was not <hi>Caeſars</hi> friend.</p>
                  <p> 
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>
                     </label> For (ſay they) who ſo maketh himſelf a King, (that is, that taketh upon him to <hi>put our Laws in execution</hi> (without the appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation of <hi>Ceſar)</hi> ſpeaketh againſt <hi>Ceſar,</hi> Mat. 22. 15, 16, 17. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> All which temptations our Saviour then avoided, becauſe the time was <hi>not yet come,</hi> that his Kingdome ſhould be <hi>on the earth,</hi> he being before that time to become <hi>a ſufferer,</hi> both in his <hi>own
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:176196:20"/> perſon,</hi> and in his <hi>Members,</hi> by that <hi>Roman power</hi> then in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, at the end whereof, <hi>i. e.</hi> at the expiration of the <hi>Little Horns Dominions</hi> Dan. 7. it ſhall ariſe out of the ruine thereof, and ſo by gradation ſpread it ſelf over the face of the <hi>whole earth,</hi> as in v. 25, 26, and 27 of that chapter.</p>
                  <p> 
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
                     </label> The <hi>Severity</hi> of <hi>Moſe's</hi> Judicials, ought not to be practiced under the Goſpel, as the continuall practice of the Church ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, as <hi>Paul</hi> willeth the inceſtuous perſon onely to be excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicated, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. there was then no Law in force to put ſuch to death.</p>
                  <p> 
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Reſp. </seg>
                     </label> This conceipt was the firſt ground of the <hi>Manichean Hereſie;</hi> for in making of <hi>difference</hi> in the <hi>proceedings</hi> of <hi>Juſtice</hi> under the <hi>Law,</hi> and under the <hi>Goſpel</hi> againſt <hi>one</hi> and the <hi>ſame Tranſgreſſion,</hi> they thereupon laid a <hi>foundation</hi> for the ſetting forth of <hi>two gods,</hi> the one <hi>ſevere,</hi> and the other <hi>mercifull,</hi> whereas the Lord Jeſus doth rather <hi>aggravate</hi> than <hi>mitigate</hi> the puniſhments of the <hi>Judici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Laws,</hi> as in the explication of that Precept. <hi>Thou ſhalt not kill.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>He to ſhew the latitude, or complement, or full extent of the mind of his Father therein, ſaith, that whoſoever <hi>is angry with his brother without a cauſe, ſhall be in danger of Judgement, and whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever ſhall ſay to his brother Racha, ſhall be in danger of the Councel: but whoſoever ſhall ſay thou fool, ſhall be in danger of hell-fire:</hi> hence <hi>John</hi> ſaith, <hi>He that hateth his brother, is a murtherer in Gods eſteem.</hi> Again v. 27. in his Expoſition of that Precept, <hi>Thou ſhalt not commit adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>He ſaith, that <hi>Whoſoever looketh after a woman to luſt after her, hath committed adultery with her already in his heart.</hi> &amp;c. And hence the Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> ſpeaking of <hi>laſcivious perſons,</hi> ſaith, <hi>They have eyes full of adultery,</hi> 2 Pet. 2. 14. In which expreſſions, Chriſt ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth that the <hi>Moral Precept</hi> extendeth as well to the <hi>inward</hi> as <hi>out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward man,</hi> and that he will puniſh the <hi>tranſgreſſions</hi> of the one, as of the other, the one by the <hi>Civil magiſtrate,</hi> and the other by his <hi>Church,</hi> and not in the leaſt <hi>mitigateth</hi> the <hi>puniſhments</hi> of the <hi>fruits of the fleſh,</hi> i. e. Theft, <hi>Aultery,</hi> Fornication, <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncleanneſſe,</hi> Laſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viouſneſſe, <hi>Idolatry,</hi> Withcraft, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And as touching the <hi>inceſtuous perſon,</hi> I have laid down a ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Reaſon why the <hi>Church</hi> could not puniſh him with death, they having <hi>not the power to put the Laws of God in execution,</hi> as alſo
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:176196:21"/> in that their Civil Magiſtrate did not act by Gods Laws, but were unjuſt Judges: ſo that it may as well be argued and concluded from <hi>Pauls</hi> expreſſion elſewhere, <hi>i. e. Let him that ſtole ſteal no more, but rather let him labour with his hands,</hi> &amp;c. That <hi>Theft</hi> under the Goſpel, is to be <hi>no other wayes puniſhed</hi> by the <hi>Civil Magiſtrate,</hi> than by an admonition <hi>to ſteal no more;</hi> therefore thoſe that affirm that the puniſhments of the <hi>Judiciall Law is mitigated by Chriſt</hi> and his Apoſtles under the Goſpel, would do well from the mouth of God, to ſhew <hi>in what it is mitigated,</hi> or <hi>to whom,</hi> and whether <hi>to all</hi> or to <hi>ſome ſinnes onely,</hi> and why not <hi>all</hi> as well as <hi>ſome,</hi> and how it can be <hi>in ſome particulars,</hi> and not <hi>in all,</hi> or <hi>each</hi> of them, or how it can be <hi>under the Goſpel,</hi> and not <hi>declared by Chriſt,</hi> and if <hi>by him,</hi> then how can he be ſaid to <hi>eſtabliſh the Law,</hi> and yet <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy all in part,</hi> and whether <hi>Idolatry,</hi> Blaſphemy, <hi>Murther,</hi> Adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery, <hi>Theft,</hi> &amp;c. be not the <hi>ſame in Gods eſteem now, as formerly</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> as in <hi>Judea,</hi> and if ſo, then why not <hi>the ſame puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments here,</hi> as <hi>there, for the violation</hi> thereof; with much more that might be urged to this purpoſe.</p>
                  <p> 
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
                     </label> If thoſe Statutes and Judgements annexed to the Moral Law for the breach of the Moral Precept, were now to be inſtituted, it would overthrow all the conſtitutions of Government in Chriſtendome, yea, in the whole world; and ſo bring all the Magiſtrates of the earth, into a Chaos of confuſion and deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction with all their adherents, and that both in things <hi>Civil,</hi> and <hi>Eccleſiaſticall.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p> 
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Reſp. </seg>
                     </label> That is no more than God hath <hi>appointed and determined</hi> ſhall come to paſſe at bringing in of the <hi>Kingdome</hi> of the <hi>Man-child,</hi> who is to <hi>rule all Nations with a rod of iron,</hi> Pſal. 2. 9. and 72. 8. <hi>Rev.</hi> 2. 27. and 19. 15. and therefore for the further clearing up of this Aſſertion, I ſhall ſet before you.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Who are the profeſſed Ant<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>goniſts of the Man-child, with the matters or things, whereby they have all along reſiſted and oppoſed his government, and Subjects.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. The determinate purpoſe of the Man-child, <hi>(i. e.</hi> the Lord Jeſus) to ſubvert and deſtroy thoſe perſons and things, which have and do ſo confront him and his Members, <hi>i. e.</hi> his Church or people.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. The manner how he will effect it in all the Nations of the earth.</p>
                  <p n="4">
                     <pb n="33" facs="tcp:176196:21"/>4. The perſons by whom he will effect it.</p>
                  <p>And firſt of the firſt, in order to which I <hi>Aſſert.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Aſſert.</hi> That the Kings or Tyrants of the earth, have in all ages been the <hi>Grand Antagoniſts</hi> to the <hi>Kingdome and Government of the Lord Jeſus,</hi> and that both in things ſpirituall and Civil, in the things appertaining to our duty towards God, and our Neighbour, compriſed in the two Tables of the Moral Law.</p>
                  <p>But before I proceed to the proof of this Aſſertion, I ſhall in the firſt place give you to underſtand, that I take theſe two Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles of the Moral Law or ten Commandements, with the Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes and Judgements afore mentioned, to be the <hi>Royal Law</hi> or <hi>Government</hi> of Jehovah the Lord Chriſt, and that thoſe <hi>Statutes</hi> and <hi>Judgements,</hi> are that <hi>Civil Law,</hi> by which <hi>he will rule the Nations with a rod of iron,</hi> in that they <hi>produce the ſword of Juſtice</hi> in the hands of the <hi>Civil Magiſtrate,</hi> which <hi>ſword of Iuſtice,</hi> I ſay, is that <hi>iron Rod,</hi> formerly mentioned, and no other thing, and hence it is, the <hi>Saints</hi> are ſaid to have <hi>a two edged ſword in their hand,</hi> as well <hi>as the high prayſes of God in their mouths,</hi> Pſal. 149. the one <hi>edge offenſive,</hi> and the other <hi>defenſive.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I alſo take the <hi>Goſpel</hi> or <hi>New Teſtament</hi> to be the <hi>Spirit of the</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">The Goſpel the ſpirit of the Law.</note> 
                     <hi>Law,</hi> and this Aſſertion our bleſſed Saviour himſelf <hi>confirms,</hi> Joh. 6. 63. where he poſitively affirmeth, that the <hi>Words which he ſpake, they were Spirit, and they were Life;</hi> which is alſo confirmed by the Apoſtles in v. 68. where they ſay, <hi>whither ſhall we go from thee, for thou haſt the words of eternal life,</hi> &amp;c. But the <hi>Goſpel</hi> or <hi>New Teſtament</hi> is the <hi>Counterpain</hi> of <hi>thoſe words</hi> ſo ſpoken <hi>by him</hi> and <hi>his Apoſtles,</hi> which they have left unto us, ratified by ſignes and miracles, to be <hi>a Lanthorn to our feet, and a light unto ourpaths,</hi> in the things that the Lord Chriſt expecteth to be done by his body, the Church: ſo that the Doctrine of the <hi>New Teſtament,</hi> I like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe take to be <hi>Chriſts Golden Scepter,</hi> which he holds forth to all Nations, and eſpecially unto his Spouſe, the Church, which with the Ordinances contained therein, I take to be the <hi>two edged ſword of his mou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>h,</hi> mentioned <hi>Rev.</hi> 19. 13, 15, 21.</p>
                  <p>Having thus given you my thoughts touching the two <hi>grand Principles</hi> of nature, in reference to <hi>our duty to God and our neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour,</hi> I ſhall proceed to the two <hi>Direct Oppoſites thereof,</hi> i. e.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>Idolatry,</hi> or <hi>falſe worſhip,</hi> as <hi>to God.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <pb n="34" facs="tcp:176196:22"/>2. <hi>Tyranny</hi> or <hi>Inhumanity,</hi> as to our <hi>Neighbour.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Which two Principles I do hereby <hi>aver</hi> to be <hi>of</hi> and <hi>from the Devil,</hi> and conſequently, that thoſe that put them in practice, <hi>are the Servants or Miniſters of the Devil,</hi> and <hi>profeſſed Antagoniſts</hi> to the <hi>Government of Iehovah,</hi> the <hi>Lord Chriſt,</hi> which he hath appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to <hi>govern</hi> the <hi>ſons and daughters of men by,</hi> whether in reference to <hi>himſelf</hi> or <hi>their Neighbour.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Now for proof of the forementioned Aſſertion, I ſhall give a <hi>brief Narrative</hi> of the firſt Originall of <hi>Idolatry</hi> and <hi>Tyranny</hi> after the Flood.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Iehovah</hi> having deſtroyed the <hi>Old world</hi> with a <hi>Deluge of water</hi> (by reaſon of the Abominable Apoſtacies of the <hi>ſonnes of God,</hi> or <hi>Profeſſours of Gods worſhip)</hi> Noah and <hi>his family onely excepted:</hi> yet notwithſtanding that ſo <hi>notorious preſident of ſin and puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> no ſooner was the preſent world <hi>repopulated,</hi> and that in a ſmall meaſure, but the <hi>depraved light of Nature</hi> (the Ranters, and Quakers preſent adored light, which is no better than the <hi>darkneſſe of hell,</hi> or <hi>bottomles pit,</hi> notwithſtanding the voluntary humiliation of the Quakers at this day, to colour it over, the Devil having now put <hi>his angel of light's habit</hi> upon the <hi>Ranters back or Principle,</hi> i. e. an <hi>externall ſhew of holineſſe,</hi> or <hi>voluntary humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity,</hi> as in <hi>Col.</hi> 2. 18, 19. where he exhorteth the true body or Church of Jeſus Chriſt, ſaying, let no man beguil you of your <hi>reward</hi> in a <hi>voluntary humility,</hi> (or ſelf-denyall in the things of this life) or worſhipping <hi>of Angels,</hi> (or figments or Notions of the mind) intruding into thoſe things that they have not ſeen, (notwithſtanding all their pretence of ſeeing) <hi>Vainly puft up with a fleſhly mind.</hi> Pure Quakers, as can be ſpit out of the Devils mouth, as wofull experience will ſhortly teach them, they being (as I hear Mr. <hi>Iohn Goodwin</hi> lately and truly characteriſed them) <hi>The laſt born of the Devil.</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">The Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers Tenent is the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils laſt game he hath to play</note> 
                  </p>
                  <p>The Devil, as I have ſaid, having put upon their accuſed Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple, his <hi>moſt beautifull robe of deluſion, which the Lord preſerve all good people from.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I ſay, no ſooner was the preſent world repopulated, and that in a ſmall meaſure, but the aforeſaid depraved light of Nature, now ſo rampant, and idolized among the <hi>Apoſtate Profeſſors</hi> of theſe dayes) in mankind became ſubject to the <hi>like temptations,</hi> and
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:176196:22"/> 
                     <hi>deluſions of Satan,</hi> which brought them into the like abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble practiſes of violating the two forementioned grand Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of nature, by practiſing <hi>Idolatry,</hi> and <hi>Tyranny.</hi> The ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginall of which defection or wicked practice (after the Flood) upon <hi>a publick account,</hi> is by <hi>Hiſtorians fixed on Nimrod.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The ground of this their Aſſertion, they take from <hi>Gen.</hi> 10. 8, 9, 10. Where <hi>Cuſh</hi> is ſaid to beget <hi>Nimrod,</hi> and that he began to be <hi>a Mighty one in the Earth, and a mighty hunter before the Lord,</hi> and the <hi>beginning</hi> of his <hi>Kingdome</hi> was <hi>Babel.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>Hierome</hi> in <hi>Tract. Gen.</hi> ſaith, that <hi>Nimrod</hi> was the firſt man after the Flood, that exerciſed <hi>Tyranny,</hi> which before was not practiſed.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. <hi>Ioſephus</hi> ſaith, he provoked men to <hi>pride</hi> and <hi>contempt of God,</hi> teaching them to aſcribe their <hi>Happineſſe</hi> to <hi>themſelves,</hi> and <hi>not unto God.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3. <hi>Hugo Annot.</hi> in <hi>Gen.</hi> ſaith he brought in <hi>Idolatry,</hi> teaching men to <hi>worſhip the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ire</hi> that was ſo <hi>commodious unto them,</hi> which pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice (ſaith he, the <hi>Caldeans followed.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="4">4. Whereas <hi>Nimrod</hi> is ſtiled a <hi>Mighty Hunter</hi> before the Lord, <hi>Auguſtine</hi> rendereth it <hi>againſt the Lord,</hi> but the proper meaning is, that it is ſpoken by a <hi>Metaphor,</hi> becauſe he <hi>hunted men,</hi> as <hi>Beaſts are chaſed</hi> (in which ſenſe <hi>David</hi> ſaith, that <hi>Saul</hi> hunted him, as <hi>Partridges</hi> are <hi>hunted in the mountains)</hi> and that in the <hi>very ſight</hi> and <hi>preſence of God,</hi> he practiſed <hi>Idolatry</hi> and <hi>Tyranny:</hi> ſo that from <hi>Nimrods Idolatrous</hi> and <hi>Tyrannical Dominion,</hi> it grew into a <hi>Proverb,</hi> to reſemble an <hi>Idolater</hi> and <hi>cruel oppreſſour</hi> to <hi>Nimrod.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Behold then, all ye <hi>Idolaters,</hi> (or <hi>falſe worſhippers)</hi> and <hi>Tyrants,</hi> (or <hi>cruell oppreſſors)</hi> the <hi>Root</hi> from which you had your <hi>Sap</hi> and <hi>Growth,</hi> from that time to this preſent day. B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hold alſo, the firſt Metropolis, or City of refuge, that this your <hi>great Grandſire</hi> prepared to <hi>ſecure himſelf from danger,</hi> the <hi>Greateſt Tyrants,</hi> ever providing the <hi>greateſt ſecurity for themſelves,</hi> knowing they are <hi>neither in favour with God or good men;</hi> and hence it is they ever <hi>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified themſelves</hi> with <hi>ſtrong Cities,</hi> &amp;c. being <hi>afraid,</hi> even of their <hi>own ſhadows,</hi> witneſſe the Hand-writing upon the wall, which made <hi>Belſhazzars countenance to change,</hi> yea, put him into <hi>ſuch ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gony,</hi> (and that in the height of all his jolily) <hi>as looſed even the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry joynts of his loyns, ſo that his knees ſmote one againſt another,</hi> Dan. 5, 6.
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:176196:23"/> yea, it put <hi>both him and his Nobles</hi> in ſuch a <hi>fright,</hi> that it was high time for them to call aloud for their <hi>Aſtrologers, Caldeans</hi> and <hi>ſouthſayers,</hi> and yet all to no Purpoſe, <hi>Lillies Art</hi> was then <hi>non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pluſt</hi> with its <hi>Albumazar,</hi> as alſo in <hi>Nebuchadnezzars Dream,</hi> touching the <hi>Fifth Monarchy,</hi> which <hi>ſhamefull diſparagement, to their diabolical profeſſion,</hi> makes them they could never endure a <hi>dreaming Prophet</hi> ſince, and eſpecially if it ſavours of that <hi>fifth Monarchy Dream,</hi> as <hi>expounded by</hi> Daniel, <hi>cap.</hi> 2. 34, 35, 44, 45. which Dream <hi>is certain,</hi> and <hi>the interpretation thereof ſure,</hi> maugre all the <hi>Diabolicall inſtruments in the world,</hi> by what name or title ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever they are called.</p>
                  <p>And hence it is, that all the <hi>Tyrannicall</hi> and <hi>Idolatrous Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">The Riſe of Pagan Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon.</note> that were from <hi>Nimrod</hi> to <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the Roman Emperor, (which I term the <hi>Old Pagan ſtate</hi> or <hi>Government)</hi> had their <hi>Riſe</hi> and <hi>being</hi> from <hi>Nimrod</hi> and that <hi>City and Tower</hi> of <hi>Babel,</hi> and therefore commonly called in Scripture the <hi>Queen</hi> or <hi>Mother</hi> of <hi>Idolatry,</hi> and <hi>Inhumanity,</hi> and conſequently of all <hi>Idolaters,</hi> and <hi>Tyrants,</hi> the iſſue of that <hi>helliſh ſpawn.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And in like manner, I alſo take the Riſe of that <hi>Autichriſtian</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">The Riſe of Antichriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Babylon.</note> 
                     <hi>Babylon,</hi> tituled in <hi>Rev.</hi> 17. 5. <hi>Myſtery</hi> Babylon <hi>the great, the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of harlots, and abomination of the earth,</hi> to be meant of <hi>Rome</hi> in point of ſituation, and the <hi>Nimrod</hi> thereof to be <hi>Conſtantine,</hi> who after he had ſwallowed up the floods of water, caſt by the <hi>Dragon</hi> after the woman, <hi>Rev.</hi> 12. from v. 13. to <hi>ult.</hi> (which (I take to be by his Conqueſt over the perſecutours of the Chriſtians,) he is ſaid to give unto the Beaſt which roſe out of the waters, cap. 13. 1, 2. his <hi>power</hi> and <hi>ſeat</hi> and <hi>great Authority,</hi> by which act of his became the mixture of <hi>Iron,</hi> and <hi>Potters clay,</hi> together in the images feet, foretold by <hi>Daniel,</hi> cap. 2. 33, 41, 42, 43. which <hi>I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>on,</hi> and <hi>Potters clay,</hi> I take to be the mixing of the <hi>Civil and Eccleſiaſtical powers together,</hi> which from that time have been continued to this preſent day.</p>
                  <p>Having thus ſtated the Riſe both of the <hi>Pagan</hi> and <hi>Antichriſtian Babylon,</hi> I ſhall in the next place enlarge my ſelf a little in refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to each of them, to the end, that by a better knowledge th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>reof, the people of God may be more induced to <hi>abominate</hi> and <hi>deteſt them,</hi> as alſo to <hi>execute the Judgement upon them</hi> and their ſupporters and adherents, as it is written, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 149. with mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titudes
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:176196:23"/> of other Scriptures to that purpoſe, and firſt of the firſt <note place="margin">A brief Narrative of Pagan Babylon.</note> 
                     <hi>(viz.)</hi> of <hi>Pagan Babylon,</hi> with its <hi>Adherents.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>As to what this <hi>Nimrod was <note>Who <hi>Nim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rod</hi> was.</note> ,</hi> ſome take him to be the ſame which <hi>Forreign ſtories</hi> call <hi>Belus,</hi> and that he was the <hi>firſt founder</hi> of the <hi>Idols</hi> in the <hi>Eaſtern Countries,</hi> who were <hi>derived from him,</hi> as <hi>Belial, Beelzebub, Belphegor,</hi> but it will appear by what follows, that <hi>Nimrod</hi> was before <hi>Belus.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>2. Touching <hi>Babel,</hi> the beginning of <hi>Nimrods</hi> Kingdome, it <note place="margin">Of <hi>Babel</hi> in general.</note> was ſo called, not from <hi>Belus,</hi> as ſome would have it, but from the <hi>Confuſion of Languages,</hi> as the <hi>ancient Saxon word Babel</hi> doth ſeem to import, which word was uſually men<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ioned by them to ſuch perſons, as ſpake confuſedly, to whom they would ſay, why <hi>Babel ye,</hi> or why <hi>confuſe ye</hi> the true <hi>etimology</hi> of the <hi>word,</hi> being <hi>why Babel ye,</hi> or why do ye imitate thoſe perſons at <hi>Babel,</hi> who ſpake ſo <hi>confuſedly,</hi> as th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t they could not be underſtood by their Auditors: but to put all out of doubt, the Scripture doth clearly teſtifie as much, <hi>Gen.</hi> 11. 9. in theſe words, <hi>therefore is the name of it called</hi> Babel, <hi>becauſe there the Lord confounded the Langua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of all the earth, and from thence did the Lord ſcatter them abroad upon the face of the earth.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>3. Touching the building of the City of <hi>Babel</hi> or <hi>Babylon,</hi> the <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Of the City and Tower of</hi> Babel.</note> 
                     <hi>firſt Metropolis</hi> of <hi>Idolatry</hi> and <hi>Tyranny, Quintus Curtius</hi> aſcribeth it to <hi>Belus,</hi> lib. 4. <hi>Beroſus</hi> cited by <hi>Joſephus</hi> to <hi>Nebuchadnezzar,</hi> lib. 1. cont. Appian. from <hi>Dan</hi> 4. 30. where <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> is preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſaying, is not this <hi>great Babel</hi> which I have builded for the Houſe of the Kingdome, the might of my power, and the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of my Majeſty. <hi>Beroſus Arrianus,</hi> maketh all three builders of <hi>Babylon,</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>As 1. That <hi>Nimrod</hi> began the Tower, <hi>anno</hi> 131. after the Flood.</p>
                  <p>2. That <hi>Belus</hi> built the <hi>City,</hi> who ſaith he reigned after <hi>Nim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rod</hi> 65 years, and that he himſelf <hi>(i. e.) Belus</hi> reigned 56 yeers.</p>
                  <p>3. That <hi>Semyramis</hi> the wife of <hi>Ninus,</hi> which reigned 24 yeers, much <hi>inlarged</hi> the <hi>City,</hi> and <hi>fortified it.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ter all this, when the Aſſyrian Kings had made <hi>Niniveh</hi> the <hi>imperial ſeat,</hi> ſo that <hi>Babylon</hi> was much neglected and decayed, at laſt, <hi>Nebuch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>dnezzar</hi> having conquered the City of <hi>Niniveh,</hi> re-<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dified <hi>Babylon,</hi> (as before mentioned) and hereto agreeth <hi>Ioſephus O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>oſinus lib</hi> 6. and <hi>Auguſt. lib. 16. de Civit. Dei, cap.</hi> ſo that the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:176196:24"/> and Foundation was laid in <hi>Nimrod,</hi> as in <hi>Gen.</hi> 10. 10. which ſaith, <hi>That the beginning of his Kingdome was</hi> Babel.</p>
                  <p>4. As touching the way and means, this <hi>Nimrod</hi> took to ſet <note place="margin">How Nim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rod became a Monark.</note> up his <hi>Idolatrous</hi> and <hi>tyrannical government,</hi> I ſhall likewiſe ſet forth, to the end that the preſent <hi>Idolaters</hi> (or falſe worſhippers) and <hi>Tyrants</hi> or <hi>civil oppreſſors</hi> of the times) may compare their <hi>preſent conditions</hi> and <hi>actions</hi> with their <hi>predeceſſors,</hi> at the erecting of their <hi>great grand-mother Babell. Nimrod,</hi> having by his <hi>craft</hi> and <hi>policy</hi> wound himſelf ſo into the affections of the people, as to be made their <hi>Captain-General:</hi> Or, <hi>Ring-leader</hi> of that company; and cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to mind how the <hi>old world was drowned</hi> and <hi>deſtroyed</hi> for <hi>Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry</hi> and <hi>Inhumanity</hi> which <hi>deſigne</hi> he had now in his heart <hi>to pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice</hi> (as his predeceſſors of the old world had done before him) though <hi>covertly;</hi> and therefore under a <note n="*" place="margin">Nimrods Policy.</note> pretence of making themſelves famous in the earth to all poſterity: And thereupon ſtirred up the rude multitude (under this plauſible pretence) to build him <hi>a City</hi> and <hi>a Tower,</hi> that might not only <hi>free him from the danger of men;</hi> but alſo from fear of any thing that <hi>God could do unto him,</hi> as alſo that he might with <hi>more boldneſſe</hi> effect his <hi>wicked</hi> and <hi>ungodly enterpriſes.</hi> And this he did in <note n="*" place="margin">One tyrant taketh ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample by another.</note> 
                     <hi>imitation</hi> of the <hi>Tyrants</hi> of the <hi>old world,</hi> i. e. the Gyants or Apoſtate ſons of God, of whom it is reported, that they had a City called <hi>Enos</hi> in the Mountains of <hi>Libanus,</hi> that <hi>ruled over the whole world.</hi> But it is to be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood that this <hi>Nimrod</hi> could not fortifie his City, Tower, and Palace with <hi>Demy Cannon</hi> and ſuch like Artillery: for the uſe of ſuch <hi>engines of cruelty</hi> were not then <hi>found out;</hi> but ſince the <hi>Devil,</hi> for the better encouragement of <hi>ſervants,</hi> hath now ſupplied them with <hi>plentifull ſtore thereof</hi> for ſuch purpoſe, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>I ſhall now in large ſomething in reference to the <hi>Tower,</hi> in the attempting and erecting whereof theſe following ſins concurred, with which I ſhall alſo mentioned, to the end the preſent <hi>Nimrods,</hi> or Idolatrous tyrannical <hi>Babel-builders</hi> of the times may rumi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate thereon, and conſider how far ſhort they <hi>now are</hi> (if any) of <hi>Nimrods</hi> then condition.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. In the building of this Tower, his <hi>impiety</hi> appeared, in at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempting it in <hi>deſpite of God.</hi> As the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> according to <note place="margin">The impiety of tyrants.</note> this pattern bringeth in the King of <hi>Babylon</hi> vanting himſelf ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, I will aſcend unto the clouds; I will be like the Moſt High.</p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <pb n="39" facs="tcp:176196:24"/>2. His <hi>vanity</hi> appeared, in ſeeking to be made <hi>famous on earth,</hi> and not by <hi>good actions</hi> to be made glorious <hi>in heaven:</hi> he thought to <note place="margin">Their vanity</note> exalt himſelf by building, and not by <hi>loving</hi> God above all, and his neighbour as himſelf.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. His <hi>diſobedience</hi> appeared, in that it was Gods ordinance, <note place="margin">Their diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedience.</note> that the earth ſhould be <hi>repleniſhed</hi> by them, and yet they wilfully oppoſe the Counſel of God, by reſolving not to depart from them, as in <hi>v.</hi> 6. where they ſay, <hi>Let us build a City and Tower, whoſe top may reach to heaven, that we may get us a name leaſt we be ſcattered.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="4">4. Herein his <hi>impudence</hi> was alſo diſcovered: For whereas <note place="margin">Their impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, pride, and volup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuouſneſſe.</note> he ſhould have been convicted in his <hi>conſcience</hi> for his <hi>pride</hi> and <hi>arrogancy, Rom.</hi> 2. 15. he <hi>openly proclaimed his ambition, voluptuouſnes, &amp;c.</hi> to all poſterity, proceeding to ſuch a <hi>violence</hi> therein, that nothing could now reſtrain him, as neither the <hi>fear of God,</hi> nor the <hi>fearfull looking for of judgment and fiery indignation</hi> (2 Pet. 3. 10.) <hi>to be poured out upon him,</hi> as in <hi>Heb.</hi> 5. 26, 27. But contrariwiſe, whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, he had <hi>proudly deviſed,</hi> he would as <hi>impudently practiſe.</hi> The <hi>confuſion of their language</hi> was therefore <hi>a fruit of their pride:</hi> as in <note place="margin">Pride bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth confuſion</note> Prov. 16. 8. Zeph. 2. 10. ſo that whereas they <hi>looked to gain credit,</hi> they found <hi>ſhame and confuſion.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Like as when <hi>Saul</hi> had thought he had made a <hi>goodly place for</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Simile.</note> 
                     <hi>himſelf,</hi> as triumphing for his <hi>late victory over Amaleck:</hi> Even then he was <hi>rejected</hi> for <hi>being King</hi> (1 Sam. 15. 28) for his not obeying <note place="margin">A warning for tyrants.</note> the command of the Lord, againſt his <hi>profeſſed enemies.</hi> All which one would think to be fair warnings to the <hi>like diſobedient Sauls of the times.</hi> (And in particular at <hi>Black-hall)</hi> the Lord give them grace to conſider thereof, if they be not <hi>paſt repenting.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Again, That the <hi>Kings</hi> of the earth were the <hi>original</hi> or <hi>root</hi> of <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolatry</hi> and <hi>Tyranny,</hi> is alſo aſſerted and proved by <hi>King Solomon,</hi> in his book titled Wiſdome cap. 13. 14. where ſpeaking of this <note place="margin">Kings the Original of Idolatry &amp; Tyranny.</note> ſubject, he ſaith:</p>
                  <q>That the <hi>deviſing</hi> of <hi>Idols</hi> were the beginning of <hi>ſpiritual forni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation,</hi> and the <hi>inventions</hi> of them the <hi>corruption of life, for neither were they from the beginning, neither ſhall they be for ever.</hi>
                  </q>
                  <p>For by the <hi>vain-glory of men,</hi> they entered into the world: And therefore ſhall they come <hi>ſhortly to an end.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <q>
                     <p>For a Father afflicted with <hi>untimely mourning,</hi> when he had made an <hi>Image of his childe,</hi>
                     </p>
                     <pb n="40" facs="tcp:176196:25"/>
                     <p>ſoon taken away: Now honoured him as a God, which was then a <hi>dead man:</hi> And delivered to thoſe that were under him, <hi>Ceremonies</hi> and <hi>Sacrifices.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Thus (ſaith <hi>Solomon,)</hi> in <hi>proceſſe of time</hi> an <hi>ungodly cuſtome</hi> grown ſtrong, <hi>was kept as a law:</hi> And <hi>graven images were worſhipped</hi> by the commandement of <hi>Kings</hi> or <hi>Tyrants,</hi> whom men could not ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, becauſe they dwelt far off. Therefore they took the counterfeit of his Viſage from far, and made an expreſſe <hi>Image of a King,</hi> whom they honoured (or worſhipped) to the end that by this their <hi>forwardneſſe,</hi> they might <hi>flatter him</hi> that was ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, as if he were <hi>preſent:</hi> Alſo the <hi>ſingular diligence</hi> of the <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tificer</hi> did help to ſet forward the <hi>ignorant</hi> to <hi>more ſuperſtition.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Reaſon</hi> 
                     <q>For he paradventure being willing to pleaſe one in <hi>Authority, forced all his skill</hi> to make the <hi>reſemblance</hi> of the <hi>beſt fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhion;</hi> and ſo the multitude being allured by the <hi>grace of the work,</hi> took him now to be <hi>a God;</hi> which a little before was but hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red as <hi>a man.</hi> And this (ſaith he) was an occaſion to deceive the <hi>world.</hi>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Reaſon</hi>
                  </p>
                  <q>
                     <p>For men <hi>ſerving</hi> either <hi>Calamity</hi> or <hi>Tyranny</hi> did <hi>attribute to ſtocks</hi> and <hi>ſtones</hi> the incommunicable Name. Moreover (ſaith <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon)</hi> this was not enough for them, that they erred in the <hi>know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of God;</hi> but whereas they lived in the <hi>great war of Ignorance,</hi> theſe ſo <hi>great plagues</hi> called they <hi>peace:</hi> For whileſt they <hi>ſlew their children in ſacrifices,</hi> and uſed <hi>ſecret ceremonies,</hi> or made <hi>revilings</hi> of ſtrange <hi>rites.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>They kept neither lives nor mariages any longer undefiled: <note place="margin">Note, The viola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the firſt prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture leads to the breach of the ſecond.</note> But either one ſlew another <hi>treacherouſly,</hi> or griev<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>d him by A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dultery: So that there remained in <hi>all men,</hi> without <hi>exception,</hi> blood, man-ſlaughter, theft and diſſimulation, corruption, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faithfulneſſe, tumults, perjury, diſquieting of good men; for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getfulneſſe of good turns, defiling of ſouls, changing of kinds, diſorder in marriages, adultery and ſhameleſſe uncleaneneſſe.</p>
                  </q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Argum.</hi> 
                     <q>For the <hi>worſhipping of Idols</hi> (of what ſort ſo ever) not to be named, is the <hi>beginning,</hi> the <hi>cauſe,</hi> and the <hi>end</hi> of <hi>all evill.</hi>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>But the Kings of the <hi>earth</hi> were the Authors, Cont<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>mners and promoters of Idols, and Idol-worſhip: as hath been ſhewed:</p>
                  <p>Therefore the <hi>Kings</hi> or <hi>Tyrants</hi> of the earth were the <hi>beginning,</hi> the <hi>cauſe,</hi> and the <hi>end of all evill.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:176196:25"/>
                  <p>And thus I have proved, and that by the teſtimony of <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> King,</hi> that the <hi>Principles of the Kings or Tyrants of the earth, are directly oppoſite</hi> to the two <hi>Grand Principles of Nature,</hi> i. e. <hi>To love God a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove all,</hi> and <hi>our Neighbours as our ſelves.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And this Doctrine is alſo plentifully confirmed by the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> in <hi>Rom.</hi> 1. from v. 18. to <hi>ult.</hi> which is well worthy alſo of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſal, as to this particular, and now I ſhall proceed to the <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond particular in order,</hi> i. e.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Aſſert.</hi> That Jehovah the Lord Chriſt is determined to have a generall reckoning day, with thoſe perſons, and things that have ſo confronted him and his Laws, <hi>i. e.</hi> theſe two Principles of Nature, with the Decalogue and Statutes, and Judgements depending thereupon, as hath been ſhewed.</p>
                  <p>And this is alſo proved by the teſtimony of King <hi>Solomon,</hi> in the aforeſaid book <hi>cap.</hi> 13. and <hi>cap</hi> 14. where having treated of the <hi>two ſorts of Idolatry, i. e.</hi> of worſhipping of the <hi>creature,</hi> and like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe of the <hi>Image</hi> of the <hi>creature,</hi> he concludes, That the ungod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and his ungodlineſſe are both alike hatefull to God; for that which is made, ſhall be puniſhed together with him that made it, <hi>Look to it then</hi> Idol-makers; for black will be your day, when the onely wiſe Potentate, King of Kings, and Lord of Lords, ſhall by his Saints bring your actions to the touchſtone of the Scriptures.</p>
                  <p>But leaſt they ſhall ſay, this <hi>Teſtimony of</hi> Solomons, (which I have cited the rather, becauſe he is <hi>a bird of their own feather in point of Title)</hi> is <hi>Apochrypha,</hi> I ſhall commend unto them the teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of that <hi>Grave Orthodox Divine,</hi> new <hi>created</hi> Doctor, and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular Dean in <hi>England</hi> (for you muſt underſtand all the reſt were Popiſh, and <hi>ſuperſtitious)</hi> which I have done, the rather in regard of that <hi>great repute</hi> he hath for a <hi>learned Rabby,</hi> to the end, what is ſaid by him, may gain the <hi>more credence</hi> with his <hi>Maſters</hi> and <hi>fraternity,</hi> with the reſt of the <hi>Rabble Rout of Locuſts, Caterpil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers</hi> and <hi>Canckerworms of the Nation.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And for their <hi>better attention,</hi> I do alſo hereby give them to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand, and that the expreſſions, I ſhall mention, are extracted out of a Sermon preached by him, before no leſſe perſons than the <hi>Houſe of Parliament,</hi> from <hi>Heb. 12, 26, 27. i. e. Whoſe voice then ſhook the earth, but he hath promiſed, ſaying, yet once more, and I ſhake
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:176196:26"/> not the earth, but the heavens alſo, and this word yet once more ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the removing of thoſe things that are ſhaken, as of things that are made, that thoſe things which cannot be ſhaken may remain.</hi> In the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>planation of which words, he uſeth theſe following expreſſions, <hi>i. e.</hi> 
                     <q>as the Apoſtle here applyes part of the Prophet <hi>Haggai,</hi> ſo that Prophefie, even in the next words gives light into the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the <hi>Apoſtle,</hi> look what <hi>Heavens</hi> and <hi>Earth</hi> the Prophet ſpeaks of, of this, and no other ſpeaks the Apoſtle. The Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of the Lord in the <hi>Scriptures,</hi> is his own beſt interpreter, ſee then the order of the words, as they lye in the Prophet <hi>Haggai, cap. 6. 7. I will ſhake Heaven and Earth, I will ſhake all Nations,</hi> God then <hi>ſhakes Heaven and Earth, when he ſhakes all Nations,</hi> that is, he <hi>ſhakes</hi> the <hi>Heaven</hi> and <hi>Earth</hi> of the <hi>Nations.</hi>
                     </q> I will <hi>ſhake Heaven</hi> and <hi>Earth,</hi> I will <hi>ſhake</hi> all Nations, is a <hi>Pleonaſme.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>For I will <hi>ſhake</hi> the <hi>Heaven</hi> and <hi>Earth</hi> of the <hi>Nations:</hi> theſe are the things <hi>ſhaken</hi> in my <hi>Text.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Query. <hi>The heavens of the Nations, what are they?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Reſp.</hi> Even the <hi>Political heighths</hi> and glory, <hi>i. e.</hi> theſe <hi>Formes</hi> of <hi>Government,</hi> which they, (meaning the <hi>Civil</hi> and <hi>Eccleſiaſticall Magiſtrates,</hi> whether under <hi>Pagan</hi> or <hi>Antichriſtian Babylon,)</hi> have <hi>ſet up</hi> for <hi>themſelves</hi> (not for Chriſt) and their <hi>own Intereſt</hi> (not <note place="margin">Note.</note> for the Intereſt of Chriſt and his ſanctified ones) with the <hi>gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure</hi> and <hi>luſtre</hi> of <hi>their Dominions.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The <hi>Nations Earth</hi> is the <hi>multitude</hi> of their <hi>people,</hi> their <hi>ſtrength</hi> and <hi>power,</hi> whereby their <hi>Heavens</hi> and <hi>Political Heighths</hi> and <hi>Splendor</hi> of the <hi>Popular Multitude,</hi> and Strength of the Nations of the earth, that are to be <hi>ſhaken,</hi> as in <hi>Rev.</hi> 12. 16. and 21. 13. where by an Earthquake, <hi>great Babylon</hi> receives a fatall blow, and <hi>Iſa.</hi> 51. 15, 16. and 34. 4. All the Hoſt of <hi>Heaven</hi> ſhall be <hi>diſſolved,</hi> and the Heavens ſhall be <hi>rolled together</hi> as a <hi>ſcroll,</hi> and all the Hoſts ſhall fall down as the leaf falleth from the Vine.</p>
                  <p>Now theſe <hi>diſſolved</hi> and <hi>rolled Heavens,</hi> are no other than the <hi>Powers</hi> and <note n="*" place="margin">Note.</note> 
                     <hi>Heighths</hi> of the <hi>popular Nations.</hi> Their <hi>Government</hi> and <hi>Tyranny:</hi> As both the foregoing and following verſes do declare, the Lords <hi>wrath</hi> (ſaith the Prophet) is upon the <hi>Nations,</hi> and his <hi>fury</hi> upon their <hi>Armies:</hi> he hath delivered them to the <hi>ſlaughter,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>vid.</hi> Ezek. 3. 2. 7. You may take it (ſaith this learned Rabby) for a <hi>rule,</hi> that in the <hi>denuntiation</hi> of the judgment of God,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:176196:26"/> throughout all the <hi>Prophets,</hi> Heavens, Sun, Moon, and Stars, and the like <hi>acceptable beauties</hi> of the <hi>Heavens</hi> are taken for <hi>Governments, Dominions</hi> in <hi>Pollitick States:</hi> As in theſe Scriptures, Iſa. 12, 13, 14, 15. Jer. 15. 9 and 51. 25. Iſa. 13. 13. and 60. 20. Pſal. 68. 8. Joel 2. 10. Obad. 4. Mat. 24. 29. Luke 21. 25. Rev. 18. 12, 13. and 11. 12. and 20. 11. and 6. 12, 13, 14, 15. The waſting and deſtroying of the <hi>Pagan Roman State,</hi> and the plagues and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motions of the people; the <hi>dethroning</hi> of <hi>idol worſhip;</hi> the deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of <hi>perſecuting Emperours,</hi> and <hi>Captains,</hi> with the <hi>tranſpoſition</hi> of <hi>Powers</hi> and <hi>Soveraignty</hi> from <hi>one ſort</hi> to <hi>another</hi> is held under this <hi>Grandure</hi> of <hi>words,</hi> being part of the ſhaking of <hi>Heaven</hi> and <hi>Earth</hi> in my Text, <hi>vid.</hi> Euſeb. Eccleſ. Hiſt. Lib. 9. c. 8. 10. Lib. 8. cap. 17. de Vet. Conſtan. lib. 1. cap. 50, 51, 52.</p>
                  <p>Adde hereunto (ſaith the Court Chaplain) the promiſes of the <hi>reſtauration</hi> of Gods people, <hi>into a glorious condition after all their ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings.</hi> How now Doctor, take heed what you ſay, for theſe words are petty Treaſon, if your Maſters come to hear thereof; But I pray what is that <hi>Reſtauration</hi> and <hi>glorious ſtate you here dream of;</hi> for I will aſſure you the Court counts ſuch expreſſions but <hi>dreams</hi> and <hi>phanſies</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nd ſuch a thing as will <hi>never be:</hi> And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore pray let us ſee what <hi>ground you have in ſcripture,</hi> for ſuch a <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtauration</hi> and <hi>glorious eſtate</hi> as you ſpeak of.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Doct.</hi> It is <hi>perpetually</hi> in the <hi>Scriptures</hi> held out under the <hi>ſame terms</hi> (meaning of <hi>Heaven</hi> and <hi>Earth)</hi> and you have a <hi>plentifull de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtration of this point</hi> (How Doctor) is there ſuch <hi>a plentifull de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtration in ſcripture, of a reſtauration of Gods people into a glorious ſtate and condition after all their ſufferings?</hi> Pray what ſcriptures are thoſe, they will be <hi>Noveliſts at Court,</hi> for they can entertain no ſuch <hi>Phanſies,</hi> therefore pray lets have them.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Doct.</hi> See <hi>Iſa. 65. 17, Behold,</hi> I creat <hi>new Heavens</hi> and a <hi>new Earth,</hi> and the <hi>former</hi> ſhall <hi>not be remembred, nor come into my mind:</hi> Doct. how ever this is to you, I am ſure it is a new and ſtrange doctrine at Court, <hi>what man?</hi> Muſt all the <hi>political government</hi> in the world with the <hi>grandure and luſtre of them, be ſo ſhaken and done away, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> that they ſhall not ſo much as be remembred, nor come into the minde of God and his people?</hi> Indeed Doctor, you muſt preach this doctrine no more at <hi>Bethel;</hi> for now it is the Kings Chappel: I will aſſure you there is now treaſon in ſuch Texts. But certainly Doctor,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:176196:27"/> you judge this glorious government to be within us; not vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible in the world. See <hi>v. 18. Be ye glad and rejoyce for ever in that which I create.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Reaſ.</hi> For <hi>behold</hi> I create <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> a <hi>rejoycing,</hi> and her <hi>people</hi> a joy: (But Doct. the Court will tell you that this <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> which God will ſo create, is meant of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> within <hi>man,</hi> and not of a <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> without <hi>man,</hi> or viſible as that <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> in which the Jews did inhabit in <hi>Canaan:</hi> And therefore for our better underſtanding of this particular, we will if you pleaſe, take a view of the following expreſſion of the Prophet: which are theſe. And I will rejoyce in <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and joy in my people, and the voice of <hi>weeping</hi> ſhall be no more heard in her, and the voice of crying. There ſhall be no more <hi>thence</hi> an infant of daies, nor an old man, that hath not filled his dayes: for the child ſhall die, an hundred years old; but the ſinner that is an hundred years old ſhall be accurſed: what think you of theſe word<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor? Is all this meant to be fulfilled within the people of God? but if we have no more than this to ſay for the Fifth Monarchy without or <hi>under the Heavens,</hi> Mr. <hi>Cardell</hi> one of the <hi>late</hi> Fifth <hi>Monarchiſts</hi> will tell us, that all the <hi>four Monarchies,</hi> three of which, are paſt and diſſolved, <hi>viz.</hi> the <hi>Babyloniſh Meads</hi> and <hi>Perſians,</hi> with the Greatian Monarchy have been all within us, and that the fourth Monarchy, <hi>viz.</hi> the Roman Monarchy is now <hi>within us,</hi> and is in like manner to bee diſſolved <hi>within us:</hi> And therefore it is far leſſe to have <hi>Infants</hi> and <hi>Old men</hi> within us at one and the ſame time, as before mentioned: therefore we muſt yet proceed to the following verſes, and ſee if we finde any thing that the Quakers cannot ſo well digeſt, as old men and children to live and die; as aforeſaid, we ſhall there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore proceed to <hi>v. 21, 22. &amp;c.</hi> where the Prophet ſaith:</p>
                  <p>They ſhall build <hi>houſes</hi> and <hi>inhabit them;</hi> they ſhall <hi>plant vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yards</hi> and <hi>eat</hi> the <hi>fruit of them.</hi> (Surely, the Quakers hath <hi>divelliſh wide weaſands,</hi> if they <hi>ſwallow</hi> downe all theſe particulars: as Houſes and Vineyards, with their builders and Planters; but they do theſe things onely when they are in their Quaking fits: But Sir, this Text puts me in minde of your brother Doctors, Maſter <hi>Thomas Goodwins</hi> Sermon upon <hi>Rev.</hi> 5. 9, 10. where ſpeaking of the <hi>glorious eſtate and condition that the people of God ſhall enjoy after all their ſufferings,</hi> citeth this very text to prove his Aſſertion, <hi>i. e.</hi>
                     <pb n="45" facs="tcp:176196:27"/> That they ſhall enjoy a Kingdome upon earth, for ſaith he, they ſhall <hi>build houſes,</hi> and <hi>plant vineyards.</hi> O, to ſee how good wits will jump, for he uſeth even your own words, <hi>i. e.</hi> A <hi>glorious con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition after all their ſufferings;</hi> and therefore Gentlemen, ſeeing you are both convinced of this truth: See if you can conquer the Souldiers with your rhethorical Artillery. But in the <hi>interim,</hi> let us lay before them the following words of the Prophet, <hi>v. 21. They ſhall not build and another inhabit, they ſhall not plant and another eat; for as is the dayes of a Tree, are the dayes of my people. And my elect ſhall long enjoy the works of their hands:</hi> (It appeareth then there muſt be <hi>Mechanical perſons in this glorious ſtate,</hi> which the two lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Doctors aſſert is to be; for the following words ſaith, <hi>They ſhall not labour in vain, nor bring forth trouble.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Reaſ.</hi> For they are the ſeed of the bleſſed of the Lord, and their off ſpring with them (they are then to procreate <hi>children under this glorious eſtate and condition,</hi> vid. cap. 66. 22. And it ſhall come to paſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> that before they ſhall call (ſaith the Lord) I will Anſwer: And whil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſt they are <hi>yet ſpealing</hi> I will hear (there is then to be the <hi>uſe of Ordinances under this glorious ſtate and condition)</hi> and pray, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> The Wolf and the Lamb ſhall feed together, and the Lyon ſhall eat ſtraw with the Bullock; and duſt ſhall be the Serpents meat, <hi>i. e.</hi> They ſhall not hurt nor deſtroy in all my holy moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, ſaith the Lord. They ſhall then beat their <hi>ſwords</hi> into <hi>plow-ſhares,</hi> and their <hi>ſpears</hi> into <hi>pruning hooks:</hi> Nation ſhall not lift up <hi>ſword againſt Nation, neither ſhall they learn war any more:</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Gentlemen you will ſtand in need of all your Rhethorick, when you go about to convince the Souldiery of putting this Doctrine in practice.</p>
                  <p>But if this ſcripture be fulfilled, and this glorious time is now under this preſent Government; Why do they not, as it is here directed by the ſpirit of God to be done? And now Doctor, I ſhall proceed to your confirmation of this <hi>grand doctrine,</hi> from the New Teſtament, to which purpoſe, I finde you to inſtance 2 Pet. 3. 13. Where the Apoſtle having before in that cap. put the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of God in minde by way of remembrance touching the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious kingdom and ſtate, which you and your <hi>brother Doctor</hi> hath affirmed <hi>muſt be,</hi> and which I am ſure yet is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Reaſ.</hi> For the Soldiers ſwords are not yet <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> to <hi>Plow-ſhares,</hi> nor their <hi>Spears into Pruning-books, &amp;c.</hi> (witne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> the intolerable
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:176196:28"/> taxes yet to ſupport them.) The Apoſtle I ſay, having put the people of God in remembrance of the words, which are ſpoken by the Holy Prophets, and likewiſe of the commandment of them the Apoſtles of the Lord Jeſus to ſuch purpoſe, and that they ſhould not be danted touching the accompliſhment thereof, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding ſcoffing and mocking, and blaſphemi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>g of the <hi>ſcof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fing Iſhmalites,</hi> and <hi>railing and blaſphemous Rabſhakahs,</hi> that ſhould happen to be neer the time of its approach: <q>Who <hi>walking after their own luſts,</hi> will ſay, where is the promiſe of his coming: for ſince the <hi>fathers</hi> fell aſleep, all things have continued as they were from the beginning: For <hi>this</hi> they are <hi>willingly ignorant of,</hi> that by the word of God, the <hi>Heavens</hi> were of old, and the <hi>Earth</hi> ſtanding out of the waters, and in the water, whereby the world that then was, being overflowed with water, periſhed. But the <hi>heavens</hi> and <hi>earth,</hi> which are now by the <hi>ſame word,</hi> are kept in ſtore, reſerved <hi>unto fire</hi> againſt the day of judgement, and perdition of ungodly men, but beloved, (faith the Apoſtle) be not <hi>ignorant</hi> of this <hi>one thing,</hi> that one day is with the Lord, as a thouſand years, and a thouſand years as one day; for the Lord is not ſlack concerning his promiſe, as ſome men count ſlack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, but is long-ſuffering to us ward, not wiling that any ſhould periſh, but tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> all ſhould come to repentance; but the day of the Lord will come as a thief in the night, in the which the Heavens ſhall paſſe away with a great noiſe, and the Elements ſhall melt with fervent heat, and the earth alſo and the works that are therein ſhall be burnt up. Seeing then that all theſe things ſhall be diſſolved, what manner of perſons ought ye to be, in all holy converſation and godlineſſe, looking for and hoping unto the coming of the day of God, wherein the heavens being on fire ſhall be diſſolved, and the Elements ſhall melt with fervent heat. Nevertheleſſe we according to his promiſe, look for new heavens, and a new earth, <hi>wherein dwelleth Righteouſneſſe,</hi> not <hi>Idolatry</hi> and <hi>Tyranny.</hi>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>Now for the better underſtanding of the Rabbies meaning t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ching the <hi>new Heaven</hi> and <hi>new Earth</hi> here mentioned, I ſhall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> another paſſage of his in <hi>pag.</hi> 12. of that book, where he having aſſerted that it is <hi>not</hi> to be meant of the <hi>material Heaven</hi> and <hi>Earth,</hi> produceth this Scripture to prove the ſame, <hi>i. e. Iſa.</hi>
                     <pb n="47" facs="tcp:176196:28"/> 51. 15, 16. <hi>I am the Lord that divided the ſea, whoſe waves roared, the Lord of Hoſts is his name, and I have put my words in thy mouth, and have covered thee with the ſhadow of my hand, that I might plant the heavens, and lay the Foundations of the Earth, and ſay unto Sion, thou art my People.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>In theſe words ſaith the <hi>Doctour,</hi>
                  </p>
                  <q>
                     <p>by a Repetition of what he hath done, he eſtabliſheth his people in expectation of what he will do.</p>
                     <p>And 1. He minds them of that wonderfull deliverance from an Army behind them, from an ocean before them, by his mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous preparing dry paths for them in the deep. <hi>I am the Lord, who divided the ſea, whoſe waves roared.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </q>
                  <p>2. <q>Of his greatneſſe, acquainting them with his mind, <hi>i. e.</hi> his <hi>Laws</hi> and <hi>Ordinances</hi> at <hi>Horeb, I have put ſaith he, my words in thy mouth.</hi>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>3. <q>Of that favourable and ſingular protection afforded them in the wilderneſſe, when they they were encompaſſed with ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies round about. <hi>I covered thee with the ſhadow of mine hand.</hi>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Query,</hi> Now (ſaith the ſingular Dean) <hi>&amp;c. to what end was all this?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Reſp.</hi> Why ſaith he (meaning the Lord by the Prophet) that I might <hi>Plant the Heavens, and Lay the Foundations of the Earth.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Query.</hi> What of thoſe <hi>material, viſible Heavens</hi> and Earth, 2460 years before, <hi>at leaſt,</hi> were they <hi>planted</hi> and <hi>eſtabliſhed.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Reſp.</hi> It is all (ſaith the Rabby) but <hi>making of Sion a people, which before was ſcattered in diſtinct Families.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Query.</hi> And how was this done? quoth the Doctour?</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Reſp.</hi> Why the <hi>Heavens are planted,</hi> or a <hi>glorious frame</hi> of <hi>Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> and <hi>Policy is erected among them,</hi> and the multitudes of their people are diſpoſed into an <hi>orderly Common-wealth,</hi> (Note) to be <hi>a firm Foundation,</hi> and <hi>Bottome</hi> for the <hi>Government among them:</hi> So that from what the Doctor hath here aſſerted, it is as clear as the Sun in <hi>its brighteſt Luſtre,</hi> that the <hi>Frame of Government</hi> for the <hi>unmovable Kingdome,</hi> or <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> or the <hi>fifth Monarchy.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Are thoſe <hi>Laws, Statutes</hi> and <hi>Judgements,</hi> which were given by Jehovah at <hi>Horeb</hi> and <hi>revived</hi> and <hi>ratified</hi> by the Lord Jeſus at <hi>Mount Olivet,</hi> Mat. 5. For thoſe are they the Doctour terms the <hi>firm Foundation, a firm Foundation</hi> for an <hi>unmovable Kingdome?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="48" facs="tcp:176196:29"/>
                  <p>And this Doctrine is alſo ratified by the Prophet <hi>Malachy</hi> c. 4. where ſpeaking of the <hi>diſſolution</hi> of thoſe <hi>old Heavens</hi> and <hi>old earth,</hi> formerly treated of, <hi>i. e.</hi> the <hi>Political Frame of Government,</hi> which men have made for themſelves, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> i. e. of thoſe <hi>Heavens,</hi> and <hi>Earth,</hi> which the Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> ſaith, are to be <hi>burned</hi> and <hi>conſumed by fire,</hi> as alſo of that <hi>new Heaven,</hi> and <hi>new earth,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in <hi>dwelleth Righteouſneſſe,</hi> I ſay the Prophet ſpeaking of that <hi>Great and notable day of triall by fire,</hi> telleth us by way of explana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion what is intended by the <hi>Holy Ghoſt,</hi> in ſuch manner of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion, ſaith, <q>Behold the day cometh that ſhall <hi>burn</hi> as an <hi>oven,</hi>
                     </q> Note, <q>and all that <hi>are proud,</hi> and all that <hi>do wickedly</hi> ſhall be as <hi>ſtubble,</hi> and the day that cometh ſhall burn them up ſaith the <note place="margin">Proud and wicked per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons muſt be this fire.</note> Lord, and it ſhall leave them <hi>neither Root nor Branch:</hi> but unto you that fear my name, ſhall the <hi>Son of Righteouſneſſe</hi> appear with healing in his wings, and ye ſhall go forth and grow as calves of the ſtall, and ye ſhall tread down the wicked, for they ſhall be as aſhes under the ſoles of your feet (Note) In that day that I ſhall do this, ſaith the Lord, <hi>Remember</hi> (what?) the <hi>Law of Moſes</hi> my ſervant, which I commanded unto him <hi>in Horeb</hi> with the <hi>Statutes</hi> and <hi>Judgements.</hi>
                     </q> 
                     <hi>Ergo</hi> That <hi>Law, Statutes</hi> and <hi>Judgments,</hi> ſhall be put again in practiſe that day.</p>
                  <p>Again the Doctour doth further confirm this Doctrine from <hi>Rev. 21. 1. I ſaw a new heaven, a new earth,</hi> for the <hi>firſt heaven</hi> and the <hi>firſt earth were paſſed away,</hi> And there was no more ſea.</p>
                  <p>Here ſaith the Doctour, the <hi>Heaven</hi> and <hi>earth</hi> is <hi>reſtored,</hi> but the <hi>ſea</hi> ſhall be <hi>no more.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <q>Thoſe gatherings together of many waters, (ſaith the <hi>Rabby)</hi> Rivers from all places, or <hi>Pretended Clergy men from all Nations into General Councels,</hi> which were the <hi>ſea</hi> or <hi>many waters,</hi> on which the <hi>Whore ſate,</hi> ſhall have <hi>no <note n="*" place="margin">Note.</note> place at all in the Churches re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored Conditions</hi>
                     </q> (Reader, you muſt underſtand the Rabby did not then <hi>dream</hi> of the <hi>Court of Tryers now at</hi> Whitehall, or elſe you muſt (if you can) conceive them not to be <hi>pretended Clergy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men,</hi> or <hi>a general Councel,</hi> no you muſt take them to be <hi>only</hi> an <hi>image</hi> of ſuch <hi>pretended Clergy men and general Councel,</hi> and the like you know, is not the ſame (a pure Juggle) But I conceive the Learned Doctor is <hi>out</hi> in the <hi>Expoſition</hi> of that forenamed Text in <hi>Rev.</hi> for the holy Ghoſt doth not there ſpeak of the <hi>Reſtauration</hi> of any of
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:176196:29"/> 
                     <hi>his Political Heavens</hi> and earth ſo much already treated of; for the Text ſaith plainly, <hi>they were paſſed away,</hi> and the Prophet <hi>Iſa.</hi> ſaith, <hi>cap. 65. 17. that they ſhall not be remembred, nor come into the mind of God or his people;</hi> therefore <hi>there can be no expectation of any reſtoring of them,</hi> it muſt therefore be <hi>unavoidably meant</hi> of the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid <hi>Laws, Statutes</hi> and <hi>Judgements,</hi> which the Doctour <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf calls the <hi>firm foundation for the unmovable Kingdome of Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> and hence it is the Lord by <hi>Malachy</hi> puts his people in mind thereof, at that <hi>notable day,</hi> ſaying, <hi>Remember ye the Law of</hi> Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as aforeſaid, and therefore whereas it is ſaid, there ſhall be <hi>no more ſea,</hi> I do underſtand there ſhall be <hi>no more uſe of the Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viticall Prieſthood,</hi> that being <hi>now aboliſhed</hi> by our bleſſed Saviour, ſhall be no more. No more uſe of the <hi>type,</hi> when the <hi>antitype</hi> is come, no more uſe of the <hi>ſhadow</hi> when we have the <hi>ſubſtance,</hi> which myſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rie the Prophets ſaw <hi>but darkly,</hi> as appears by their writings, few of them ſeeing <hi>a Change of the Leviticall Prieſthood,</hi> which I conceive to be the <hi>great ſtumbling block</hi> to the <hi>Jews</hi> from Chriſts abode on earth to this preſent day.</p>
                  <p>But nevertheleſſe, the Prophet <hi>David</hi> doth moſt excellently foretell the change thereof under the <hi>Goſpel-diſpenſation,</hi> as in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 40. where ſpeaking in the <hi>perſon of Chriſt,</hi> (for it is impoſſible it ſhould be underſtood of himſelf ſaith, <hi>ſacrifice and offering thou didſt not deſire, mine ears haſt thou opened, burnt-offerings and ſin-offerings haſt thou not required. Then ſaid I, Lo I come, in the Volume of thy Book it is written of me, that I ſhould do thy Will, O God,</hi> which Text the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> doth clearly expound of Chriſt, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10. 8. ſaying above, <hi>When he ſaith, Sacrifice and offering, and burnt-offering for ſin thou wouldeſt not, neither haſt pleaſure therein, which are offended by the Law, (i. e.</hi> the ceremoniall Law) <hi>Then ſaid he, Loe I come to do thy will, O God.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>He taketh away the firſt, that he may eſtabliſh the ſecond, he taketh a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way</hi> the <hi>ſhadow,</hi> that he may <hi>eſtabliſh the ſubſtance.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Now where was it propheſied of <hi>David</hi> that he ſhould have a <hi>body</hi> given him to <hi>do away Sacrifice,</hi> or to <hi>put an end thereunto:</hi> it muſt therefore be meant of <hi>ſome others,</hi> and what other than he that hath born our <hi>tranſgreſſions,</hi> and by whoſe <hi>ſtripes</hi> we are <hi>heal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, vid.</hi> Iſa. 54. 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and 52. 13, 14. 15. in both which places alſo the Prophet ſpeaketh of <hi>another perſon,</hi> and not of
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:176196:30"/> himſelf, <hi>i: e.</hi> Jeſus Chriſt the <hi>Righteous,</hi> who is the pro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>for our ſinnes,</hi> Rom. 3. 25. 1 John 2. 2. and 4. 10.</p>
                  <p>The Learned Doctour having thus proved for me what is meant by the <hi>Old Heavens,</hi> and the <hi>Old Earth,</hi> as alſo the <hi>New Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens</hi> and the <hi>New Earth,</hi> i. e. by the <hi>Old Heaven</hi> and <hi>Old Earth,</hi> all the <hi>Old Forms of Government ſince the Creation, that have been made by Political</hi> or <hi>Humane invention,</hi> as alſo the <hi>New Heavens,</hi> and <hi>new Earth</hi> to be <hi>that Conſtitution</hi> or <hi>Government made by God himſelf, and ratified and confirmed by Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> (i. e. the two <hi>grand Principles of Nature, afterward branched forth into the Deoalogue or ten Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, with the Statutes and Judgements unneued thereunto,</hi> and the <hi>Ordinances of Jeſus Chriſt in the New Teſtament,</hi> which is the <hi>Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual, Eccleſiaſtical,</hi> or <hi>Goſpel</hi>-part thereof) I ſhall in the next place bring the <hi>preſen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> powers</hi> and <hi>Conſtitutions</hi> of <hi>Government</hi> in the <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> to the <hi>teſt</hi> or <hi>touchſtone of the Scriptures,</hi> and in this particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar alſo Mr. <hi>Owen</hi> ſhall ſay for me in the forementioned Sermon, <hi>p.</hi> 21. i. e. That the <hi>Kings of the Earth have given their power to Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt, indeavouring to the uttermoſt, to keep the Kingdome of Chriſt out of the world,</hi> or that we term the <hi>fifth Monarchy.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <q>
                     <p>What I pray, hath been their <hi>main buſineſſe</hi> for 700 years and upward, even almoſt ever ſince the Man of ſin was inthroned, <note place="margin">The Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries to this purpoſe.</note> How have they <hi>earned the Titles of eldeſt ſon of the Church.</hi> The <hi>Catholick and moſt Chriſtian King, Defender of the Faith and the like.</hi> Hath it not been by the <hi>blood of Saints?</hi> Is there not in every one of theſe Kingdomes the ſlain and the <hi>baniſhed ones of Chriſt,</hi> to anſwer for in particular? <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Have not all the Kings round a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout waſhed their <hi>bands</hi> and <hi>Garments</hi> in the blood of a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand of Proteſtants? and do not the Kings of all theſe <hi>Nations</hi> as yet ſtand up in the room of their Progenitors, with the ſame <hi>implacable enmity</hi> to the power of the <hi>Goſpel?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>And is there not a cry for all this? How long Lord, holy and true, doſt thou not avenge our blood on them that dwell in the earth,</hi> Rev. 6. 10. Doth not Sion cry, <hi>the violence done unto me, and my children be upon Babylon, and my blood upon thoſe heavens of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; and will not the Lord avenge his elect, that cry unto him day and night? will he not do it ſpeedily? will he not call the fowls of Heaven to eat the fleſh of Kings, and Captains, and great men of the Earth,</hi> Rev. 19. 18. <hi>Will he not make the Heavens like the wood of the Vine, &amp;c.</hi> (and what of all this Doctour?</p>
                     <pb n="51" facs="tcp:176196:30"/>
                     <p>The time ſhall come to <hi>diſcover her ſlain,</hi> and not the <hi>ſimpleſt Hereticks,</hi> as they were counted, ſhall have <hi>his blood <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap>enged :</hi> Neither ſhall any attonement he made for this blood, or <hi>expia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion be allowed, whileſt a Toe of the image, or a Bone of the Beaſt, is left unbroken.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </q>
                  <p>Again p. 13.</p>
                  <q>
                     <p>
                        <hi>No kind of government in</hi> Europe, <hi>or line of Governors ſo ancient,</hi> but that the <hi>Beaſt is as old as they;</hi> and had a great in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence into their <hi>conſtitution,</hi> or <hi>eſtabliſhment, to provide that it might be for his own intereſt,</hi> where the <hi>Pope hath not expreſſely bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gained for his own intereſt,</hi> and provided that <hi>he</hi> ſhould have the <hi>chief place,</hi> in all the <hi>Oaths</hi> and <hi>bonds</hi> that were <hi>betwixt Prince</hi> and <hi>People,</hi> either by <hi>pretended collation of Right to pacifie the Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences of blood-thirſty Potentates</hi> in the undertaking, and purſuing their <hi>unjuſt Conqueſts,</hi> or <hi>fooliſh Mitred confirmations</hi> of <hi>ſword pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſes,</hi> he hath got them <hi>framed</hi> to his own end and purpoſe, which was to bring in all <hi>theſe Nations</hi> into <hi>ſubjection</hi> to his <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byloniſh uſurpations:</hi> Which thoſe Kings finding <hi>no way inconſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtent</hi> with their <hi>own deſignes,</hi> did <hi>willingly promote,</hi> labouring to <hi>enforce all Conſciences</hi> into ſubjection to the <hi>Romiſh Sea.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Hence it is, that ſuch an <hi>interpoſition</hi> was made of the <hi>rights</hi> of <hi>Holy Church:</hi> That is, <hi>Babylon</hi> the <hi>Mother of Harlots,</hi> in all the Types, Oathes, and Bonds between Prince and People, and for the advancement of the righteous judgements of God. That the ſons of men may learn to fear and tremble before him. And it may be obſerved, that that which doth, and ſhall ſtick upon <hi>Potentates</hi> to their <hi>ruine,</hi> is not ſo much their own, or any other intereſt, as the <hi>dregs of that Papall Antichriſtian intereſt,</hi> thruſt into their <hi>Oathes</hi> and <hi>Obligations,</hi> for no other end in the world, <hi>but to keep the Lord Jeſus out of his Throne.</hi> And this is a reaſon, why the Lord Jeſus by his mighty power, at the bringing in of his unmoveable Kingdom, will ſhake the <hi>Heavens</hi> and <hi>Earth</hi> of the <hi>Nations.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Reaſ.</hi> 
                     <q>Even becauſe in their preſent <hi>conſtitutions,</hi> they are <hi>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly framed</hi> to the <hi>intereſt of Antichriſt,</hi> which by notable advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages at their firſt <hi>moulding</hi> and <hi>contrived inſinuation,</hi> ever ſince hath ſo <hi>rivited</hi> it ſelf into the very <hi>fundamentals</hi> of them, that no <hi>digging</hi> nor <hi>myneing</hi> with an <hi>earthquake</hi> will caſt up the <hi>foundation ſtones thereof,</hi> &amp;c. Becauſe as is their <hi>Intereſt,</hi> ſo is their <hi>Acting.</hi>
                        <pb n="52" facs="tcp:176196:31"/> The preſent <hi>powers</hi> of the <hi>Nations,</hi> ſtand in <hi>direct oppoſition</hi> to the <hi>bringing in of the Kingdome of Chriſt.</hi> At which time, ſaith the <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor)</hi> Two things there are that will be confeſſed incumbent on him in this day of his <hi>advancement.</hi>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>1. <q>The bringing home of his <hi>antient people</hi> to be <hi>one fold,</hi> with the <hi>fulneſſe of the Gentiles;</hi> raiſing up the Tabernacle of <hi>David,</hi> and building it as in the <hi>dayes of old:</hi> In the accompliſhment of <hi>innumerable promiſes,</hi> and anſwer to <hi>millions of prayers.</hi> (Doctor in this, you and your brother yet hath not cut a thred:) but pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed Doctor. Now there are two <hi>main hinderances of this work,</hi> that muſt be <hi>removed,</hi> the firſt whereof is:</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>1. <hi>Real,</hi>
                  </p>
                  <q>
                     <p>The <hi>great river</hi> Euphrates, the ſtrength and fulneſſe of thoſe ſtreams do yet rage ſo high, that there is no paſſage for the <hi>Kings of the Eaſt</hi> to come over, wherefore this muſt alſo be dryed up as other waters were, for their forefathers of old, <hi>Rev.</hi> 16. 12. and doubtleſſe this is ſpoken in <hi>alluſion</hi> to <hi>Abrahams</hi> going over that River into <hi>Canaan,</hi> when the Church of God in his family was there to be <hi>erected:</hi> whence he was <hi>called</hi> the <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew:</hi> that is the <hi>Paſſenger,</hi> i. e. <hi>over that River,</hi> Gen. 14. 13.</p>
                     <p>And then it may well enough denote the <hi>Turkiſh power,</hi> which proud as it is at this day, poſſeſſing in peace, all thoſe Regions of the Eaſt: yet God can <hi>quickly make it wither,</hi> and <hi>be dryed up:</hi> Or to the deliverance of the <hi>Jews in Babylon,</hi> when it was taken and deſtroyed, by the drying up of the <hi>ſtreams of that river;</hi> and ſo the yoke of her tyranny broken from the Churches neck, <hi>Jer.</hi> 51. 31. &amp;c. <hi>And ſo it can be no other, but the power of the</hi> Romiſh Babylon, <hi>ſupporting the Kings of the Nations.</hi> Which muſt therefore be ſhaken and dryed up.</p>
                  </q>
                  <p>2. <hi>Moral,</hi>
                  </p>
                  <q>
                     <p>Or the <hi>Idolatry of the Gentile worſhippers:</hi> The <hi>Jews</hi> ſtick hard as yet at this: That God ſhould aboliſh any kinde of worſhip, <hi>which himſelf inſtituted.</hi> But that he ſhould ever ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept any <hi>falſworſhip,</hi> which he had once <hi>ſtrictly prohibited,</hi> and no where to this day <hi>appointed.</hi> To this they will never be recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciled: Now ſuch is all the <hi>invented idolatrous worſhip,</hi> which the Kings of the <hi>earth</hi> have ſucked in, from the <hi>Cup of Fornications</hi> held out unto them <hi>in the hand,</hi> and <hi>by the Authority</hi> of the <hi>Roman Whore.</hi> This ſtill they cleave cloſe unto, and will not hearken to the Angel preaching the <hi>everlaſting Goſpel;</hi> that men ſhould <hi>wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:176196:31"/> him,</hi> who made the Heavens and the Earth, and the Sea, and the fountains of Water, <hi>Rev.</hi> 13. 6, 7. i. e. The God of Heaven in Jeſus Chriſt, according to his holy, juſt, and righteous laws, ſtatutes, judgements, and Ordinances as afore mentioned) in oppoſition to all their <hi>Jeonolatry, Artolatrys, Hagiolatry, Stanro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry,</hi> and <hi>Maſſe abomination.</hi> This then muſt alſo be <hi>removed:</hi> And becauſe (as it hath been ſaid) it is ſo <hi>rivited</hi> and <hi>cemented into,</hi> and with <hi>all the Orbs</hi> of the <hi>Nations,</hi> Heaven and Earth, <hi>i. e.</hi> the <hi>politick</hi> or <hi>humane Frames of Government,</hi> which they have made <hi>for * themſelves</hi> and <hi>their intereſts)</hi> they therefore muſt be <hi>ſhaken</hi> and brought to <hi>deſtruction</hi> before it <hi>can be effected.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The ſecond thing he hath to accompliſh is the <hi>Tremendous</hi> totall <hi>Deſtruction</hi> of the <hi>man of Sin,</hi> and <hi>all his adherents,</hi> that are not obedient to the <hi>Heavenly call,</hi> Rev. 18. 4. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Doct.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <q>Pray, what is your meaning by the <hi>adherents</hi> of <hi>Babylon?</hi>
                  </q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Reſp.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <q>Are not moſt <hi>Potentates</hi> tyed by Oath, or <hi>other compact,</hi> either to maintain <hi>the whole,</hi> or ſome part of the <hi>old Tower,</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the name of <hi>Right</hi> of <hi>Holy Church, Prelates</hi> and the <hi>like:</hi> (true Doctor they are?)</q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Query</hi>
                  </p>
                  <q>It is <hi>clear then,</hi> that you <hi>include</hi> all <hi>ſorts</hi> of <hi>Governours,</hi> and <hi>Governments</hi> to be <hi>adherents</hi> to the <hi>Papal power</hi> (or myſtery Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon the great, the Mother of Harlots, and abomination of the the earth) <hi>who ſupport</hi> Prelacy. But what is your meaning by thoſe words or the like:</q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Reſp.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <q>He that thinketh <hi>Babylon</hi> to be confined to <hi>Rome</hi> and its <hi>open Idolatry,</hi> knows nothing of <hi>Babylon,</hi> nor of the <hi>New Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem,</hi> the <hi>depth</hi> of that <hi>ſubtill myſtery,</hi> Rev. 17. 5. <hi>doth not lye in groſſe viſible folly:</hi> It hath been <hi>inſinuating</hi> it ſelf into <hi>all the Nations</hi> for 1600 years, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And is now become as the <hi>marrow</hi> in the <hi>bones,</hi> which before it can be ſhaken out; The Heaven muſt be <hi>diſſolved</hi> and the Earth <hi>ſhaken.</hi>
                  </q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Query</hi>
                  </p>
                  <q>It ſeems then <hi>Doctor,</hi> you conclude that all <hi>Governours</hi> and <hi>Governments,</hi> that do ſupport the <hi>Prelatical</hi> part of the <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacie,</hi> are <hi>adherents to Babylon,</hi> and therefore muſt be <hi>deſtroyed with it.</hi>
                  </q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Reſp.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <q>The <hi>late King</hi> had learned a ſaying from his <hi>Predeceſſors, No Biſhop, No King;</hi> Hence he ſuppoſes his <hi>main intereſt</hi> to lye in <hi>holding faſt Prelacy:</hi> What ever he ſeems to part with all, that he will not let go? thats his <hi>main intereſt.</hi>
                  </q>
                  <pb n="54" facs="tcp:176196:32"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Query</hi> And what is this Prelacy?</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Reſp.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <q>A meer <hi>Antichriſtian encroachment</hi> upon the inheritance of Chriſt: <hi>Chriſt coming to take his own,</hi> ſhakes the other in pieces.</q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Query</hi> Well ſaid Doctor, and ſo he hath done bleſſed be Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hovah for it. But what think you of <hi>Presbytery?</hi> Is not that <hi>it</hi> you meant where you ſaid <hi>Prelacy,</hi> or the <hi>like?</hi> Pray Doctor tell me your minde freely, what you think of the <hi>Presbyterian Gov<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>rn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> and that <hi>Civil, Political Power</hi> that <hi>doth ſupoort it?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Reſp.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <q>Thoſe who would have been our <hi>oppreſſors</hi> in <hi>Scotland,</hi> but that God hath cruſhed the <hi>Cockatrice</hi> in the <hi>ſhell;</hi> and filled the Pit with their <hi>dead bodies,</hi> which they had digged <hi>for us:</hi> They alſo had prepared a <hi>Procruſtes bed,</hi> a <hi>heavy yoak;</hi> a <hi>Beaſt,</hi> that had it <hi>grown</hi> to <hi>perfection,</hi> would have had <hi>Horns</hi> and <hi>Hoofs;</hi> and in <hi>maintaining this,</hi> they think their <hi>great intereſt</hi> to lie: <hi>And in hold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this faſt,</hi> are they after <hi>all their aſſociations broken in pieces.</hi>
                  </q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Query</hi> I plainly perceive that <hi>this Presbytery</hi> would have been a <hi>helliſh Bondage</hi> to have been <hi>confined unto;</hi> for you have painted it out in <hi>very notable ſignificant characters;</hi> but pray what was the <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigne of the</hi> Scots <hi>if they had prevailed?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Reſp.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <q>The <hi>corrupt deſign</hi> of theſe in <hi>Scotland</hi> was to have ſet up a Son of <hi>Tu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>eal</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> and themſelves to be great under him: that they and their <hi>partakers</hi> might impoſe upon the reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>due of the Nation: Eſpecially in the <hi>things</hi> of God. Their great deſire that things ſhould be thus, corrupts their minds <hi>to think</hi> that it <hi>ought to be ſo,</hi> and <hi>ſhall be ſo:</hi> Hence <hi>ambition to rule,</hi> and to have <hi>all under their power,</hi> Even <hi>in Conſcience,</hi> I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> quickly miſtaken for zeal to the Kingdome of Chriſt. Re-in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throning of <hi>Tyranny</hi> is <hi>Royalty,</hi> and all according to the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Thus mens <hi>mindes</hi> and <hi>judgments</hi> are <hi>diſtempered</hi> by <hi>their Iuſt</hi> and <hi>intereſts,</hi> which makes them <hi>frame a way</hi> for God to <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed</hi> in, which when he doth not, <hi>How are they ſurpriſed?</hi>
                  </q>
                  <p>Thanks <hi>(noble Doctour)</hi> you are then <hi>clear of opinion,</hi> that <hi>Preſby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery,</hi> and the <hi>Civil Magiſtrates</hi> and <hi>Governments</hi> that ſupport it, are alſo Adherents to the beaſt or Papacy, and conſequently, that they alſo are to participate of that <hi>Tremendous, Final deſtruction,</hi> and totall amotion, as you have declared to fall on <hi>Babylon.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But I pray, is there <hi>no hopes</hi> of taking off the Civil Magiſtrate from joyning hands with the <hi>Horned</hi> and <hi>Hoofed Beaſts</hi> of the <hi>Presbyterian judgement?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="55" facs="tcp:176196:32"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Reſp.</hi> Can any expect that ſuch as theſe, <hi>i. e.</hi> Civil Magiſtrates of <hi>Political Governments,</hi> ſuch as they have made for themſelves and their intereſt, as the Doctour hath formerly mentioned) ſhould take up the <hi>deſpiſed quarrel of Chriſt</hi> againſt that <hi>Flouriſhing Queen.</hi> Doubtleſſe, no ſuch fruit will grow on theſe trees, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <q>
                     <p>No ſooner is one <hi>Carnal Form ſhaken out,</hi> but they are ready to cleave to another, yea, to <hi>warm themſelves</hi> in the <hi>feathered neſts of. unclean Birds,</hi> all <hi>Fleſhly Dominion</hi> (therefore) within doores, and <hi>Civil Dominion,</hi> that oppoſeth without doores ſhall be ſhaken.</p>
                     <p>Now theſe things are ſo glewed alſo to mens earthly Poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, the <hi>tallons of the birds of prey,</hi> having firmly ſeaſed on them, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>hey alſo muſt be ſhaken with them, and therefore from them alſo will be have us (meaning the Saints and people of God (to be looſed, <hi>vid. 2 Pet.</hi> 3. v. 12, 13.</p>
                  </q>
                  <p>I Perceive Doctor, there is then but one way to be taken with the <hi>Papal, Prelatical</hi> and <hi>Presbyterian Magiſtrates,</hi> and <hi>Miniſters,</hi> that will not be obedient to the Heavenly call, (as you have for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly hinted) <hi>i. e.</hi> a final deſtruction, and total amotion of them together, and ſo <hi>Needhams</hi> Objection is anſwered with a wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and fully verified, <hi>i. e.</hi> 
                     <q>That the erecting or inſtituting of the Statutes and Judgements, annexed to the Moral Precept<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> will and is appointed by God to be the overthrow of all the Political Gouernments in the world,</q> and ſo I ſhall proceed to the <hi>third particular.</hi> But now it comes in my mind, I ſhall before I enter thereupon, deſire to compare our <hi>preſent Government with your Text,</hi> to the end we may ſee whether or no it be in the <hi>Black Bead-roll,</hi> that is, to receive the <hi>final deſtruction</hi> and <hi>total amotion you ſay muſt happen unto them.</hi> And for better Order ſake, I ſhall once more recite the words of your Text <hi>Heb.</hi> 27.</p>
                  <p>And this word <hi>once more,</hi> ſignifies the <hi>removing</hi> of thoſe things that are <hi>ſhaken,</hi> us of <hi>things that are made,</hi> that thoſe things that cannot be <hi>ſhaken</hi> may <hi>remain.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Argum.</hi> Now in theſe words it is <hi>notoriouſly p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ident</hi> to every <hi>Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional Man,</hi> that all ſuch <hi>Heavens</hi> and <hi>Earths,</hi> (or <hi>Political Forms of Government,</hi> which men have <hi>made for themſelves,</hi> as afore menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned by you) as are made (by ſuch means) <hi>ſhall be be ſhaken</hi> and <hi>removed,</hi> (i. e. by <hi>a fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>al deſtruct<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>n,</hi> and <hi>total <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="4 letters">
                           <desc>••••</desc>
                        </gap>tion,</hi> as you have alſo affirmed.)</p>
                  <pb n="56" facs="tcp:176196:33"/>
                  <p>But the <hi>preſent Government</hi> of this <hi>Nation</hi> was made his <hi>State-Policy</hi> or <hi>Humane Invention.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Ergo</hi> according to Mr. <hi>Owens Aſſertion</hi> and <hi>Atteſtation,</hi> the <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Government</hi> of this <hi>Nation,</hi> is to receive a <hi>final deſtruction</hi> and <hi>total amotion.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Proof.</hi> That the <hi>preſent Government of this Nation</hi> was made by <hi>State Policy</hi> or <hi>Humane Invention,</hi> I appeal to every <hi>rational man,</hi> ſure I am, it was neither <hi>made</hi> in <hi>Mount Sina,</hi> nor <hi>ratified</hi> in <hi>mount Olivet,</hi> unleſſe the <hi>Learned Doctour</hi> can prove the <hi>Cock-pit</hi> to be the <hi>one,</hi> and the <hi>Parliament-Houſe</hi> to be the <hi>other,</hi> (which I believe will ſtrain his Logick to the <hi>higheſt key.)</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Argument.</hi> Again from this Text it is alſo <hi>undeniably evident,</hi> that <hi>all ſuch Governments as may be ſhaken, muſt be alſo ſhaken</hi> and <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved,</hi> and that <hi>upon the Account of being made as aforeſaid.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But the <hi>preſent Government</hi> of <hi>Nation, is ſuch a Government,</hi> as <hi>may be ſhaken.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Therefore according to the <hi>Doctours Aſſertion,</hi> the preſent Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of this Nation, is to receive a final deſtruction, and total amotion.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Proof.</hi> That the <hi>preſent Government of this Nation is ſuch as may be ſhaken,</hi> I refer to the alterations, which the late Parliament, if they might have had their wills, would have made therein, and if it may be ſhaken by them, then conſequently by others, therefore a Government that may be ſhaken, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Argument.</hi> A third Argument may be drawn from the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctours own Aſſertions, who ſaith, that ſuch Magiſtrates as are either tyed by Oath, or other Compact to maintain either the whole or ſome part of the old Tower, under the Right of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Church-Prelacy or the like, (by which word <hi>like</hi> he intendeth <hi>Presbytery,</hi> as hath been ſhewed) that ſuch a Magiſtrate and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, is to be enumerated among <hi>Babylons</hi> Adherents, and conſequently to receive that, final deſtruction and total amotion as afore mentioned.</p>
                  <p>But the preſent <hi>governors</hi> &amp; <hi>government</hi> of this nation doth <hi>provide for the maintenance of the Presbyterian Miniſtry</hi> of the <hi>nation,</hi> which the Doctor looketh upon and judged as a part of <hi>Antichriſtian Hierar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy,</hi> witneſſe the terming them a <hi>Procruſts bed, a heavy yoke,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>Therefore the preſent Governours and Government of this
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:176196:33"/> Nation according to Mr. <hi>Owens</hi> Aſſertion, is to be enumerated as aforeſaid, and likewiſe to ſuffer as aforeſaid, and thus I ſhall proceed to the third particular, <hi>i. e.</hi> How, or in what manner, the Lord Chriſt will effect this <hi>final deſtruction</hi> and <hi>total amotion</hi> of all <hi>Politick,</hi> or <hi>Humane Forms of Government,</hi> 
                     <q>and in this parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular, the Learned Rabby ſhall plead for me in that <hi>notable Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mile,</hi> which he hath culled out of the Scriptures to that very end and purpoſe, <hi>i. e.</hi> Now as <hi>Sampſon.</hi> intending the Deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction <note place="margin">Vide p. 27 <hi>upon</hi> Heb. 12. 17.</note> of the Princes, Lords, and reſidue of the Philiſtines, who were gathered together in their <hi>Idol-Temple,</hi> he effected it by pulling away the Pillars, whereby the building was ſupported, whereupon the whole frame topled to the ground. So the Lord intending the Ruine of that mighty Power, whoſe top ſeems to reach Heaven, will do it by pulling away the Pillars and Supporters of it, after which it cannot ſtand one moment.—<hi>Sic tranſit gloria mundi.</hi>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Query.</hi> Doctour this hath been <hi>a ſtrange ſort of Language,</hi> and dangerous I will aſſure you, I wiſh you be not called in queſtion for it, but what are the <hi>Pillars</hi> of that <hi>fatal building,</hi> which muſt thus be <hi>ruinated</hi> with it.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Doct. Reſp.</hi> 
                     <q>Are they not the <hi>Powers</hi> of <hi>the world,</hi> as <hi>preſently ſtated</hi> and <hi>framed</hi> (implying they are) <hi>Pull them away,</hi> and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſſe what is Antichriſt? It is the <hi>Glory of Kings put upon her,</hi> that makes mens eyes <hi>dazle</hi> on that <hi>Roman Harlot,</hi> otherwiſe ſhe is but like the <hi>Egyptian Deities,</hi> who <hi>ſilly worſhippers,</hi> through many <hi>glorious portlets</hi> and <hi>Frontiſpices</hi> were led to <hi>adore the Image</hi> of an <hi>ugly Ape.</hi>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>Well <hi>Doct.</hi> Seeing you have in brief given me ſo <hi>full</hi> and <hi>am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſatisfaction</hi> in this <hi>particular,</hi> I ſhall proceed to the other, <hi>i. e.</hi> The Perſons by whom he will effect it.</p>
                  <p>To the knowledge of this particular the Holy Ghoſt doth plentifully inform us, <hi>i. e. By the moſt deſpicable inſtrument,</hi> as will appear by theſe following inſtances.</p>
                  <p>When the <hi>Iſrael of God</hi> muſt be delivered from the <hi>Egyptian bondage, Moſes</hi> muſt be preſerved by an <hi>Ark of Bul-ruſhes,</hi> and ſo <hi>bred up</hi> to that purpoſe. Again, when they were in great diſtreſſe by the <hi>Midianites,</hi> the Lord made choyce of <hi>Gedeon,</hi> a man of a poore Family in <hi>Manaſſeh,</hi> and <hi>Gedeon</hi> the leaſt or meaneſt of that Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:176196:34"/> 
                     <hi>Judg. 6. 15. &amp;c.</hi> After this, <hi>David</hi> the ſon of <hi>Jeſſe</hi> muſt be brought from the <hi>flock</hi> to vanquiſh <hi>Goliah,</hi> and the Army of the Philiſtines, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 17.</p>
                  <q>
                     <p>And thus the acting of Gods providence, in carrying on of <note place="margin">The Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly intereſt of Chi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ſt how mana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged.</note> the intereſt of Chriſt, as the Doctour ſaith, <hi>will be exceedingly un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuited to the Reaſonings and expectations of men in theſe dayes,</hi> as it was in the laying of the foundations of the Goſpel, or Prieſtly Office of Chriſt, where quite contrary to the expectations of the Jews, who then expected outward Glory, Beauty, Delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, Carnal Power and Dominion, God inſte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>d thereof produceth a poore man, that had not where to lay his head, (followed by a few Fiſhermen and ſimple women) that had neither Form not Comelineſſe, that he ſhould be deferred, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuted, <note place="margin">Mark 1. 16, 19. and 2. 14.</note> deſpiſed, crucified, from the beginning to the end, quite another thing than they looked for, and thus he laid the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of the Goſpel in the perſon of his ſon, by fruſtrating the expectations of the moſt of men, <hi>The ſtone, which the builders refuſed became the head of the corner.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Again, ſeeing Salvation is of the Jews, the rod of Chriſts ſtrength to be out of <hi>Sion,</hi> and that living waters were to flow <note place="margin">The prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>t <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap> inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>ſt of Chriſt how ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>aged.</note> forth from <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> the Goſpel being from thence to be pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed through the world. Who did the Lord chuſe to do it? Did he make uſe of the learned of the Nations? the high Prieſts, learned Scribes, devout Phariſes, that might have <hi>won their Meſſage ſome Repute and Credit in the World</hi> No, but <hi>quite con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">John 14. 16. and 25. 26, 27. Luk. 24. 48, 49. Act. 1. 4, 5. and 2. 1, 2, 3, 4, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                        </note> to all the wiſdome of the fleſh, he ſendeth <hi>his Propheti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>al Spirit</hi> upon a few <hi>ignorant,</hi> weak, <hi>unlearned</hi> Fiſhermen, <hi>deſpiſd up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on all accounts,</hi> and commits this <hi>great work to them,</hi> and accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly <hi>out they go,</hi> friendleſſe, <hi>helpleſſe, harbourleſſe</hi> unto their <hi>imployments, Acts</hi> 4. 13. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1. 20. 26, 27, 28. The like inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment hath the Lord Chriſt alſo for the moſt part imployed in making an entrance upon the great work of caſting down falſe worſhip and idolatry. <note place="margin">How the Kingly inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt of Christ ſhall be brought in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the world.</note> 
                     </p>
                  </q>
                  <p>And now in reference to the bringing in of the Kingly inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt of the Lord Jeſus into the world (which is to be accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the ruine and deſtruction, both of <hi>Pagan</hi> and <hi>Antichriſtian Babylon,</hi> with all their adherents, whether in reference to their <hi>Civil</hi> or <hi>Eccleſiaſtical governments,</hi> as hath been plentifully treated
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:176196:34"/> of) which muſt be done with might, power, and ſtrength, with <hi>Armies</hi> and <hi>Blood,</hi> Rev. 19. 11, 12, 13, 14, 15, 16, 17, 18. (where by the <hi>Iron Rod is meant the material ſword,</hi> yea, even that <hi>material</hi> ſword propheſied of <hi>Pſal.</hi> 2. 9. and 72. and 149. 6. <hi>Rev.</hi> 2. 27.) who will now the Lord make uſe of? will it be of <hi>Kings, Potentates, Nobles,</hi> and <hi>Great ones of the earth,</hi> no it is contrary even to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ſence that he ſhould; for as the Doctor hath well obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, it cannot be expected thoſe men ſhould take up the deſpiſed quarrel of the intereſt of Chriſt, and that for theſe Reaſons.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Becauſe they are ſuch as have given their powers and ſtates, and ſtrength unto the Beaſt, or to maintain Idolatrous or falſe worſhip, <hi>Rev</hi> 13. 1, 2. and 17. 12, 13, 14, 15, 16, 17. without which their <hi>Tyrannical Government cannot be keppt up.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. In that they have committed fornications with the Beaſt, as alſo their Subjects, <hi>Rev.</hi> 17. 1, 2.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. It is by them that ſhe is ſupported at this day, as hath been proved.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. For that it is declared by the <hi>Holy Ghoſt,</hi> that at the <hi>Ruine of Babylon, the Kings of the earth, who have committed fornication, and lived delitiouſly with her, ſhall bewail her, and lament for her,</hi> Rev. 10. 9. 20. as alſo the <hi>Merchants of the earth,</hi> as from v. 11. to v. 20. as alſo the Harpers, mufitians, pipers, and Trumpeters of <hi>Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon,</hi> i. e. all her dependents, and therefore it is contrary to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ſence, that they ſhould be active in her deſtruction, <hi>Rev.</hi> 6. 15, 16, 17.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. In that this Supper of the Lamb, or the day of Chriſts power, the fowls that fly in the <hi>middeſt of heaven</hi> are invited to eat of the <hi>Fleſh of Kings</hi> and the <hi>fleſh of Captains,</hi> and the <hi>Fleſh of mighty men,</hi> and the <hi>Fleſh of Horſes,</hi> and <hi>them that ſit on them,</hi> and the Fleſh of all men, both free and bond, ſmall and great.</p>
                  <p>Therefore it is impoſſible, that they ſhould be inſtrumental for Chriſt againſt <hi>Babylon,</hi> but contrary-wiſe, <hi>antagoniſts</hi> thereunto, which with the former Reaſons given by the Doctor, <hi>doth clearly hold forth,</hi> that the Lord Jeſus will not make uſe of any of the <hi>preſent authorities</hi> or <hi>powers of the world,</hi> to bring this utter de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation upon <hi>Babylon, for in ſo doing, they ſhould fight againſt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Object.</hi> The Text ſaith peremptorily, that the ten horns ſhall
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:176196:35"/> hate the Whore, and make her deſolate and naked, and ſhall eat her Fleſh, and burn her with fire, which manifeſtly implies, that the horns ſhall continue till her deſtruction, if not longer, and that they ſhall be the notable inſtruments that God will make uſe of in her Ruine.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Reſp.</hi> The ſpirit of God in the Scriptures, <hi>doth not claſh againſt it ſelf</hi> in this particular any more, than where it ſaith, we are <hi>juſtified</hi> by works and not by faith onely, <hi>Jam.</hi> 1. 24, 25. as alſo by faith without the deeds of the Law, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3. 18. as alſo <hi>freely by grace,</hi> v. 24, <hi>Tit,</hi> 3. 7. the firſt being a <hi>viſible</hi> or <hi>demonſtrative Juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation,</hi> the ſecond <hi>a Juſtification</hi> in a mans <hi>own Spirit,</hi> and the third <hi>a Teſtification</hi> of the <hi>Spirit of God,</hi> evidencing or <hi>witneſſing the truth thereof,</hi> wrought by Chriſt <hi>to that ſpirit of man,</hi> Rom. 8 16. So in <hi>this particular,</hi> where the <hi>ten horns</hi> are ſaid ſhall <hi>hate the Whore,</hi> &amp;c. I ſay, <hi>is impoſſible</hi> it ſhould be meant of theſe very horns, that I have mentioned for thoſe Reaſons I have laid down, and therefore it muſt <hi>unavoidably</hi> be meant <hi>of ſome other Horne, (viz.</hi> powers) as by the Lords aſſiſtance I ſhall prove from <hi>Rev. cap.</hi> 17. in v. 12. of which chapter it is ſaid, <hi>The ten horns which thou ſaweſt are ten Kings, which have received no Kingdome as yet, but receive power as Kings<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> one houre with the beaſt: theſe ſhall make war with the Lamb, and the Lamb ſhall overcome them.</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Gedeons <hi>number from</hi> 32000 <hi>to</hi> 300. <hi>Read</hi> Judges 1. <hi>&amp;c. and ſee if you be</hi> Lappers; <hi>for the Lord will ſave Iſrael by no other. Such as have burn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Lamps in their earthen pitchers, in the earthly tabernacles of their fl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ſh</hi>
                     </note> 
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Reaſ.</hi> 
                     <q>For he is Lord of Lords, and King of Kings, and they that are with him, are called, and choſen, and faithful, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Note</hi> 1. The three characters of the Lambs army, leaſt any pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume to come to the <hi>Marriage Supper,</hi> to eat the Fleſh of Kings and Captains, <hi>Rev.</hi> 19. 17, 18. without <hi>a wedding garm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>nt, vide Luke</hi> 14. to this purpoſe, from v. 15. to v. 25. <hi>Mat.</hi> 22. from v. 1. to v. 15, for <hi>many</hi> will be <hi>called,</hi> but <hi>few choſen,</hi> they muſt be <hi>ſuch</hi> as will <hi>forſake all to follow the Lamb where ever he goeth,</hi> you ſee what became of the <hi>Merchants, Farmers,</hi> and <hi>effeminate perſons,</hi> they muſt be ſuch, as if they have <hi>not a ſword, they muſt ſell their coat and buy one,</hi> Luk. 22. 36. they muſt be ſuch, as will leave the dead to bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry their dead, <hi>Mat.</hi> 8. 22. ſuch as will beat their plow-ſhares into ſwords, and their pruning hooks into ſpears, ſuch as of weak, are made ſtrong, <hi>Joel 12. 3. &amp;c.</hi> but to the matter in hand.</p>
                  <p>I ſay, that by the afore mentioned Scripture it <hi>doth clearly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> that the <hi>Battel</hi> betwixt the <hi>Kings of the earth,</hi> and the <hi>Lamb</hi>
                     <pb n="61" facs="tcp:176196:35"/> and his Army, is to be fought, <hi>before they are ſaid to hate the Whore,</hi> &amp;c. as in v. 16. untill which time <hi>God hath put it into their hearts, to fulfill his will, and to give their Kingdome unto the beaſt, untill the word of God ſhall be fulfilled, v.</hi> 17. So that I gather from hence, That as the <hi>Conqueſt of the Lambs Army</hi> extends it ſelf over the <hi>Dominions of the Beaſt,</hi> and her ſupporters, <hi>(viz.</hi> The <hi>Civil Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, and Governments of the earth,</hi> with their <hi>people and multitudes</hi> implyed by the <hi>waters</hi> on which the <hi>whore ſitteth) v.</hi> 15. 1. and that the <hi>Laws, Statutes, Judgements</hi> and <hi>Ordinances</hi> of Jehovah the Lord Chriſt <hi>is planted inſtead thereof,</hi> by ſo much the ſaid <hi>Nations</hi> or <hi>earthly powers,</hi> ſhall be ſaid to <hi>hate the whore,</hi> and make her <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolate and naked, and eat her fleſh, and burn her with fire,</hi> that is, they ſhall ſee ſo much <hi>excellency</hi> in thoſe <hi>Laws, Statutes, Judgements,</hi> and <hi>Ordinances,</hi> beyond all what they <hi>injoyed</hi> under their former <hi>Governments,</hi> as that they ſhall abhor and det<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſt both their <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours</hi> and <hi>Governments,</hi> whether <hi>Civil</hi> or <hi>Eccleſiaſtical,</hi> the one <hi>ſurmounting</hi> the other, <hi>as far</hi> as the light of the Moon excels the <hi>ſmalleſt ſtar.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>When they ſhall have Judges as at the firſt, and Rulers as at the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning,</hi> Iſa. 1. 26. <hi>Not the Arbitrary powers of the Kings of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,</hi> which were brought into the <hi>Common-wealth of Iſrael,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the mind of God, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 8. as for <hi>Saul</hi> to take their ſons, and appoint them for himſelf, for his Chariots and for his Horſemen, and ſome to run before his Chariot (or to make <hi>foot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boyes of free born Iſraelites)</hi> to appoint Captains over thouſands, and Captains over fifties, to eare his ground, and to reap har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſt, and to make his inſtruments of war, to take their daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters to be confectionaries, and to be <hi>Cooks</hi> and to be <hi>Bakers,</hi> to take their <hi>fields</hi> and their <hi>vineyards,</hi> and their <hi>Olive-yards,</hi> even the b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſt of them, and give them to his ſervants, to take the tenths of their ſeed, and of their vineyards, and give them unto his Officers and to his ſervants, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> No, the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> knew no ſuch ſervitude in <hi>Samuels</hi> dayes, if they had, Surely <hi>Samuel would not have ſet that Goverment before them as ſo ſtrange a thing:</hi> No, <hi>honeſt</hi> Samuel (who could ſay in the <hi>integrity of his heart, whoſe ox have I taken, or whoſe Aſſe have I taken, or whom have Y defranded)</hi> uſed no ſuch <hi>Tyranny,</hi> Good man he could <hi>govern the people</hi> without a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of theſe <hi>Kickſhaws,</hi> neither do we read of any of the <hi>Judges
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:176196:36"/> of Iſrael,</hi> that ever kept a ſtanding <hi>Army,</hi> notwithſtanding they were invironed with enemies on every ſide, but that when need required they unanimouſly joyned themſelves together for the defence of each other; and ſo freed themſelves from expence in that kinde: neither do I ever read of one Tax that ever was laid by the Judges of Iſrael.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. When <hi>violence</hi> ſhall be no more heard in the land, nor waſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing or deſtruction within our borders, when the walls ſhall be called <hi>ſalvation,</hi> and the <hi>Gates praiſe: Iſa. 60. verſ.</hi> 18. when <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem</hi> ſhall be <hi>a quiet habitation,</hi> a Tabernacle that ſhall not be taken down, nor one of the Stakes thereof be removed; nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther any of the cords thereof broken, when the glory of the Lord ſhall be unto us <hi>a place of broad rivers</hi> and <hi>ſtreams,</hi> wherein ſhall go no Gally with Ore, neither gallant ſhip paſſe thereby: (no need then of the <hi>Romiſh Merchants,</hi> or <hi>Factors,</hi> for no m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n will then buy her Merchandiſe any more, <hi>Rev.</hi> 18. 11.)</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Reaſ.</hi> For the Lord is our Judge, The Lord is our <hi>Law-giver</hi> the Lord is our King, <hi>He will ſave us.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3. When our officers ſhall be peace, and our exactors Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reouſnes <hi>Iſa.</hi> 60. 18. when they ſhall be ſuch as <hi>fear God, and hate covetouſnes;</hi> men of <hi>truth,</hi> that will not <hi>reſpect perſons in judgment, but ſhall hear the ſmall as well as the great,</hi> Deut. 1. 17. when the judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſhall not be mans, but the Lords: when the people ſhall ſay, The Lord bleſſe thee, <hi>O habitation of juſtice, and mountain of holineſſe,</hi> i. e. <hi>the Civil and Church Government.</hi> I ſay when the Nations who are <hi>now under the Dominions of the Antichriſtian Babylon,</hi> ſhall <hi>once ſee</hi> and <hi>finde the difference betwixt this</hi> Governments, <hi>I have here given a ſmall glimps of, and the</hi> preſent Idolatrous and tyrannical domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions they are now <hi>ſlaves</hi> and <hi>bondmen unto;</hi> they ſhall then begin to <hi>hate the Whore, and make her naked and deſolate, and ſhall eate her fleſh, and burn her with fire:</hi> And note that is to be <hi>rationally concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved,</hi> that the <hi>ten horns</hi> ſhall all at <hi>once</hi> ſtand looking upon the <hi>City of Rome</hi> lamenting over it, to ſee it on fire, and yet <hi>to have a bond in that her deſtruction:</hi> which conflict betwixt the <hi>Lamb</hi> and the <hi>Beaſt,</hi> I conceive doth take its riſe at the <hi>Dominion of the little Horn, Dan. 7. 8, &amp;c.</hi> and ſhall be determined at the <hi>Armageddon battel, Rev.</hi> 16. 13, 14, 15, 16. at which time we are to <hi>expect the coming of Chriſt</hi> as a thief in the night.</p>
                  <pb n="63" facs="tcp:176196:36"/>
                  <p>Again, That the Inſtruments, which the Lord Jeſus will make uſe of in this great deſign, ſhall be <hi>poore contemptible perſons,</hi> ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e Iſa. 41. 14, 15, 16. <hi>fear not thou worm Jacob, &amp;c. I will help thee ſaith the Lord, &amp;c. Behold, I will make thee a new threſhing inſtrument, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving teeth, thou ſhalt threſh the mountains and beat them ſmall; thou ſhalt make the hits chaffe, thou ſhalt fan them, and the winde ſhall car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry them away, and the whirl-winde ſhall ſcatter them. And that this hath an alluſion to</hi> Giddeon <hi>the Threſher, and his army.</hi> Read Iſa. 10. Where the Lord ſpeaking of the <hi>deliverance</hi> of his people from the <hi>Aſſyrians,</hi> or <hi>Babyloniſh</hi> bondage or <hi>ſervitude,</hi> ſaith, v. 24. <hi>Thus ſaith the Lord God of Hoaſts, O my people that dwelleth in Sion, be not affraid of the Aſſyrian, he ſhall ſmite thee with a rod, and ſhall lift up his ſtaffe againſt thee after the manner of Aegypt:</hi> For yet <hi>a very little while,</hi> and the <hi>indignation</hi> ſhall <hi>ceaſe,</hi> and mine anger in their deſtruction: And the Lord of hoaſt ſhall ſtir up a ſcourge for him according to the <hi>ſlaughter of Median,</hi> at the <hi>Rock Oreb, &amp;c.</hi> And it ſhall come to paſſe In that day that his burthen ſhall be taken off from thy ſhoulders, and his yoak from off thy neck: and the yoak ſhall be <hi>deſtroyed</hi> becauſe of the <hi>annointing.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Again, Dan. 2. 34. <hi>Thou ſaweſt till a ſtone was cut without hands</hi> (or which was not in hands) <hi>which ſmote the image upon his feet,</hi> th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t were of <hi>Iron</hi> and <hi>clay,</hi> and brake them in pieces: Then was the <hi>Iron,</hi> the <hi>clay,</hi> the <hi>braſſe,</hi> the <hi>ſilver,</hi> and the <hi>gold,</hi> broken in pieces together, and became like the <hi>chaffe</hi> of the ſummer threſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing floor; and the winde carried them away, and the whirle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d ſcattered them, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Again, that theſe <hi>deſpicable perſons</hi> ſhall be the <hi>Saints</hi> of the <hi>moſt high,</hi> vid Pſal. 149. Let the <hi>Saints</hi> be joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full in glory; let them ſing aloud upon their beds: Let the high praiſes of God be in their mouths, and a <hi>two edged ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ord</hi> in their <hi>hands,</hi> to execute vengeance upon the Heathen, and puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments upon the people; To binde <hi>their Kings</hi> in chains, <hi>and</hi> heir <hi>Nobles</hi> with <hi>fetters of Iron,</hi> to execute <hi>upon them</hi> the judgement written: <hi>This honour have all his Saints, praiſe ye the Lord, Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Again, <hi>Dan.</hi> 7. 17, 18. Theſe <hi>great beaſts,</hi> which are four Kings, which ſhall riſe out of the earth; but the Saints of the <hi>moſt high,</hi> ſhall take the Kingdome, and poſſeſſe the Kingdome for ever and ever. Verſ. 21, 22. I beheld, and the ſame horn <hi>(viz.</hi> the <hi>little<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horn, Dan.</hi> 7. 8.) made the war with the Saints, and prevailed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:176196:37"/> them, untill the ancient of dayes, and judgment was gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to the Saints of the moſt high, and the <hi>time come</hi> that the <hi>Saints poſſeſſed the Kingdom. Verſ.</hi> 25. And he, (i. e. the little horn) ſhall ſpeak great words <hi>againſt</hi> the <hi>moſt High,</hi> and ſhall wear out the <hi>Saints</hi> of the <hi>moſt High,</hi> and ſhall think to change times and laws, and they ſhall be given into his hands, untill a <hi>time,</hi> and <hi>times,</hi> and the dividing of <hi>time,</hi> (which I conceive to be, 3 <hi>years and a half,</hi> i. e. from the <hi>firſt entrance</hi> of <hi>his Dominion,</hi> at which time) <hi>Judgment</hi> ſhall ſit (i. e. at the <hi>end</hi> of the 3 <hi>years and a half:)</hi> And (then) they <hi>(i. e.</hi> the Saints) ſhall <hi>take away his dominion,</hi> To <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume</hi> and <hi>deſtroy</hi> it, unto the <hi>end. Verſ.</hi> 27. And the Kingdome, and greatneſſe of the Kingdome, <hi>under</hi> the <hi>whole heavens</hi> (the <hi>Quakers</hi> will have a <hi>large Gut,</hi> to <hi>hold this Kingdome and Dominion)</hi> ſhall be given to the people of the Saints of the moſt High; whoſe kingdome is an everlaſting kingdome, <hi>and all dominions ſhall ſerve and obey him.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Iſa.</hi> 60. 12. That Nation and Kingdome, which will not ſerve thee ſhall be broken in pieces, that is ſaith the learned Doctor: All the Nations of the earth, not a <hi>known nation,</hi> but the <hi>blood of the Saints of Chriſt is found in the skirt thereof;</hi> and yet all this (ſaith he) ſhall be <hi>tranſacted</hi> with ſo much <hi>obſcurity</hi> and <hi>darkneſſe,</hi> Chriſt not <hi>openly appearing unto carnal eyes,</hi> that though <hi>many</hi> ſhall be <hi>purified</hi> and <hi>made white,</hi> yet the <hi>wicked</hi> ſhall do <hi>wickedly,</hi> and <hi>none</hi> of the wicked ſhall underſtand, but the <hi>wiſe</hi> ſhall underſtand <hi>Dan.</hi> 12. 10.</p>
                  <p>There ſhall be <hi>no ſuch demonſtration of Chriſt preſence,</hi> as to <hi>open the eyes of hardned men,</hi> but at length having ſuffered the <hi>poore decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved wretches, to drink of the Cup prepared for them: He appears himſelf gloriouſly,</hi> cap. 19. 13. in a more e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>inent manner than ever before, to the <hi>totall deſtruction</hi> of the <hi>reſidue of</hi> oppoſers, and this will be the <hi>utmoſt cloſe of that diſpenſation,</hi> which he <hi>now beginneth to ſtir up the hearts of his Saints unto,</hi> i. e. <hi>to execute the vengeance written,</hi> and to which purpoſe he hath alſo <hi>commiſſionated them,</hi> Rev. 18. 6, 7, 8. But before I ſpeak to the <hi>Commiſſion,</hi> it is worthy of our <hi>beſt obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation,</hi> to take notice of the <hi>juſt</hi> and <hi>righteous dealings</hi> of God unto the <hi>inhabitants of Babylon:</hi> for I ſay before he giveth out his <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion</hi> to his Saints, (who are to judge the world) 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6. 2. and to be the <hi>rod of his ſtrength,</hi> Pſal. 110. 2. <hi>His battel-Axe, weapon of
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:176196:37"/> war will break in pieces the horſe and his rider,</hi> &amp;c. Jer. 51. 20. 21, &amp;c. he doth in the firſt place ſend his Meſſengers from his Churches with great power to enlighten them with his Glory, crying mightily with a ſtrong voice, ſaying, <hi>Babylon is fallen, is fallen, and is become the habitation of Devils, and the hold of every ſoul ſpirit, and a cage of every unclean and hatefull bird.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Reaſ.</hi> 
                     <q>For all nations have drunk of the wrath of the wine of her fornication, and the Kings of the earth have committed fornica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion with her, and the Merchants of the earth are waxen rich through the abundance of her delicates, and this I take to be by way of <hi>Aggravation,</hi> to ſhew her <hi>abominations,</hi> and how ripe ſhe is for <hi>Judgement</hi> and <hi>executions,</hi> as alſo to ſtrike <hi>a terrour in the hearts of the people of God, that are yet in her,</hi> of what rank ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver:</q> which having done in 4. and 5. v. he ſendeth other <hi>Meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers</hi> to call the people of God out of her, ſaying, <hi>Come out of her my people,</hi> God hath his people in <hi>Babylon.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Reaſon.</hi> 1. That ye do not <hi>partake</hi> of her <hi>Sinnes.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>2. That ye <hi>receive</hi> not of her <hi>Plagues.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Thoſe then that <hi>partake of her ſins,</hi> ſhall <hi>rrceive of her plagues.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Reaſon.</hi> For her ſins have reached unto heaven, and God hath remembred her iniquity after which fair warning he forthwith giveth his Commiſſion to his Saints, in theſe words, <q>Reward <note place="margin">The Saints Commiſſion againſt Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon and all her ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herents.</note> her as ſhe rewarded you, and double unto her double accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to her works: in the cup which ſhe hath filled fill to her double: how much ſhe hath glorified her ſelf, and lived deliti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly ſo much Torment and Sorrow give her.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Reaſon.</hi> For me ſaith in her heart, <hi>I ſit a Queen and am no widow, and ſhall ſee no ſorrow, Therefore ſhall her Plagues come in one day,</hi> (viz. this day of vengeance) <hi>Death,</hi> and <hi>mourning</hi> and <hi>famine,</hi> and ſhe ſhall be <hi>utterly burnt with fire.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Reaſon.</hi> 
                     <q>For ſtrong is the Lord God that judgeth her,</q> ſo, that it is clear, this Judgement and Vengeance is to be inflict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon <hi>Babylon</hi> and her adherents by way of recompence, for the further confirmation whereof, ſee theſe following Scriptures <hi>id eſt,</hi> 
                     <q>
                        <bibl>
                           <hi>Pſalme</hi> 2. 4, 5.</bibl> He that ſitteth in Heaven ſhall laugh, the Lord ſhall have them in deriſion, then ſhall he ſpeak unto them, <hi>(viz.</hi> to the Kings of the earth and the Rulers, v. 2.) in his wrath, and vex them in his ſore diſpleaſure,</q> 
                     <q>
                        <bibl>
                           <hi>Pſal.</hi> 139 8, 9.</bibl>
                        <pb n="66" facs="tcp:176196:38"/> O Daughter of <hi>Babylon,</hi> who art to be deſtroyed, happy ſhall he be that rewardeth thee as thou haſt ſerved us, happy ſhall he be that taketh and daſheth thy little ones againſt the ſtones,</q> 
                     <q>
                        <bibl>
                           <hi>Iſa.</hi> 54.</bibl> For my ſword ſhall be bathed in heaven, <hi>(viz.</hi> in the <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gans</hi> and Antichriſtian heaven or Church) <hi>Behold it ſhall come down upon</hi> Idumea <hi>and upon the people of my curſe to Judgement. The ſword of the Lord is filled with blood, it is made fat with fatneſſe,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>and the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>
                           <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicorns ſhall come down with them, and the Bullocks with the Bulls,</hi> and <hi>their Land ſhall be ſoaked with blood, and their duſt made fat with fatneſſe.</hi>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>Reaſon. <hi>For it is the day of the Lords vengeance,</hi> and the <hi>year of recompence,</hi> for the <hi>Controverſies of Sion,</hi> &amp;c. (the remainder of that cup) <hi>Iſa.</hi> 47. 1, 2, 3. <hi>Come down and ſit in the duſt, O Virgin, daughter of Babylon, ſit on the ground, there are no thrones, O daughter of the Caldeans, for thou ſhalt no more be called the tender and delicate, take the Milſtone and grind meal, and cover thy locks,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Thy naked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe ſhall be uncovered, yea, thy ſhame ſhall be ſeen, I will take ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>vid. cap.</hi> 49. 26, <hi>Jer.</hi> 50, 35, 36. A ſword upon the Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deans-ſaith the Lord, and upon the <hi>Inhabitants</hi> of <hi>Babylon,</hi> and upon her <hi>Princes,</hi> and upon her <hi>wiſe men,</hi> a ſword is upon their <hi>ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, (viz.</hi> her <hi>Aſtrologers, &amp;c.)</hi> they ſhall <hi>dote.</hi> A ſword upon her mighty men, (her Army-men) and they ſhall be <hi>diſmayed.</hi> A ſword upon their <hi>Horſes</hi> and their <hi>Chariots,</hi> and upon all the mingled people, good and bad that ſhall be found in her, <hi>Rev.</hi> 18. 4.) and <hi>they</hi> ſhall become as <hi>women</hi> (there will be no fear of <hi>Lao<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diceans,</hi> the <hi>Meroſh</hi> 
                     <note n="*" place="margin">As in the Epistle.</note> 
                     <hi>Churches,</hi> that hath <hi>one word</hi> for <hi>God,</hi> and <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother</hi> for <hi>Baal,</hi> of thoſe that halt between Chriſt and Antichriſt, that can ſwallow a Parſonage, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and yet be a Church-gather<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, in the world, and not of the world, the <hi>Hocus Pocus</hi> Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians of the times) A ſword upon the <hi>Treaſurers</hi> and they ſhall be <hi>robbed,</hi> (it will be an ill day with <hi>Treaſurers it ſeems,</hi> let them therefore look to it) A drought upon her <hi>Waiters,</hi> i. e. her Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy men of <hi>all ſorts</hi> and <hi>ſiſes, vid.</hi> Rev. 18.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Reaſon.</hi> For it is a Land of <hi>graven Images, (i. e.</hi> either of <hi>Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try</hi> or <hi>Tyranny)</hi> and they are mad upon their Idols,</p>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Jer.</hi> 5. 30. 31.</bibl> Therefore the wild beaſt; of the Deſart, with the wild beaſts of the Iſland ſhall dwell there, and the owls ſhall dwell therein, and it ſhall be no more inhabited for ever, neither ſhall it be
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:176196:38"/> dwelt in from generation to generation, as God overthrew <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Gomorrhah,</hi> and the <hi>Neighbour Cities</hi> thereof, ſaith the Lord, ſo ſhall no man abide there, <hi>neither ſhall any ſon of man dwell therein.</hi>
                  </q>
                  <p>Again, the Lord ſpeaking of his people, <hi>(Jer. 51. &amp;c)</hi> ſaith, <q>I will render unto Babylon, and to all the inhabitants of Caldea all theſe evils they have done unto <hi>Sion</hi> in your ſight, ſaith the Lord, Behold I am againſt thee O deſtroyinng Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, ſaith the Lord, which deſtroyeſt all the earth, and I will ſtretch out my hand upon thee, and roll thee down from the Rocks, and will make thee a burnt mountain, [<hi>Note</hi>] and they ſhall not take of thee a ſtone for a corner, nor for a foundation,</q> (not the leaſt grain of humane invention, either in things ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertaining to Babylon) whether in its Civill or Eccleſiaſticall e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate, where the Lord hath given a c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ear and expreſſe command himſelf, <hi>But thou ſhalt be deſolate for ever, ſaith the Lord.</hi> Zach. 12. 2. <hi>Behold, I will make Jeruſalem a cup of trembling unto all people round about it,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>and in that day will I make Jeruſalem a burdenſome ſtone,</hi> for all people that <hi>burden themſelves with it, ſhall be cut in pieces,</hi> though <hi>all the people of the earth be gathered together againſt it,</hi> in that day, ſaith the Lord, will I ſmite <hi>every <note n="*" place="margin">Mat. 18. 7. Luke 17. 1. 2.</note> horſe</hi> with <hi>aſtoniſhment,</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Note.</note> and his <hi>Rider</hi> with <hi>madneſſe,</hi> (no great fear then of ſuch <hi>Horſes</hi> and <hi>Riders,</hi> for it ſeems both <hi>Horſe</hi> and <hi>Man</hi> will be <hi>confounded to move</hi> againſt the <hi>Holy, juſt and perfect Laws of Jehovah the Lord Chriſt)</hi> if they do, <hi>woe</hi> and <hi>ſadneſſe</hi> will be unto them, yea, it had been better that a <hi>Milſtone</hi> had been tyed about their neck, and that they had been caſt into the bottome of the ſea, than to offend one of thoſe little ones, that ſhall be made inſtrumentall for <hi>Babylons</hi> deſtruction.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Rev. 6. 12. &amp;c.</hi> And I <hi>beheld</hi> when he had opened the <hi>ſixth Seal,</hi> and loe there was a great earthquake, and the <hi>Sun</hi> became <hi>black</hi> as <hi>ſackcloth of hair,</hi> and the <hi>Moon</hi> became as <hi>blood</hi> and the <hi>ſtarres of</hi> heaven fell unto the earth, even as a fig-tree <hi>caſteth</hi> her <hi>untimely figges,</hi> when ſhe is <hi>ſhaken</hi> with a <hi>mighty wind,</hi> and the heavens de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted as a <hi>ſcroll,</hi> that is, <hi>rolled together,</hi> and every mountain and Iſland were moved out of their places, and the <hi>Kings of the earth,</hi> and the <hi>greatmen,</hi> and the <hi>rich men</hi> (Weep and howl you rich men, for the miſeries that are now coming upon you, for your <hi>riches</hi>
                     <pb n="68" facs="tcp:176196:39"/> are corrupted, and your <hi>Garments moth-eaten,</hi> your gold and ſilver is canckred, and the ruſt of them ſhall be <hi>a witneſſe againſt you,</hi> and ſhall eat your fleſh as it were with fine, <hi>Jam. 5. 1 &amp;c. Ye have heaped treaſure together for the laſt dayes,</hi> &amp;c.) and chief Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains, <hi>(i. e.</hi> Generals, Lieutenant-Generals, Commiſſary-Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rals, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and Colonels of Armies,) and the mighty men (whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in point of honour or eſtate) hid themſelves in the <hi>dennes,</hi> and in the <hi>Rocks of the mountains,</hi> and ſaid unto the <hi>Mountains</hi> and <hi>Rocks,</hi> fall on us, and hide us from the wrath of the <hi>Lamb.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Reaſon.</hi> For the <hi>Greateſt day</hi> of <hi>his wrath is come, and who ſhall be able to ſtand: (Repent therefore, that your ſinnes may be blotted out at the day of refreſhing of the Lords people from himſelf, leſt he tear you in pieces, and there be none to deliver you,</hi> and know it will be <hi>a fearfull thing to fall into the hands of the great God of heaven and earth,</hi> the Lord in much mercy ſet theſe theſe things home upon your hearts and ſouls, leſt you <hi>be found fighters againſt the Lord of Hoſts, the God of Battel, who is able to conſume you with the blaſt of his noſtrils.)</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Laſtly, as to the means whereby theſe great tranſactions ſhall be accompliſhed by the poore, weak, few, and contemptible number of the Army of the Lamb, the <hi>Learned Doctour Owen</hi> hath given us a <hi>brief</hi> and <hi>full anſwer, (i. e.)</hi> Such as are the things <hi>ſhaken, ſuch</hi> muſt their <hi>ſhaking</hi> be, <hi>i. e. Spiritual,</hi> if <hi>Spiritual, Natural,</hi> if <hi>Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, Civil</hi> if <hi>Civil,</hi> &amp; hence it is, that the <hi>great Champion of the truth</hi> is diſcovered unto us, by theſe following characters, <hi>i. e.</hi> And I ſaw (ſaith <hi>John)</hi> and <hi>behold</hi> a <hi>white Horſe,</hi> and he that ſat upon him, was <hi>called faithful,</hi> and <hi>true,</hi> (note this fifth Monarchy-man) and in <hi>Righteouſneſſe</hi> doth he <hi>judge</hi> and make <hi>war,</hi> his eyes were as a <hi>Flame of Fire,</hi> and on his <hi>Head</hi> were many <hi>Crowns,</hi> and he had a <hi>Name written</hi> that no man knew, <hi>but himſelf,</hi> and he was clothed with a veſture <hi>dipt in blood, and his Name is called the Word of God.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Note.</hi> The Word of God muſt then be the <hi>Rule</hi> and <hi>Sinew</hi> of all the <hi>Actions</hi> of the <hi>fifth Monarchy men,</hi> they muſt onely execute the <hi>Judgement written,</hi> bringing all the actions of <hi>Babylon</hi> and her <hi>Adherents</hi> to the <hi>Touchſtone of the Scriptures,</hi> as for example in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference to the <hi>Political Government of the World,</hi> they are to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce <hi>Jam. 4. 12. There is one Law-giver, who is able to ſave, and to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy;</hi>
                     <pb n="69" facs="tcp:176196:39"/> and from thence demand of the <hi>Civil Magiſtrate,</hi> by what <hi>Rule</hi> or <hi>Authority</hi> he maketh his <hi>own Laws,</hi> ſeeing he petends him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf a <hi>Miniſter</hi> or <hi>Servant</hi> unto the alone <hi>Law-maker,</hi> and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently to put his <hi>Laws in-execution,</hi> and thus they will be ſtruck as <hi>dumb</hi> as <hi>doore nails,</hi> for in this caſe they have nothing <hi>to plead,</hi> but the authority and <hi>cuſtome of their Anceſtours,</hi> and their Ance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors from <hi>Nimrod,</hi> and <hi>Nimrod</hi> from the <hi>Apoſtate ſons of God in the old world,</hi> and they from the <hi>Corruption and vain imaginations of fall'n man,</hi> and fall'n man from the <hi>ſuggeſtions and deluſions of Satan,</hi> and ſo <hi>primarily from the Devil.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Again in point of Eccleſiaſtical Government and Doctrine, the fifth Monarchy-men are to produce, <hi>Mat. 15. 8. In vain do ye worſhip me, teaching for doctrine the Traditions or commandements of men,</hi> and ſo keep them cloſe to the word of God, and not to ſuffer them to continue as they are, <hi>i. e.</hi> partly <hi>Jure Divino,</hi> and partly <hi>Jure Humano,</hi> as the <hi>Presbyterians</hi> do acknowledge their Government to be, and ſo down with it <hi>even to the ground,</hi> for being found in <hi>Babylon, they and their Government muſt be deſtroyed with Babylon,</hi> as the learned Doctour hath <hi>aſſerted,</hi> and <hi>clearly proved, and ſo conſequently</hi> to all other <hi>falſe worſhips, or Governments whatſoever:</hi> and hence it is, that the <hi>Lambs followers</hi> are ſaid to be <hi>clothed in white Linnen,</hi> white and clean, all their Acts will be done in <hi>truth</hi> and <hi>righteouſneſſe,</hi> the white Linnen is the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe of the Saints, <hi>Rev.</hi> 19. 8. 2. And out of his <hi>mouth</hi> goeth a <hi>ſharp ſword,</hi> that with it he ſhould ſmite the <hi>Nations,</hi> and he ſhall <hi>rule them</hi> with a <hi>Rod of iron:</hi> here we ſee, the <hi>word</hi> maketh way for the <hi>material ſword,</hi> which the <hi>Rod of iron</hi> doth clearly <hi>import,</hi> ſo that as the Doctour ſaith, the <hi>Civil part of Antichriſt</hi> muſt be <hi>conquered</hi> with the <hi>iron Rod,</hi> and the <hi>Eccleſiaſtical</hi> part with the <hi>ſword that proceedeth out of the Lambs mouth, (viz.)</hi> the <hi>Holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures,</hi> and this doth further appear from <hi>Pſal.</hi> 149. 6, 7, 8, 9. as alſo from the following words of the afornamed chapter of <hi>Rev. 19. i. e.</hi> v. 17, 18, 19, 20. which muſt unavoidably be applyed to the Conqueſt of the <hi>material ſword,</hi> in that (the other, <hi>i. e.)</hi> the remnant are ſaid to be <hi>ſlain,</hi> with the <hi>ſword of him</hi> that ſate upon the <hi>Horſe, which ſword proceedeth out of his mouth,</hi> as in v. 13. as al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo in v. 16.</p>
                  <p>And therefore O <hi>Babylon,</hi> whether <hi>Pagan</hi> or <hi>Antichriſtian,</hi> I do
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:176196:40"/> hereby in the name of the <hi>Lord Jeſus bid defiance to thee,</hi> in whom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever thou refideſt, whether by <hi>Idolatry</hi> or <hi>falſe worſhip,</hi> or whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by <hi>Tyranny</hi> or <hi>cruel Dominion,</hi> being in oppoſition to the two grand Principles of nature, <hi>i. e.</hi> of <hi>loving God above all,</hi> and <hi>our neigbours as our ſelves,</hi> and conſequently to the bringing of the <hi>unmovable Laws</hi> and <hi>Ordinances</hi> of the <hi>unmovable Kingdome</hi> of the Lord Jeſus <hi>upon earth,</hi> and now in daily expectation by his <hi>Saints,</hi> and therefore I adviſe thee, (as the Lord did <hi>Niniveh</hi> by the Prophet <hi>Nahum)</hi> to conſider, <q>Art thou better than <hi>Populus No-Ammon</hi> that was <hi>ſituate among the Rivers</hi> that had the waters round about it, whoſe Rampart was the ſea, and her wall was from the ſea, <hi>Ethiopia</hi> and <hi>Egypt</hi> were her ſtrength, and it was infinite, <hi>Put</hi> and <hi>Lubim</hi> were the helpers, yet was ſhe carried away, ſhe went ino captivity, her young children were alſo daſhed in pieces at the top of all the ſtreets, and they caſt lots for their <hi>Honourable men,</hi> and all her great men were bound in chains, thou alſo ſhalt be <hi>drunken,</hi> thou ſhalt <hi>be hid,</hi> thou alſo ſhalt <hi>ſeek ſtrength</hi> becauſe of <hi>the enemy,</hi> and all thy <hi>ſtrong holds</hi> ſhall be like <hi>fig-trees</hi> with the <hi>firſt ripe figs,</hi> if they be <hi>ſhaken</hi> they ſhall even <hi>fall into the mouth of the eater. Behold,</hi> thy people in the midſt of thee <hi>are women,</hi> the gates of thy Land ſhall be <hi>ſet wide open</hi> unto thine enemies, the fire ſhall devour thy Bars. Draw the <hi>Waters</hi> for the <hi>Siege, fortifie</hi> thy <hi>ſtrong holds</hi> (with Demy Canon, <hi>&amp;c.)</hi> Go Into <hi>clay and tread morter,</hi> make ſtrong the <hi>Brick-kil,</hi> there ſhall the fire devour thee, it ſhall eat thee up as <hi>Canker<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worm,</hi> make thy ſelf many as the <hi>Canker-worm,</hi> make thy ſelf many as the <hi>Locuſt,</hi> yet for all this, before <hi>two years be expired,</hi> the Laws and ordinances of Jehovah the Lord Chriſt, ſhall be <hi>magnified</hi> and <hi>made Honourable in this Nation,</hi> and <hi>Idolatry</hi> and <hi>Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rany</hi> ſhall be <hi>extinguiſhed,</hi> even ſo <hi>Amen.</hi>
                     </q>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb facs="tcp:176196:40"/>
            <head>Poſtſcript.</head>
            <p>I Am deſired to give the <hi>people of God</hi> to underſtand, that the laſt <hi>news-book,</hi> publiſhed by one <hi>Walker</hi> an Ironmonger, and a no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious lying Pamphleter (and yet an <hi>approved Preacher</hi> by the <hi>High Court</hi> of <hi>Tyers,</hi> i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> lieu of his large obedience to the <hi>Beaſt</hi> now up) comprehended ſeventeen or eighteen large <hi>Lyes</hi> in four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen or fifteen <hi>Lines</hi> in his paſſages, relating to Mr. <hi>Rogers</hi> and the <hi>Members</hi> of his <hi>Society,</hi> which were lately ſent for to <hi>O. C.</hi> and that Mr. <hi>Rogers</hi> was ſo far from being put to ſilence by <hi>O. C.</hi> as <hi>Walker</hi> doth impudently aſſert, as that he gave a <hi>full,</hi> undenyable and <hi>pregnant Teſtimony,</hi> to the very faces of thoſe that are got into <hi>power,</hi> againſt the <hi>Apoſtacies</hi> of the <hi>Army,</hi> their Breach of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clarations, Blaſphemy, <hi>lying,</hi> perſecution <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>lf-ſee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing,</hi> and other <hi>crying ſinnes,</hi> proving that the now <hi>priſoners of the Lord,</hi> ſuffer for an <hi>eſſential truth,</hi> and fundamental point of faith, which Mr. <hi>Rogers</hi> challenged to diſpute with any man, upon even ground<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and that this lively, <hi>teſtimony</hi> was continued in the ſtrength of the <hi>anointing,</hi> to the very laſt, keeping and gaining <hi>C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ound</hi> upon the <hi>Antagoniſts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus much is thought meet at preſent to undeceive the <hi>people of God,</hi> in <hi>City</hi> and <hi>Countrey,</hi> untill the truth hereof do more largely <hi>appear.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>J. S.</signed>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:176196:41"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
